<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog</id>
    <title>Alvaro Lorente, Fractional CTO &amp; Founder Blog</title>
    <updated>2025-04-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Alvaro Lorente, Fractional CTO &amp; Founder Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://alvarolorente.dev/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <rights>Copyright © 2025 Alvaro Lorente</rights>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transforming Systems Operations Teams into a Unified Platform Team: The Cultural Change]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/30/T00:00:00.000Z-Transforming Systems Operations Teams into a Unified Platform Team: The Cultural Change</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/30/T00:00:00.000Z-Transforming Systems Operations Teams into a Unified Platform Team: The Cultural Change"/>
        <updated>2025-04-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over the last months, I've witnessed firsthand the transformation of my team from a basic operation provider to an internal service provider.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last months, I've witnessed firsthand the transformation of my team from a basic operation provider to an internal service provider.</p>
<p>In many organizations, systems operations teams are often segmented into specialized units such as DBA, backend operations, networking, etc. While this specialization ensures deep expertise and support to teams in complex situations. It also leads to inefficiencies as it focuses on the reactiveness to the needs of the teams &amp; company and not a proactive approach towards the same long-term needs due to the lack of common vision. It also has the drawback that enforces the dev vs ops culture and not a DevOps culture that has shown over and over again the positive effect on quality and speed of delivery of stream-aligned teams.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="devops-or-dev-vs-ops">’DevOps’ or ‘Dev vs Ops’<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/30/T00:00:00.000Z-Transforming%20Systems%20Operations%20Teams%20into%20a%20Unified%20Platform%20Team:%20The%20Cultural%20Change#devops-or-dev-vs-ops" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to ’DevOps’ or ‘Dev vs Ops’" title="Direct link to ’DevOps’ or ‘Dev vs Ops’">​</a></h2>
<p>Traditionally, Dev and Ops teams have operated in silos, each with their own distinct goals and priorities.</p>
<table><thead><tr><th></th><th>Focus</th><th><strong>Priorities</strong></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><strong>Dev Culture</strong></td><td>Development teams are primarily focused on creating new features, writing code, and ensuring the software meets user requirements.</td><td>Speed and innovation</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Ops Culture</strong></td><td>Operations teams are responsible for maintaining the stability, security, and performance of the software in production environments.</td><td>Reliability and uptime</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>This separation can lead to several challenges:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Communication Barriers:</strong>&nbsp;Lack of communication between Dev and Ops can result in misunderstandings and delays. Developers may not fully understand the operational constraints, while Ops may struggle with the rapid pace of development.</li>
<li><strong>Conflicting Goals:</strong>&nbsp;Developers prioritize speed and innovation, while Ops prioritize stability and reliability. These conflicting goals can create friction and hinder collaboration.</li>
<li><strong>Inefficiencies:</strong>&nbsp;Siloed teams often duplicate efforts and use different tools, leading to inefficiencies and wasted resources.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-devops-solution"><strong>The DevOps Solution</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/30/T00:00:00.000Z-Transforming%20Systems%20Operations%20Teams%20into%20a%20Unified%20Platform%20Team:%20The%20Cultural%20Change#the-devops-solution" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to the-devops-solution" title="Direct link to the-devops-solution">​</a></h2>
<p>The goal of DevOps is to create a culture of ownership to stream aligned teams to do development and operations, breaking down traditional silos and fostering a more integrated approach to software delivery. While the existing operations teams become a provider of abstractions that simplifies that work, reducing the cognitive load of operating the system.</p>
<p>This brings the next benefits:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enhanced Collaboration:</strong>&nbsp;Breaking down silos fosters a culture of collaboration, enabling teams to work together more effectively and share knowledge.</li>
<li><strong>Improved Efficiency:</strong>&nbsp;Streamlined workflows and standardized tools reduce redundancy and improve operational efficiency.</li>
<li><strong>Greater Innovation:</strong>&nbsp;A unified approach allows teams to quickly adapt to new technologies and methodologies, driving innovation and continuous improvement.</li>
<li><strong>Customer-Centric Approach:</strong>&nbsp;By aligning development and operations goals, teams can better understand and meet the needs of end-users, resulting in higher customer satisfaction.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-birth-of-the-platform-team">The Birth of the Platform Team<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/30/T00:00:00.000Z-Transforming%20Systems%20Operations%20Teams%20into%20a%20Unified%20Platform%20Team:%20The%20Cultural%20Change#the-birth-of-the-platform-team" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Birth of the Platform Team" title="Direct link to The Birth of the Platform Team">​</a></h2>
<p>A platform team acts as a service provider for all internal stream-aligned teams, offering essential tools, infrastructure, and support to streamline their work and enhance productivity. We could start enumerating systems and solutions that a platform team can own. But the reality is that would be the same as creating a product without doing any research on your clients.</p>
<p>To truly drive value within an organization, a platform team must deeply understand and address the needs of stream-aligned teams. These teams are directly responsible for delivering products and services to customers, and their success hinges on the support and resources provided by the platform team. Here’s how a platform team can effectively drive value by focusing on the needs of stream-aligned teams:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Active Engagement and Communication:</strong>&nbsp;work collaboratively with stream-aligned teams to develop solutions that address their specific pain points, fostering a sense of shared responsibility and mutual support.</li>
<li><strong>Continuous Improvement and Innovation:</strong>&nbsp;Implement iterative development practices to continuously refine and improve tools and services.</li>
<li><strong>Metrics and Performance Tracking:</strong>&nbsp;Establish key performance indicators (KPIs) to measure the effectiveness of the platform team’s support and use data-driven approaches to make informed decisions about resource allocation and process improvements.</li>
<li><strong>Empowerment and Autonomy:</strong>&nbsp;Develop self-service platforms that empower stream-aligned teams to manage their own resources and workflows, and provide comprehensive training and support to ensure proficiency in using the tools and services offered by the platform team.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>The key benefits this strategy tries to achieve are:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Efficiency:</strong>&nbsp;By centralizing infrastructure management, tooling, and support, the platform team reduces redundancy and improves operational efficiency. Stream-aligned teams can focus on delivering value to customers without worrying about underlying infrastructure.</li>
<li><strong>Consistency:</strong>&nbsp;Standardized tools and processes ensure consistency across the organization, making it easier to manage and scale applications.</li>
<li><strong>Reliability:</strong>&nbsp;A dedicated platform team ensures that the infrastructure is reliable and secure, minimizing downtime and enhancing the overall stability of applications.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/30/T00:00:00.000Z-Transforming%20Systems%20Operations%20Teams%20into%20a%20Unified%20Platform%20Team:%20The%20Cultural%20Change#closing-thoughts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Closing thoughts" title="Direct link to Closing thoughts">​</a></h2>
<p>By fostering a culture of ownership and collaboration, and by providing abstractions that simplify operations, the platform team can significantly reduce the cognitive load on stream-aligned teams. This transformation brings enhanced collaboration, improved efficiency, greater innovation, and a customer-centric approach, ultimately driving the success of the organization.</p>
<p>As we continue to evolve, the key to driving value lies in deeply understanding and addressing the needs of stream-aligned teams. Through active engagement, continuous improvement, metrics tracking, and empowerment, the platform team can ensure that stream-aligned teams are equipped to deliver exceptional products and services to our customers. This strategy not only centralizes infrastructure management and standardizes tools but also ensures reliability and consistency across the organization, paving the way for sustained growth and success.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Role of Transparency in Leadership: How You can Build Trust and Healthy Chains of Command]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/28/T06:00:00.000Z-The Role of Transparency in Leadership: How You can Build Trust and Healthy Chains of Command</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/28/T06:00:00.000Z-The Role of Transparency in Leadership: How You can Build Trust and Healthy Chains of Command"/>
        <updated>2025-04-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover why transparency is a cornerstone of effective leadership and how it contributes to a healthy chain of command. Learn how being open and honest with your team builds trust, fosters accountability, and enhances employee morale. Explore the importance of avoiding secrecy in strategic decisions to improve engagement and organizational performance. Embrace transparency to become a trusted and effective leader.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As someone who has spent years navigating the complexities of engineering leadership, I can tell you that transparency is one of the most critical elements of effective leadership. If you're aspiring to take on a leadership role, understanding the importance of transparency and how it contributes to a healthy chain of command is essential.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/f0f021ee-1928-4761-8864-9d2992de42b9/image.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB4667NHSBZZO%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115508Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJIMEYCIQD9to3uKVVkQLmoLUIA2bPBcwDtiPa6p%2FcroWa7eX1rxwIhAK99TsL8ZE0tozeB48uYo990gWYRDSVBuxyYUW7Ow0AvKogECNT%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEQABoMNjM3NDIzMTgzODA1IgwQdNMmozzhImGCSnUq3AN3y4o%2BV1sT4ZgeysCyaKrqIdzo9qsQaoiHFq1zTpT6saR9QO2RY3IPPpfuab6xf58LfrZYbL9AjMQEdZbMBQA%2FdnKrzxPeCOA%2FPqeUwhpSal1aq9GCKglfCjIcGkyyZJPPNqh6UkmgP1MJPI2VmX%2BaBbRavM8wplpGudxzBnbAgX6kB6AIu2A%2BiQ34CzPC5T5VE%2F2aFCXF8suWrgXZKhmtm8Sc4yBNS15qt4qOLgQsaKw3Oi1lqZixb0W91RffS0Z2A42PgDRXrF430MxXyietmnxdFNmNfDyUNFnq7Y8g2DCHFn7ESzGPq6mi%2BmmgD%2BbvhjfkPAW%2FwgQaIWDjcW4dNS92xDtcmt3G0yDkTDwZD5Z%2F0aw7a%2Fw8hBcPTp3rNTxp0Gn%2BbOzWzVj8uY%2F1%2BcZ7laVtXy%2Fb3ZLRLhS5WjC4Sen9SSWbThy2qbMISVxin1r89TTcFq0nvSJB3kz1BW10Dn7EE6tUQiK80xGdOzM3yQrmvHt5Xhq%2BOTHJlZ7m3KYzJPt3q%2FnSPag72Szs2yAeBh43pHsnl1Oi2EnKZWMtaxpVDiEh8BNdX99nepXUqFosgnWntPWqGUgPBAFBUA73V0Xfe4M54z5eiXliHg15ofQONgdTe4EJD0FWZzD4nK3EBjqkAdmS7BdzugaH0RZswP114eb09GXlStUahSMuGyYggLCXCpFQsld3tvZeyorNiD2m5BJKtO8ZO8uDQqOVJXV0TtKq%2BkdDKyjee092C0CY7VoWsqvhqA9jJiLfAAcRouB%2FHlZJ2n2izduaLRjvaEQt0QAFAyf7BFHoRl%2FL8p3gsbfhIAI8fBv%2F7r5voAKVsY2M3xLRnG%2B8IoFekxjTQkMTX6dUsgXJ&amp;X-Amz-Signature=93721462968a2990d25f4acc615fdfb7875f27b3ba88d01c07bcc37ead3dee83&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="image.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-transparency-matters"><strong>Why Transparency Matters</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/28/T06:00:00.000Z-The%20Role%20of%20Transparency%20in%20Leadership:%20How%20You%20can%20Build%20Trust%20and%20Healthy%20Chains%20of%20Command#why-transparency-matters" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to why-transparency-matters" title="Direct link to why-transparency-matters">​</a></h2>
<p>Transparency in leadership is about being open, honest, and straightforward with your team. It involves sharing information, explaining decisions, and being clear about expectations and goals. This openness builds trust, fosters a culture of accountability, and encourages open communication.</p>
<p>When leaders are transparent, they create an environment where team members feel valued and respected. They know that their leaders are not hiding anything from them and that they can rely on the information provided. This helps to:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Building Trust and Credibility:</strong> Trust is not something that can be demanded; it must be earned. By being transparent, you demonstrate integrity and honesty, which are crucial for building credibility.</li>
<li><strong>Encouraging Open Communication:</strong> When team members see that their leaders are open and honest, they are more likely to reciprocate. This creates a culture where everyone feels comfortable sharing their ideas, concerns, and feedback.</li>
<li><strong>Fostering Accountability:</strong> When you are open about your own performance and hold yourself accountable for your actions, you encourage your team to do the same. This culture of accountability leads to higher performance and continuous improvement.</li>
<li><strong>Enhancing Employee Morale and Engagement:</strong> Employees who work in a transparent environment are generally more satisfied and engaged. They appreciate knowing that their leaders are honest and forthcoming, which creates a sense of security and belonging. When employees feel informed and included in the decision-making process, they are more likely to be committed to the organization's mission and values.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="transparency-in-a-healthy-chain-of-command"><strong>Transparency in a Healthy Chain of Command</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/28/T06:00:00.000Z-The%20Role%20of%20Transparency%20in%20Leadership:%20How%20You%20can%20Build%20Trust%20and%20Healthy%20Chains%20of%20Command#transparency-in-a-healthy-chain-of-command" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to transparency-in-a-healthy-chain-of-command" title="Direct link to transparency-in-a-healthy-chain-of-command">​</a></h2>
<p>A healthy chain of command relies heavily on transparency. In a transparent organization, information flows freely up and down the hierarchy. Leaders at all levels are open about their decisions, goals, and challenges, which ensures that everyone is aligned and working towards the same objectives.</p>
<p>When transparency is lacking, it can lead to misunderstandings, mistrust, and a breakdown in communication. Team members may feel left out of the loop, leading to disengagement and decreased morale. On the other hand, a transparent chain of command fosters a sense of unity and collaboration, as everyone is aware of their roles and how they contribute to the organization's success.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-importance-of-avoiding-secrecy-in-strategic-decisions"><strong>The Importance of Avoiding Secrecy in Strategic Decisions</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/28/T06:00:00.000Z-The%20Role%20of%20Transparency%20in%20Leadership:%20How%20You%20can%20Build%20Trust%20and%20Healthy%20Chains%20of%20Command#the-importance-of-avoiding-secrecy-in-strategic-decisions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to the-importance-of-avoiding-secrecy-in-strategic-decisions" title="Direct link to the-importance-of-avoiding-secrecy-in-strategic-decisions">​</a></h2>
<p>While there are instances where strategic secrecy is necessary, it's equally important to recognize the potential downsides of keeping strategic decisions hidden from your team. Transparency in strategic decision-making can significantly enhance trust, engagement, and overall organizational performance.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/c4f8e2a4-13c8-4265-9de2-068dd8950a51/image.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB4667NHSBZZO%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115508Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJIMEYCIQD9to3uKVVkQLmoLUIA2bPBcwDtiPa6p%2FcroWa7eX1rxwIhAK99TsL8ZE0tozeB48uYo990gWYRDSVBuxyYUW7Ow0AvKogECNT%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEQABoMNjM3NDIzMTgzODA1IgwQdNMmozzhImGCSnUq3AN3y4o%2BV1sT4ZgeysCyaKrqIdzo9qsQaoiHFq1zTpT6saR9QO2RY3IPPpfuab6xf58LfrZYbL9AjMQEdZbMBQA%2FdnKrzxPeCOA%2FPqeUwhpSal1aq9GCKglfCjIcGkyyZJPPNqh6UkmgP1MJPI2VmX%2BaBbRavM8wplpGudxzBnbAgX6kB6AIu2A%2BiQ34CzPC5T5VE%2F2aFCXF8suWrgXZKhmtm8Sc4yBNS15qt4qOLgQsaKw3Oi1lqZixb0W91RffS0Z2A42PgDRXrF430MxXyietmnxdFNmNfDyUNFnq7Y8g2DCHFn7ESzGPq6mi%2BmmgD%2BbvhjfkPAW%2FwgQaIWDjcW4dNS92xDtcmt3G0yDkTDwZD5Z%2F0aw7a%2Fw8hBcPTp3rNTxp0Gn%2BbOzWzVj8uY%2F1%2BcZ7laVtXy%2Fb3ZLRLhS5WjC4Sen9SSWbThy2qbMISVxin1r89TTcFq0nvSJB3kz1BW10Dn7EE6tUQiK80xGdOzM3yQrmvHt5Xhq%2BOTHJlZ7m3KYzJPt3q%2FnSPag72Szs2yAeBh43pHsnl1Oi2EnKZWMtaxpVDiEh8BNdX99nepXUqFosgnWntPWqGUgPBAFBUA73V0Xfe4M54z5eiXliHg15ofQONgdTe4EJD0FWZzD4nK3EBjqkAdmS7BdzugaH0RZswP114eb09GXlStUahSMuGyYggLCXCpFQsld3tvZeyorNiD2m5BJKtO8ZO8uDQqOVJXV0TtKq%2BkdDKyjee092C0CY7VoWsqvhqA9jJiLfAAcRouB%2FHlZJ2n2izduaLRjvaEQt0QAFAyf7BFHoRl%2FL8p3gsbfhIAI8fBv%2F7r5voAKVsY2M3xLRnG%2B8IoFekxjTQkMTX6dUsgXJ&amp;X-Amz-Signature=7f69bfc4cefc7281b2f294d1221d5686f55aa8958fbe41724032bec35d5b3a82&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="image.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Here’s why avoiding secrecy in strategic decisions is crucial:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Enhancing Trust and Engagement:</strong> When leaders are transparent about strategic decisions, it builds trust within the team. Employees feel valued and respected when they are kept in the loop about the direction of the organization. This trust fosters a sense of ownership and commitment, leading to higher levels of engagement and motivation. Research has shown that organizations with high levels of trust and transparency tend to have more engaged employees, which directly correlates with improved performance and lower turnover rates.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Improving Decision Quality:</strong> Transparency in strategic decision-making encourages diverse perspectives and input from various levels of the organization. When employees are aware of the strategic direction and the reasons behind it, they can provide valuable insights and feedback that might not have been considered otherwise. This collaborative approach leads to more informed and well-rounded decisions, ultimately benefiting the organization.</p>
<p>For example, a study by Harvard Business Review found that companies that involve employees in strategic planning processes are more likely to achieve their goals and adapt to changes effectively. By avoiding secrecy, leaders can tap into the collective intelligence of their team, leading to better outcomes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Preventing Misinformation and Rumors:</strong> Secrecy can often lead to misinformation and rumors, which can be detrimental to organizational morale and cohesion. When employees are left in the dark, they may speculate and create their own narratives, which can lead to confusion and mistrust. By being transparent about strategic decisions, leaders can ensure that accurate information is disseminated, reducing the likelihood of rumors and fostering a more cohesive and informed team.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion"><strong>Conclusion</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2025/04/28/T06:00:00.000Z-The%20Role%20of%20Transparency%20in%20Leadership:%20How%20You%20can%20Build%20Trust%20and%20Healthy%20Chains%20of%20Command#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to conclusion" title="Direct link to conclusion">​</a></h3>
<p>In conclusion, transparency is a cornerstone of effective leadership and a healthy chain of command. By being open and honest, leaders can build trust, encourage open communication, foster accountability, enhance employee morale, and drive organizational success. As you aspire to take on leadership roles, remember that transparency is not just a strategy; it's a commitment to creating a positive and thriving workplace culture.</p>
<p>Embrace transparency, and you'll be well on your way to becoming a trusted and effective leader.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Job Trial Period: A Two Way Street For Success]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/09/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Job Trial Period: A Two Way Street For Success</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/09/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Job Trial Period: A Two Way Street For Success"/>
        <updated>2024-09-26T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover how job trial periods benefit both employers and employees. Learn to maximize this evaluation time for mutual success and informed decision-making.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Dear readers, I am back. I apologize for the hiatus, it has been a few “interesting” months in my life that have made me reflect a lot on some topics that before I thought were trivial, and one-sided. I will try to share some thoughts over the next few posts. So let's start with a subject that is really fresh in my mind, as it's what has been affecting me over the last few months.</p>
<p>To the question “During your career, did to pass a Job trial period?” the most common answer will be “Yes”. Traditionally, it is viewed as a tool for employers to evaluate potential hires, nevertheless it's crucial to recognize that these periods serve a dual purpose. They are, in fact, a two-way street that benefits both employers and employees alike.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-is-in-for-us">What is in for Us?<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/09/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Job%20Trial%20Period:%20A%20Two%20Way%20Street%20For%20Success#what-is-in-for-us" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is in for Us?" title="Direct link to What is in for Us?">​</a></h2>
<p>The trial period is an evaluation period, it can even be seen as an extension of the interview process, as you will never get to know a person you will spend most of your awake workday day with.</p>
<p>With this in mind, the same as in interview, we need to remember is not a one-sided evaluation, Employers should evaluate ROI &amp; employees should evaluate company fitness.</p>
<p>From an <strong>employer's standpoint</strong>, trial periods offer several advantages:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Skill Assessment:</strong> Employers can evaluate a candidate's practical skills and how they apply their knowledge in real-world scenarios.</li>
<li><strong>Cultural Fit:</strong> It provides an opportunity to assess how well the new hire integrates with the existing team and company culture.</li>
<li><strong>Performance Evaluation:</strong> Employers can gauge the employee's productivity, work ethic, and ability to meet deadlines.</li>
<li><strong>Risk Mitigation:</strong> If the employee doesn't meet expectations, the company can part ways with minimal legal and financial implications.</li>
</ul>
<p>Equally important, but often overlooked, is the <strong>employee's perspective</strong> on trial periods:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Company Culture Experience:</strong> Employees can immerse themselves in the company culture and determine if it aligns with their values and work style.</li>
<li><strong>Job Satisfaction Assessment:</strong> It allows individuals to evaluate if the role meets their expectations and career aspirations.</li>
<li><strong>Team Dynamics:</strong> Employees can assess how well they work with their colleagues and immediate supervisors.</li>
<li><strong>Work-Life Balance:</strong> The trial period offers insight into the company's approach to work-life balance and flexibility</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="maximizing-the-trial-period">Maximizing the Trial Period<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/09/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Job%20Trial%20Period:%20A%20Two%20Way%20Street%20For%20Success#maximizing-the-trial-period" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Maximizing the Trial Period" title="Direct link to Maximizing the Trial Period">​</a></h2>
<p>To make the most of a job trial period, both parties should approach it with openness and clear communication:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Set Clear Expectations:</strong> Employers should outline specific goals and performance metrics for the trial period.</li>
<li><strong>Regular Feedback:</strong> Implement a system for frequent, two-way feedback to address concerns and acknowledge progress.</li>
<li><strong>Encourage Questions:</strong> Create an environment where the new hire feels comfortable asking questions and seeking clarification.</li>
<li><strong>Provide Necessary Resources:</strong> Ensure the employee has all the tools and information needed to perform their job effectively.</li>
</ul>
<p>To achieve this, we need to use the correct tools for the job</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="onboarding-plan">Onboarding Plan<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/09/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Job%20Trial%20Period:%20A%20Two%20Way%20Street%20For%20Success#onboarding-plan" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Onboarding Plan" title="Direct link to Onboarding Plan">​</a></h3>
<p>An effective onboarding plan should contain:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Comprehensive introduction:</strong> Include an overview of the company's culture, policies, and procedures.</li>
<li><strong>Role-specific training:</strong> Provide training tailored to the new employee's specific job responsibilities.</li>
<li><strong>Introduction to team and colleagues:</strong> Facilitate meetings with team members and key personnel.</li>
<li><strong>Resource provision:</strong> Ensure the employee has all necessary tools and information to perform their job effectively.</li>
<li><strong>Assign a buddy</strong>: pair the employee with a more experienced colleague who can provide informal guidance and support that can help navigate the day-to-day aspects of the job.</li>
<li><strong>Assign a mentor</strong>: pair the employee mentor is usually a more senior employee who can provide guidance, share industry insights, and help them grow in their role over a longer period.</li>
<li><strong>Regular feedback sessions:</strong> as a manager, schedule frequent check-ins to address concerns and acknowledge progress.</li>
</ul>
<p>A well-structured onboarding plan helps new employees quickly integrate into their roles and the organization, reducing the learning curve and increasing productivity during the trial period.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="30-60-90-plan">30-60-90 Plan<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/09/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Job%20Trial%20Period:%20A%20Two%20Way%20Street%20For%20Success#30-60-90-plan" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 30-60-90 Plan" title="Direct link to 30-60-90 Plan">​</a></h3>
<p>A 30-60-90 plan is a strategic framework used for onboarding new employees or setting goals for the first 90 days in a new role. It breaks down objectives and expectations into three distinct periods:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>30 days:</strong> Focus on learning and understanding the role, company culture, and immediate responsibilities.</li>
<li><strong>60 days:</strong> Begin contributing more actively, implementing initial strategies, and identifying areas for improvement.</li>
<li><strong>90 days:</strong> Fully integrate into the role, start driving results, and propose long-term strategies or improvements.</li>
</ul>
<p>This plan helps structure the transition period, ensuring clear expectations and measurable progress for both the employee and the employer during the trial period, with a framework that can help focus the feedback and</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="evaluation-of-the-outcome-of-a-trial-period">Evaluation of the outcome of a trial period<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/09/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Job%20Trial%20Period:%20A%20Two%20Way%20Street%20For%20Success#evaluation-of-the-outcome-of-a-trial-period" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Evaluation of the outcome of a trial period" title="Direct link to Evaluation of the outcome of a trial period">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="pass">Pass<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/09/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Job%20Trial%20Period:%20A%20Two%20Way%20Street%20For%20Success#pass" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Pass" title="Direct link to Pass">​</a></h3>
<p>When a trial period results in a successful outcome, it's important to celebrate this achievement. Both the employer and employee should acknowledge the positive experience and use it as a foundation for future growth.</p>
<p>This is an opportunity to set new goals, discuss career development plans, and reinforce the mutual commitment to success. A successful trial period can lead to increased motivation, job satisfaction, and a stronger sense of belonging within the organization.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="no-pass-by-employer">No Pass by Employer<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/09/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Job%20Trial%20Period:%20A%20Two%20Way%20Street%20For%20Success#no-pass-by-employer" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to No Pass by Employer" title="Direct link to No Pass by Employer">​</a></h3>
<p>If an employer decides not to continue the employment relationship after the trial period, it's crucial to handle the situation professionally and sensitively.</p>
<p>The employer should provide clear, constructive feedback about why the trial was unsuccessful, focusing on the root cause without personal criticisms. This feedback can be valuable for the employee's future career development.</p>
<p>Additionally, the employer should ensure all legal and contractual obligations are met, including any notice periods or severance pay if applicable. Treating the departing employee with respect and dignity during this process is not only ethical, but also maintains the company's reputation as a fair employer.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="no-pass-by-employee">No Pass by Employee<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/09/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Job%20Trial%20Period:%20A%20Two%20Way%20Street%20For%20Success#no-pass-by-employee" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to No Pass by Employee" title="Direct link to No Pass by Employee">​</a></h3>
<p>When an employee decides not to continue after the trial period, it's equally important to handle the situation professionally.</p>
<p>The employee should provide honest feedback about their experience, highlighting any misalignment or concerns that led to their decision. This feedback can be valuable for the employer to improve their onboarding process or workplace environment.</p>
<p>The employee should also ensure they fulfill any contractual obligations, such as providing proper notice.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/09/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Job%20Trial%20Period:%20A%20Two%20Way%20Street%20For%20Success#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>Job trial periods are an opportunity for both parties to evaluate the potential for a long-term, mutually beneficial relationship. By approaching these periods with transparency, open communication, and a willingness to learn, both employers and employees can make informed decisions about their future together.</p>
<p>This period should not be demonized, even if it ends in a “No Pass”, it should be taken as a good outcome as it's a relationship that would have most probably failed, or would create friction and other risks down the road when legal obligation from both sides are more complex.
If you're the employee, remember this is not a failure. Your worth remains unchanged—it simply wasn't the right fit or timing. If you're the employer, don't be too hard on yourself. Not all relationships work out. The best approach is to move forward and end things on the best terms possible.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rethinking Technical Tasks: Define any task as user value]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/31/T22:00:00.000Z-Rethinking Technical Tasks: Define any task as user value</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/31/T22:00:00.000Z-Rethinking Technical Tasks: Define any task as user value"/>
        <updated>2024-07-31T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover how to eliminate the divide between technical and product tasks in your development team. Learn strategies for a unified approach to task management that enhances product quality, efficiency, and team collaboration.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever considered the various types of tasks within a team? Why do we often separate tasks into 'technical' and 'product' categories? Is this division a reality, or is it simply a reflection of our difficulty in articulating the value of non-functional behavior?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-current-concept-of-technical-task">The Current Concept of Technical Task<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/31/T22:00:00.000Z-Rethinking%20Technical%20Tasks:%20Define%20any%20task%20as%20user%20value#the-current-concept-of-technical-task" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Current Concept of Technical Task" title="Direct link to The Current Concept of Technical Task">​</a></h2>
<p>Technical tasks are typically considered those that involve the underlying work on non-functional related endeavors. These can include activities like updating dependencies, improving performance, etc.
While they may not always have a direct visible impact on the end user, In reality, almost every task a development team undertakes has some level of impact on the product. Even tasks perceived as purely technical, such as improving code quality or optimizing performance, ultimately contribute to a better user experience and product reliability.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="understanding-the-net-value-of-tasks">Understanding the Net Value of Tasks<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/31/T22:00:00.000Z-Rethinking%20Technical%20Tasks:%20Define%20any%20task%20as%20user%20value#understanding-the-net-value-of-tasks" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Understanding the Net Value of Tasks" title="Direct link to Understanding the Net Value of Tasks">​</a></h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Any team effort needs to have a clear purpose, whether it's technical or product-related.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>IIf we approach our work with the previous quote in mind, any endeavor a team undertakes should yield a positive return on investment. Let's express this value as a simple formula:</p>
<p>$ = Value - Cost</p>
<p>where:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Value</strong>: The benefit or worth that a task or project brings to the organization, often measured in terms of revenue.</li>
<li><strong>Cost</strong>: The amount of resources, including time, money, and effort, required to complete a task or project.</li>
</ul>
<p>It's normally simpler to calculate the expected value of functional tasks because their impact on user experience and business metrics is more direct and measurable. However, even technical tasks, when evaluated through this lens, can reveal significant contributions to the product's overall value.</p>
<p>The benefit we will achieve from this approach is a more cohesive and efficient development process, where all tasks are recognized for their contribution to the product's success. This integrated approach to task management allows for more strategic prioritization. When all tasks are evaluated based on their potential impact on the product, teams can make more informed decisions about where to allocate their resources. This can result in more timely delivery of features and improvements, better risk management, and a more adaptable development process.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="example-of-task-calculations">Example of Task Calculations<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/31/T22:00:00.000Z-Rethinking%20Technical%20Tasks:%20Define%20any%20task%20as%20user%20value#example-of-task-calculations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Example of Task Calculations" title="Direct link to Example of Task Calculations">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="functional-task-adding-a-new-feature">Functional Task: Adding a New Feature<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/31/T22:00:00.000Z-Rethinking%20Technical%20Tasks:%20Define%20any%20task%20as%20user%20value#functional-task-adding-a-new-feature" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Functional Task: Adding a New Feature" title="Direct link to Functional Task: Adding a New Feature">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Task</strong>: Implement a new user login feature.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Value</strong>: This feature is expected to increase user sign-ups by 5%, leading to an estimated increase in revenue of $5,000 per month.</li>
<li><strong>Cost</strong>: The development team estimates that it will take a week to complete this task (around 40 hours). Assuming an average hourly rate of $50, the total cost is $2,000.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>$ Value Calculation</strong>:
$ = Value - Cost</p>
<p>$ = $5,000 - $2,000</p>
<p>$ = $3,000 per month</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="non-functional-task-performance-improvements">Non-Functional Task: Performance Improvements<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/31/T22:00:00.000Z-Rethinking%20Technical%20Tasks:%20Define%20any%20task%20as%20user%20value#non-functional-task-performance-improvements" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Non-Functional Task: Performance Improvements" title="Direct link to Non-Functional Task: Performance Improvements">​</a></h3>
<p><strong>Task</strong>: Optimize the application's performance to reduce load times and enhance user experience.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Value</strong>: Faster load times are expected to improve user retention by 15%, leading to an estimated increase in paid users and an additional revenue of $7,000 per month.</li>
<li><strong>Cost</strong>: The development team estimates that it will take 50 hours to complete this task. Assuming an average hourly rate of $50, the total cost is $2,500.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>$ Value Calculation</strong>:
$ = Value - Cost</p>
<p>$ = $7,000 - $2,500</p>
<p>$ = $4,500 per month</p>
<p>With these examples in mind, it makes more sense to start with performance improvements and not working on the functional task.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="embrace-a-unified-approach-to-task-management">Embrace a Unified Approach to Task Management<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/31/T22:00:00.000Z-Rethinking%20Technical%20Tasks:%20Define%20any%20task%20as%20user%20value#embrace-a-unified-approach-to-task-management" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Embrace a Unified Approach to Task Management" title="Direct link to Embrace a Unified Approach to Task Management">​</a></h2>
<p>To truly integrate technical and product tasks, teams should adopt a unified approach to task management. This involves recognizing that every task, no matter how technical it may seem, plays a crucial role in the overall product vision. Here are some additional strategies to ensure this integration:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Unified Backlog</strong>: Maintain a single backlog that includes both product features and technical tasks. This ensures that all tasks are visible to the entire team and can be prioritized based on their overall impact on the product.</li>
<li><strong>Cross-functional Teams</strong>: Foster cross-functional teams where developers, product managers, and other stakeholders work closely together. This can help bridge the gap between technical and product perspectives, leading to more informed decision-making.</li>
<li><strong>Regular Reviews</strong>: Conduct regular reviews of the backlog and ongoing tasks to ensure that technical debt is being addressed, and that product features are aligned with technical improvements.</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/31/T22:00:00.000Z-Rethinking%20Technical%20Tasks:%20Define%20any%20task%20as%20user%20value#final-thoughts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Final Thoughts" title="Direct link to Final Thoughts">​</a></h2>
<p>In conclusion, the distinction between technical and product tasks is often more conceptual than practical. By recognizing the interdependence of these tasks and integrating them into a unified development process, teams can enhance both product quality and development efficiency. It's time to stop segregating tasks and start viewing them as integral parts of a cohesive product development strategy. This holistic approach will improve the end product and foster a more collaborative and productive team environment.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Improving Mental Health at Work: Strategies for a Healthier Workplace]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/25/T22:00:00.000Z-Improving Mental Health at Work: Strategies for a Healthier Workplace</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/25/T22:00:00.000Z-Improving Mental Health at Work: Strategies for a Healthier Workplace"/>
        <updated>2024-07-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover essential strategies to enhance mental health in the workplace. Learn how to balance workloads, foster a supportive culture, and implement practical tips for both organizations and individuals to maintain well-being and productivity.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, we discussed the importance of managing 100% utilization within the team to maintain their well-being. As individuals, we each react differently to experiences, which can have long-term consequences.</p>
<p>You may have noticed that I haven't been writing as frequently as I would like. I feel bad about this, but I was overwhelmed from overworking in multiple areas. Had this continued without any action, I might have faced significant burnout. So, let's talk today about mental health at work.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-is-mental-health--why-is-it-important">What is Mental Health &amp; Why is it Important<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/25/T22:00:00.000Z-Improving%20Mental%20Health%20at%20Work:%20Strategies%20for%20a%20Healthier%20Workplace#what-is-mental-health--why-is-it-important" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is Mental Health &amp; Why is it Important" title="Direct link to What is Mental Health &amp; Why is it Important">​</a></h2>
<p>Mental health goes beyond the absence of mental illness; it includes our overall emotional, psychological, and social well-being. It affects how we think, feel, and act, influencing our ability to manage stress, relate to others, and make decisions. Understanding and prioritizing mental health is crucial for maintaining a productive and positive work environment.</p>
<p>We typically spend 50% of our waking hours at work, this is why work can significantly impact our mental health.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="evaluating-mental-health">Evaluating Mental Health<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/25/T22:00:00.000Z-Improving%20Mental%20Health%20at%20Work:%20Strategies%20for%20a%20Healthier%20Workplace#evaluating-mental-health" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Evaluating Mental Health" title="Direct link to Evaluating Mental Health">​</a></h2>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="self">Self<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/25/T22:00:00.000Z-Improving%20Mental%20Health%20at%20Work:%20Strategies%20for%20a%20Healthier%20Workplace#self" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Self" title="Direct link to Self">​</a></h2>
<p>It's important to regularly assess your own mental health. Reflect on how you're feeling, both physically and emotionally. While this can be challenging, several tools and methods can help:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Journaling</strong>: Keeping a daily journal of your thoughts, feelings, and experiences can help you identify patterns and triggers of stress or anxiety.</li>
<li><strong>Mood Tracking</strong>: Apps or simple paper-based mood trackers can help you monitor your mood over time and notice any significant changes.</li>
<li><strong>Online Assessments</strong>: Various websites offer self-assessment tools that provide insights into your mental health status. These assessments often cover areas like stress, anxiety, and depression.</li>
<li><strong>Physical Health Monitoring</strong>: Since mental and physical health are closely linked, tracking physical symptoms like sleep patterns, appetite, and energy levels can provide clues about your mental health.</li>
<li><strong>Professional Help</strong>: Regular check-ins with a mental health professional, even when you're feeling okay, can offer valuable insights and support.</li>
</ol>
<p>Using these tools regularly can help you stay in tune with your mental health and take proactive steps to address any issues that arise.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="others">Others<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/25/T22:00:00.000Z-Improving%20Mental%20Health%20at%20Work:%20Strategies%20for%20a%20Healthier%20Workplace#others" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Others" title="Direct link to Others">​</a></h3>
<p>As leaders, it's equally important to recognize signs of burnout and stress in others. Here are some indicators to watch out for:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Decreased Productivity</strong>: Noticeable decline in work output.</li>
<li><strong>Increased Absenteeism</strong>: Frequent sick days or unexplained absences.</li>
<li><strong>Changes in Behavior</strong>: Irritability, mood swings, or withdrawal from team activities.</li>
<li><strong>Physical Symptoms</strong>: Complaints of headaches, fatigue, or other stress-related ailments.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of Engagement</strong>: Disinterest in work or decreased enthusiasm for projects.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="factors-that-affect-mental-health-at-work">Factors That Affect Mental Health At Work<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/25/T22:00:00.000Z-Improving%20Mental%20Health%20at%20Work:%20Strategies%20for%20a%20Healthier%20Workplace#factors-that-affect-mental-health-at-work" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Factors That Affect Mental Health At Work" title="Direct link to Factors That Affect Mental Health At Work">​</a></h2>
<p>Several factors can significantly affect mental health in the workplace, and it’s essential to recognize these to create a supportive environment for everyone on the team. Here are some of the key factors:</p>
<ul>
<li>Workload and Stress: Excessive workload and high levels of stress are common contributors to poor mental health. When employees are consistently overwhelmed with tasks and responsibilities, it can lead to burnout, anxiety, and decreased productivity.</li>
<li>Work-Life Balance: A lack of work-life balance can negatively impact mental health. When work encroaches on personal time, it can lead to stress, fatigue, and strained relationships. It’s crucial for organizations to promote a healthy balance between work and personal life.</li>
<li>Job Security: Uncertainty about job security can cause significant stress and anxiety. Concerns about layoffs, contract renewals, or organizational changes can create an environment of fear and instability.</li>
<li>Workplace Relationships: The quality of relationships with colleagues and supervisors can greatly influence mental health. Positive, supportive interactions can enhance well-being, while toxic or unsupportive relationships can lead to stress and dissatisfaction.</li>
<li>Organizational Culture: A company's culture plays a vital role in mental health. A culture that values mental well-being, provides support, and encourages open communication can help mitigate stress and improve overall morale.</li>
<li>Recognition and Reward: Feeling undervalued or unrecognized for contributions can negatively impact mental health. Regular acknowledgment and reward for hard work and accomplishments can boost morale and motivation.</li>
<li>Physical Environment: The physical work environment, including factors like noise levels, lighting, and ergonomics, can affect mental well-being. A comfortable and conducive workspace can enhance productivity and reduce stress.</li>
<li>Change Management: How changes are managed within an organization can impact mental health. Poorly communicated or managed changes can create uncertainty and stress, while transparent and supportive change management can ease transitions.</li>
<li>Personal Factors: Personal issues such as financial concerns, health problems, or family responsibilities can also impact mental health at work. It’s important for organizations to be aware of and sensitive to these external factors.</li>
<li>Team Dynamics: The dynamics within a team can greatly influence individual mental health. A collaborative, cohesive team can provide support and reduce stress, while a dysfunctional team can create additional pressure and conflict.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="strategies-to-improve-mental-health">Strategies to Improve Mental Health<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/25/T22:00:00.000Z-Improving%20Mental%20Health%20at%20Work:%20Strategies%20for%20a%20Healthier%20Workplace#strategies-to-improve-mental-health" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Strategies to Improve Mental Health" title="Direct link to Strategies to Improve Mental Health">​</a></h2>
<p>Addressing mental health in the workplace requires a multifaceted approach. Here are some strategies that can help create a healthier work environment:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="organizational-strategies">Organizational Strategies<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/25/T22:00:00.000Z-Improving%20Mental%20Health%20at%20Work:%20Strategies%20for%20a%20Healthier%20Workplace#organizational-strategies" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Organizational Strategies" title="Direct link to Organizational Strategies">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Promote Work-Life Balance</strong>: Encourage employees to take regular breaks, use their vacation days, and disconnect after work hours. Flexible work schedules can also help employees manage their personal and professional responsibilities more effectively.</li>
<li><strong>Foster a Supportive Culture</strong>: Create a culture where mental health is openly discussed and supported. Encourage leaders to model healthy behaviors and provide training on recognizing and addressing mental health issues.</li>
<li><strong>Provide Resources</strong>: Offer access to mental health resources such as Employee Assistance Programs, counseling services, and stress management workshops. Make sure employees know how to access these resources.</li>
<li><strong>Manage Workload</strong>: Ensure that workloads are reasonable and that employees have the resources they need to complete their tasks. Regularly check in with team members to assess their workload and make adjustments as needed.</li>
<li><strong>Encourage Social Connections</strong>: Foster a sense of community within the workplace. Encourage team-building activities, social events, and opportunities for employees to connect on a personal level.</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="individual-strategies">Individual Strategies<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/25/T22:00:00.000Z-Improving%20Mental%20Health%20at%20Work:%20Strategies%20for%20a%20Healthier%20Workplace#individual-strategies" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Individual Strategies" title="Direct link to Individual Strategies">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Set Boundaries</strong>: Clearly define your work hours and stick to them. Avoid checking emails or working outside your designated work time.</li>
<li><strong>Practice Self-Care</strong>: Engage in activities that help you relax and recharge. This could include exercise, meditation, hobbies, or spending time with loved ones.</li>
<li><strong>Seek Support</strong>: Don’t hesitate to reach out for help if you’re struggling. Talk to a trusted colleague, supervisor, or mental health professional.</li>
<li><strong>Stay Organized</strong>: Use tools like to-do lists, calendars, and project management software to keep track of your tasks and deadlines. This can help reduce feelings of overwhelm.</li>
<li><strong>Take Breaks</strong>: Regular breaks throughout the day can help you stay focused and reduce stress. Even a short walk or a few minutes of deep breathing can make a big difference.</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="closing-words">Closing Words<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/07/25/T22:00:00.000Z-Improving%20Mental%20Health%20at%20Work:%20Strategies%20for%20a%20Healthier%20Workplace#closing-words" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Closing Words" title="Direct link to Closing Words">​</a></h2>
<p>Mental health is a crucial aspect of overall well-being and productivity in the workplace. By recognizing the factors that affect mental health and implementing strategies to address them, we can create a supportive and healthy work environment. Remember, prioritizing mental health benefits not only individuals but also the entire organization. It’s okay to take a step back, evaluate your well-being, and make necessary adjustments. Your mental health matters.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Boosting Success in Engineering Changes: The Power of Patience & Alignment]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Boosting Success in Engineering Changes: The Power of Patience &amp; Alignment</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Boosting Success in Engineering Changes: The Power of Patience &amp; Alignment"/>
        <updated>2024-06-26T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore how patience and knowledge alignment can enhance the success rate of implementing new methodologies in engineering departments. Understand the role of culture, transparent communication, and leadership in fostering change.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ever found yourself in engineering departments where tools and practices are adopted and discarded rapidly?</p>
<p>One example that might resonate are companies that try to implement their goals through OKRs. Typically, the first year doesn't yield substantial value, leading to a gradual disregard in the second year. Before the close of year two, a new acronym supersedes the existing goal definition, setting off yet another cycle.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/3816ad44-52a9-4057-83c7-faac3b9e61b8/ep1.jpg?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466TXZD6IVJ%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115508Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIQDvuCKEP3jbPBLQKeIqfmBx%2BxDHFunROfLcgrcQxLVcggIgaYVv7%2F%2B%2FdQ5e273qo6VHVywHCynoag3vTRLvAZHlPL8qiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDDdLQn5J9BdoE4dl%2ByrcA%2FbYycgT52TKq%2BS2vuQvC4CNUK4UG3VRz3%2F%2BNkY23ymVvham7lQ1MKoZqEgudSJ9cSLqTsk01pzqTqhQiXKAMrSqcUx5W1uBj0MVAHjCU9SA0%2BEz%2FheffdvBN7luSAcZfuScSlnlHlZW9MXv6fBCbUZF1Unx6aFKefUWxA2JlvLq2%2B%2F0W31yUyR5EuMlrEu1XaDY6e%2Bo4SZZK0feHrE9RqQD6ObAs35a0tD9GCsi0XMTciMKgAd6%2Fs6qzkmrc%2BQbU7u9IEJZH5wa9wJc8aLKFp8t6cQBNcTNMk6DMxAcsBW5DNLVZ4NIf0igDX6%2FdBX%2F2tZgieNEhVKa4DxUY2oaFEdbmBcaJcEhKVFWlZPUqIQaeD0smw%2F77MKF9F84VIlhvwJbCjz6XKHemt7mMi2Y%2FK1fW2fBGF9IBO4Utx6MaIX1RqiCbOvYCmV9E2194OPxNGSUU0GKJBUBXCiycKEGRjyfiF%2FdlGwtEW%2F7PafkzT%2FOYJNtYyIwT4TwuFdEtBwA4oNHT12nwZb8haLEmI3ymWFER5eeRoL7SUVPRqyZ7e9f87bfUl%2BNJtwXR%2Bvy6eOeuu10Gs0lXrP1ya7yEO6wPvo4HXpkPRtNJ37KZQ3MEQd0vjXfjoGjZXys0tLQMMmdrcQGOqUBUKi12VFvcAfjhKJ2DYrU64jASEXhOq6Gt%2Fg%2FAEf9SkNAJ8wuGhsVOAcmcA2TqCghK0isXlGdu3R%2F20ayJXTM20xa1ntbjR%2FFkWoS%2BOe02GhL%2BwkIL4sR1ibN%2F%2BFRPIxfa%2F2ZFrnbV0OzK7aGWboMTYGwN7dA78gaJaOqmjHGYpiSaChdOjDUl7xu8BEApX4linsSfdfewwhJkMPBAE4LvpOQX%2Bis&amp;X-Amz-Signature=9f140f9726439b44697da47b8f577b843c7751aa7b510c81c462e7e22328afdd&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="ep1.jpg" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="understanding-why-new-methodology-implementations-often-fall-short">Understanding Why New Methodology Implementations Often Fall Short<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Boosting%20Success%20in%20Engineering%20Changes:%20The%20Power%20of%20Patience%20&amp;%20Alignment#understanding-why-new-methodology-implementations-often-fall-short" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Understanding Why New Methodology Implementations Often Fall Short" title="Direct link to Understanding Why New Methodology Implementations Often Fall Short">​</a></h2>
<p>Whether we're discussing company-wide methodologies like OKRs or team-specific practices like pair programming, it's common to see implementations fall short. Often, methodologies bear the brunt of the blame due to misalignment.</p>
<p>Let's delve into the reasons behind these failures, and assess whether the methodology itself is at fault.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Difficulty in Tracking Results</strong>: When new methods are introduced, it's often challenging to see immediate results or advantages. This can lead to premature rejection of the new approach.</li>
<li><strong>Insufficient Engagement</strong>: This covers situations where members aren't entirely on board with the new process. This could stem from inadequate understanding, disagreement with the methodology, or simple resistance to change.</li>
</ul>
<p>While there are other reasons for failure, they typically fall under or relate closely to these main points.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="boosting-success-rates-via-engineering-culture">Boosting Success Rates via Engineering Culture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Boosting%20Success%20in%20Engineering%20Changes:%20The%20Power%20of%20Patience%20&amp;%20Alignment#boosting-success-rates-via-engineering-culture" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Boosting Success Rates via Engineering Culture" title="Direct link to Boosting Success Rates via Engineering Culture">​</a></h2>
<p>As we've previously discussed, enhancing the success rate of engineering changes hinges on shifts in the following cultural aspects:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="patience">Patience<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Boosting%20Success%20in%20Engineering%20Changes:%20The%20Power%20of%20Patience%20&amp;%20Alignment#patience" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Patience" title="Direct link to Patience">​</a></h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Remember, results take time</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To foster patience within the engineering department, it's essential that the company culture not only values it, but actively encourages it. Here's how:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Celebrate Patience</strong>: Recognize and reward patience in your workspace. This could involve acknowledging those who demonstrate patience when faced with challenges, or associating rewards and promotions with the successful long-term execution of changes.</li>
<li><strong>Highlight the Role of Patience</strong>: Keep reminding your people about the crucial role patience plays in long-term success. Share anecdotes or instances where patience has proven beneficial in the past.</li>
<li><strong>Lead by Example</strong>: Leadership should portray patience in their actions and decision-making. This means resisting the urge to follow the latest trends without adequate evaluation, and allowing new processes sufficient time to integrate and yield results.</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/bbd1c363-b3fc-484c-8d7d-2c8df4994176/patience.jpg?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466TXZD6IVJ%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115508Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIQDvuCKEP3jbPBLQKeIqfmBx%2BxDHFunROfLcgrcQxLVcggIgaYVv7%2F%2B%2FdQ5e273qo6VHVywHCynoag3vTRLvAZHlPL8qiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDDdLQn5J9BdoE4dl%2ByrcA%2FbYycgT52TKq%2BS2vuQvC4CNUK4UG3VRz3%2F%2BNkY23ymVvham7lQ1MKoZqEgudSJ9cSLqTsk01pzqTqhQiXKAMrSqcUx5W1uBj0MVAHjCU9SA0%2BEz%2FheffdvBN7luSAcZfuScSlnlHlZW9MXv6fBCbUZF1Unx6aFKefUWxA2JlvLq2%2B%2F0W31yUyR5EuMlrEu1XaDY6e%2Bo4SZZK0feHrE9RqQD6ObAs35a0tD9GCsi0XMTciMKgAd6%2Fs6qzkmrc%2BQbU7u9IEJZH5wa9wJc8aLKFp8t6cQBNcTNMk6DMxAcsBW5DNLVZ4NIf0igDX6%2FdBX%2F2tZgieNEhVKa4DxUY2oaFEdbmBcaJcEhKVFWlZPUqIQaeD0smw%2F77MKF9F84VIlhvwJbCjz6XKHemt7mMi2Y%2FK1fW2fBGF9IBO4Utx6MaIX1RqiCbOvYCmV9E2194OPxNGSUU0GKJBUBXCiycKEGRjyfiF%2FdlGwtEW%2F7PafkzT%2FOYJNtYyIwT4TwuFdEtBwA4oNHT12nwZb8haLEmI3ymWFER5eeRoL7SUVPRqyZ7e9f87bfUl%2BNJtwXR%2Bvy6eOeuu10Gs0lXrP1ya7yEO6wPvo4HXpkPRtNJ37KZQ3MEQd0vjXfjoGjZXys0tLQMMmdrcQGOqUBUKi12VFvcAfjhKJ2DYrU64jASEXhOq6Gt%2Fg%2FAEf9SkNAJ8wuGhsVOAcmcA2TqCghK0isXlGdu3R%2F20ayJXTM20xa1ntbjR%2FFkWoS%2BOe02GhL%2BwkIL4sR1ibN%2F%2BFRPIxfa%2F2ZFrnbV0OzK7aGWboMTYGwN7dA78gaJaOqmjHGYpiSaChdOjDUl7xu8BEApX4linsSfdfewwhJkMPBAE4LvpOQX%2Bis&amp;X-Amz-Signature=b74c5099333a92fe4b484f49bdb63e762659e2154eb010bf7b04ced6a4b41520&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="patience.jpg" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="aligning-knowledge">Aligning Knowledge<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Boosting%20Success%20in%20Engineering%20Changes:%20The%20Power%20of%20Patience%20&amp;%20Alignment#aligning-knowledge" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Aligning Knowledge" title="Direct link to Aligning Knowledge">​</a></h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Teamwork makes the dream work.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To effectively share knowledge throughout the engineering department, it's essential that our company culture actively supports and fosters it. This includes:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Transparent communication</strong>: It's crucial for everyone to understand why we're making changes and what we should anticipate. A thorough explanation of the process, timeline, potential challenges, and anticipated benefits can ensure we're all on the same page.</li>
<li><strong>Offering support and resources</strong>: As we've discussed, lack of support can lead to frustration and potential failure. We must ensure our people have the necessary resources to successfully implement new methodologies.</li>
<li><strong>Promoting open dialogue</strong>: We should create spaces for our people to share their thoughts, concerns, and feelings about upcoming changes. This approach encourages a sense of ownership and commitment, which can minimize the risk of premature termination.</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/33d6a69c-f572-4538-88d7-e722705b7191/teamwork.jpg?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466TXZD6IVJ%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115509Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIQDvuCKEP3jbPBLQKeIqfmBx%2BxDHFunROfLcgrcQxLVcggIgaYVv7%2F%2B%2FdQ5e273qo6VHVywHCynoag3vTRLvAZHlPL8qiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDDdLQn5J9BdoE4dl%2ByrcA%2FbYycgT52TKq%2BS2vuQvC4CNUK4UG3VRz3%2F%2BNkY23ymVvham7lQ1MKoZqEgudSJ9cSLqTsk01pzqTqhQiXKAMrSqcUx5W1uBj0MVAHjCU9SA0%2BEz%2FheffdvBN7luSAcZfuScSlnlHlZW9MXv6fBCbUZF1Unx6aFKefUWxA2JlvLq2%2B%2F0W31yUyR5EuMlrEu1XaDY6e%2Bo4SZZK0feHrE9RqQD6ObAs35a0tD9GCsi0XMTciMKgAd6%2Fs6qzkmrc%2BQbU7u9IEJZH5wa9wJc8aLKFp8t6cQBNcTNMk6DMxAcsBW5DNLVZ4NIf0igDX6%2FdBX%2F2tZgieNEhVKa4DxUY2oaFEdbmBcaJcEhKVFWlZPUqIQaeD0smw%2F77MKF9F84VIlhvwJbCjz6XKHemt7mMi2Y%2FK1fW2fBGF9IBO4Utx6MaIX1RqiCbOvYCmV9E2194OPxNGSUU0GKJBUBXCiycKEGRjyfiF%2FdlGwtEW%2F7PafkzT%2FOYJNtYyIwT4TwuFdEtBwA4oNHT12nwZb8haLEmI3ymWFER5eeRoL7SUVPRqyZ7e9f87bfUl%2BNJtwXR%2Bvy6eOeuu10Gs0lXrP1ya7yEO6wPvo4HXpkPRtNJ37KZQ3MEQd0vjXfjoGjZXys0tLQMMmdrcQGOqUBUKi12VFvcAfjhKJ2DYrU64jASEXhOq6Gt%2Fg%2FAEf9SkNAJ8wuGhsVOAcmcA2TqCghK0isXlGdu3R%2F20ayJXTM20xa1ntbjR%2FFkWoS%2BOe02GhL%2BwkIL4sR1ibN%2F%2BFRPIxfa%2F2ZFrnbV0OzK7aGWboMTYGwN7dA78gaJaOqmjHGYpiSaChdOjDUl7xu8BEApX4linsSfdfewwhJkMPBAE4LvpOQX%2Bis&amp;X-Amz-Signature=178c4675a0ba7939cb6b570ca5e0a7a1505becc2cf03d26b319a84199ce44355&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="teamwork.jpg" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/26/T22:00:00.000Z-Boosting%20Success%20in%20Engineering%20Changes:%20The%20Power%20of%20Patience%20&amp;%20Alignment#final-thoughts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Final thoughts" title="Direct link to Final thoughts">​</a></h2>
<p>Remember, embracing change is a journey, not a race. It's important to acknowledge that while the process may be fraught with challenges, the benefits of perseverance  often outweigh the initial discomfort or resistance.</p>
<p>Patience, coupled with knowledge alignment, can significantly increase the success rate of implementing new methodologies in engineering departments. By fostering a culture that values patience and open communication, we can better adapt to changes, overcome challenges, and achieve our long-term goals.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Superstar vs. Rockstar Engineers: Balancing Innovation and Stability in Tech Teams]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/12/T22:00:00.000Z-Superstar vs. Rockstar Engineers: Balancing Innovation and Stability in Tech Teams</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/12/T22:00:00.000Z-Superstar vs. Rockstar Engineers: Balancing Innovation and Stability in Tech Teams"/>
        <updated>2024-06-12T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover the unique roles and contributions of Superstar and Rockstar engineers in tech teams. Learn how to balance innovation and stability for optimal productivity and competitiveness]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you noticed a broad spectrum of aspirations among your team members?</p>
<p>Some individuals are eager to tackle new challenges and progress rapidly, while others prefer maintaining the status quo. Do you find one approach more valuable than the other, and if so, why?</p>
<p>Drawing inspiration from the book Radical Candor, this article will discuss the categorization of engineers into Superstars and Rockstars. We'll examine their unique traits, contributions, and roles within the development process.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="superstar-engineers">Superstar Engineers<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/12/T22:00:00.000Z-Superstar%20vs.%20Rockstar%20Engineers:%20Balancing%20Innovation%20and%20Stability%20in%20Tech%20Teams#superstar-engineers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Superstar Engineers" title="Direct link to Superstar Engineers">​</a></h2>
<p>Superstar Engineers are those who strive for more than just the ordinary, who are ready to take calculated risks for innovation. Within the technology sector, they act as catalysts for change and disruption.</p>
<p>Some traits you can find in the work of these engineers:</p>
<ul>
<li>They continuously pursue growth and development</li>
<li>They’re not content with the status quo</li>
<li>They’re willing to take risks to innovate</li>
<li>They’re frequently the driving force behind breakthroughs  in technologies, processes, practices, or products</li>
<li>They’re motivated by a passion for innovation and growth</li>
<li>They propel the team forward, ensuring it stays relevant and competitive</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="rockstar-engineers">Rockstar Engineers<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/12/T22:00:00.000Z-Superstar%20vs.%20Rockstar%20Engineers:%20Balancing%20Innovation%20and%20Stability%20in%20Tech%20Teams#rockstar-engineers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Rockstar Engineers" title="Direct link to Rockstar Engineers">​</a></h2>
<p>Rockstar Engineers are the backbone of the team, providing the dependability that keeps everything running smoothly. Without their steady influence, the boundary-pushing work of Superstars would be far less effective.</p>
<p>Some traits you can find in the work of these engineers:</p>
<ul>
<li>They provide stability and consistency within the team.</li>
<li>They're domain experts, with a deep understanding of particular systems or processes</li>
<li>They ensure the smooth running of systems and processes</li>
<li>They manage and enhance existing systems</li>
<li>They're highly reliable, often serving as the go-to person for issues within their domain</li>
<li>They're incredibly dependable, often the first person you'd call for problems in their area</li>
<li>They value quality and take genuine pride in their work</li>
<li>While they may not be the most visible, their contribution to the team and the business is absolutely critical</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="types-of-engineers-and-engineering-strategy">Types of Engineers and engineering strategy<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/12/T22:00:00.000Z-Superstar%20vs.%20Rockstar%20Engineers:%20Balancing%20Innovation%20and%20Stability%20in%20Tech%20Teams#types-of-engineers-and-engineering-strategy" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Types of Engineers and engineering strategy" title="Direct link to Types of Engineers and engineering strategy">​</a></h2>
<p>Having discussed different types of engineers, let's now explore how this impacts various aspects of our company or team.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="team--company-composition">Team &amp; Company Composition<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/12/T22:00:00.000Z-Superstar%20vs.%20Rockstar%20Engineers:%20Balancing%20Innovation%20and%20Stability%20in%20Tech%20Teams#team--company-composition" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Team &amp; Company Composition" title="Direct link to Team &amp; Company Composition">​</a></h3>
<p>It's crucial to strike a balance between these two types of engineers inside a team or company. The optimal engineering strategy blends Superstars and Rockstars, ensuring the team has both the stability to manage current tasks and the innovative spirit required to stay competitive.</p>
<p>An overabundance of Superstars may lead to instability due to frequent changes, causing the team to remain in a perpetual state of upheaval.</p>
<p>On the other hand, an excess of Rockstars might lead to stagnation, preventing the team from adapting to necessary changes and reducing productivity.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="remuneration--growth">Remuneration &amp; Growth<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/12/T22:00:00.000Z-Superstar%20vs.%20Rockstar%20Engineers:%20Balancing%20Innovation%20and%20Stability%20in%20Tech%20Teams#remuneration--growth" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Remuneration &amp; Growth" title="Direct link to Remuneration &amp; Growth">​</a></h3>
<p>Equally important than having the correct profiles is ensuring that both are valued equally.</p>
<p>This is often a challenge as engineering ladders tend to favor Superstars, who are generally more motivated to climb the ladder.
These ladders often dictate an employee's financial compensation. Leading to Superstars accelerating their remuneration faster than Rockstars, who may hit a pay ceiling.
For this, it's important to tie compensation not to a specific role, but to the unique value an individual contributes to the company or team.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/12/T22:00:00.000Z-Superstar%20vs.%20Rockstar%20Engineers:%20Balancing%20Innovation%20and%20Stability%20in%20Tech%20Teams#closing-thoughts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Closing thoughts" title="Direct link to Closing thoughts">​</a></h2>
<p>Recognizing this duality and managing it effectively is one of the key roles of leadership in the tech industry. By acknowledging and valuing the unique contributions of both Superstars and Rockstars, leaders can foster a diverse, balanced, and highly productive team. This duality is not a hindrance, but a strength that can be harnessed to drive a team or company's success.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Key Strategies for Building High-Performance Teams in Tech]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/07/T00:00:00.000Z-Key Strategies for Building High-Performance Teams in Tech</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/07/T00:00:00.000Z-Key Strategies for Building High-Performance Teams in Tech"/>
        <updated>2024-06-07T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the journey from forming a team to creating a high-performance tech team. Discover the stages of team development, learn about traits of high-performance teams, and uncover effective tools to enhance team dynamics for optimum productivity.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We all continuously hear about high-performance teams and the importance of becoming one. But there is actual no real definition of it. Is it?</p>
<ul>
<li>A team that releases many cards</li>
<li>The one that delivers high-quality code</li>
<li>The one that has all the best engineers</li>
</ul>
<p>The answer, at least for me, is none of the above.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-is-a-team">What is a Team?<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/07/T00:00:00.000Z-Key%20Strategies%20for%20Building%20High-Performance%20Teams%20in%20Tech#what-is-a-team" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What is a Team?" title="Direct link to What is a Team?">​</a></h2>
<p>A definition by Professor Leigh Thompson of the Kellogg School of Management:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A team is a group of people who are interdependent with respect to<br>
<!-- -->information, resources, knowledge and skills and who seek to combine<br>
<!-- -->their efforts to achieve a common goal.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A group itself does not represent a team, for a group to become a team, there is a need for a common goal. As a group evolves into a team, it needs to go through several transformations.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="evolution-from-group-to-team">Evolution From Group to Team<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/07/T00:00:00.000Z-Key%20Strategies%20for%20Building%20High-Performance%20Teams%20in%20Tech#evolution-from-group-to-team" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Evolution From Group to Team" title="Direct link to Evolution From Group to Team">​</a></h2>
<p>Teams typically go through several stages of development. These stages represent the journey from a group of strangers to a united group with common goals.</p>
<p>Tuckman's model describes the four stages of team development as:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Forming</strong>: This is the initial stage where team members meet for the first time. Everyone is polite and positive, and there are high expectations but little understanding of the tasks ahead.</li>
<li><strong>Storming</strong>: As team members start to work together, differences of opinion may lead to conflict. This stage is marked by resistance, competition, and conflict as individual personalities emerge.</li>
<li><strong>Norming</strong>: Gradually, the team moves into the norming stage where they start to resolve their differences, appreciate colleagues' strengths, and respect the leader's authority. The team begins to develop cohesion and unity.</li>
<li><strong>Performing</strong>: This is the stage where the team is fully functional and works towards achieving the team's goals. There is a strong bond between team members, and everyone works collaboratively and efficiently.</li>
</ol>
<p>On the top of Performing, we could say there is o<strong>utperforming</strong> is where <strong>High-Performance</strong> teams live. This final stage is reached when the team consistently exceeds expectations and delivers exceptional results. The team is highly collaborative, innovative, and operates with a shared vision and purpose.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="transitioning-from-one-team-stage-to-another">Transitioning from One Team Stage to Another<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/07/T00:00:00.000Z-Key%20Strategies%20for%20Building%20High-Performance%20Teams%20in%20Tech#transitioning-from-one-team-stage-to-another" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Transitioning from One Team Stage to Another" title="Direct link to Transitioning from One Team Stage to Another">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Forming to Storming</strong>: The transition from forming to storming requires team members to start working together and engaging in discussions and decision-making. It's important for each member to feel comfortable expressing their opinions and ideas, even if they differ from others. This phase often triggers conflicts due to diverse views, but it is a crucial part of the team's evolution, as it allows members to understand and appreciate each other's perspectives.</li>
<li><strong>Storming to Norming</strong>: The shift from storming to norming is marked by the resolution of conflicts and the establishment of processes and norms. This stage requires effective conflict management and open communication. Besides, the team should focus on recognizing and appreciating the strengths of each member and fostering a collaborative environment. The team begins to feel a sense of unity, and a collaborative culture starts to develop.</li>
<li><strong>Norming to Performing</strong>: Moving from norming to performing entails the team becoming more focused on achieving shared goals. The team has now established effective working relationships and understood each other's working styles. At this stage, it's important to stay focused on the team's objectives and ensure everyone is working collaboratively towards them. The team becomes more autonomous, with members taking on responsibilities and roles that align with their strengths.</li>
<li><strong>Performing to Outperforming (High-Performance)</strong>: The leap from performing to outperforming is achieved by exceeding expectations consistently. It's vital to maintain the momentum, continuously innovate, and strive for improvement. Commitment to the team's shared vision and purpose, trust among team members, and open communication are crucial factors in this stage. The team should also be flexible in adapting to changes and challenges and should be driven to continually improve their performance.</li>
</ol>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/aef88634-c6eb-45e7-a72c-5d2ffd4c7737/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466RHCGMUO6%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115508Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJGMEQCIF3rynQTZV%2BJFFa2PlmHIv7usOv9%2FnEUL8U5vhBpm1xxAiAA4sewwC%2FfYIZsAHAwDYKkSO1b0HDpEyUKXKClooQTqiqIBAjU%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F8BEAAaDDYzNzQyMzE4MzgwNSIM0oJA40bCGC3mtcSRKtwDpWH4OshfNZoKe9TBdKwTx3wUbCLTE5yRJIHvSfNjzD%2FVoe%2Fmud7oc9zYQdokFeis2AIy6%2Bw1tmObD7ByBprOuPr%2Fqn6RjoR4AxPTE2f6T5oAZ8fXD8PtI%2FQbk3kLgwFgs9oWDvTLNYrQoZlyuFFN1tXaEM9hkjVOPMW3xdZjBW8jIcOru4CveAzuZUGBtoMdgNNeEj70dM4aoBD%2FHLOHg5hhuaWFcCrUQdY550wbhhXy40RXCQz5HbPJft0dF2Q1cAbhiHa9F%2FIEcUOTKBDuSmGFfK%2BD%2B8mnATjGA1F%2BazqpiIBgRORLjCJ6pXzRb5KPtXaA3qr1vK7bGvpanRnBLNu3xeu2Qywp8E4Z5oy9mZdt8kSh9wWyeo2vQweBaIqPXwck1xJygM1K9%2FQIKBf0Hy3v0KYgTDIQg%2Fb6L%2FbNJFf0y35MGtXZY2Ux2A1NQ4GJ2vQ3wX3%2BQaq82yxvjmwyH6%2BdJLyp%2BbVKBHoI0srdEdQUG91Bx3UNph%2FD9UE36ukYI4xGataoBNxUmvo16UQODavVfCGrRbafZ5rbR4Zjdk8PRhRmLQ6q%2BNNn148qwutvpyLLBGT%2FDazPokEVm1v3i7tmbKFc8YNFyLnvVbojDxfGy2QgunhDqpLrfx4wnJ2txAY6pgE0UKYvx0nKt9AYxWrDsDKAHxzAtPO7xhpGvoQlrO2PT6sqjiXcjeoGXS5ESixN4ue6X%2FWyJ755Rm52Oo5LFO2b%2FVkwpX9q89bz%2BagJv8y5zyQg0s3SGiKiECqbJ3ZJj8FQeHSC2VWSNkpsVvUZYre0RRF763fjhzSHVoECeSQ4buBhIiCW6s1%2FXb3z7or78ByldIN1fUZ41z059iG4ubv06DOrMPMu&amp;X-Amz-Signature=be975562d7898da976dd27df71b42e3779ad19d119fbcddaf520307279f38d29&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="Untitled.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="traits-of-a-high-performance-team">Traits Of a High-Performance Team<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/07/T00:00:00.000Z-Key%20Strategies%20for%20Building%20High-Performance%20Teams%20in%20Tech#traits-of-a-high-performance-team" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Traits Of a High-Performance Team" title="Direct link to Traits Of a High-Performance Team">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Trust</strong>: This refers to the confidence among team members that each person will fulfill their responsibilities and maintain a commitment to the common goal.</li>
<li><strong>Mutual Support</strong>: This involves members actively helping each other to succeed, promoting a culture of cooperation and interdependence.</li>
<li><strong>Drive</strong>: This indicates the team's collective motivation and ambition to achieve their goals and continually improve their performance.</li>
<li><strong>Edit Their Needs</strong>: This implies the team's ability to self-assess and adjust their requirements and strategies based on the evolving circumstances.</li>
<li><strong>Open Communication</strong>: This refers to the team's ability to communicate effectively, ensuring that everyone feels heard and understood. Open communication fosters transparency and encourages team members to share their ideas and feedback.</li>
<li><strong>Do Not Depend on a Leader</strong>: This means the team operates in a decentralized manner where every member takes initiative and responsibility, rather than relying on a single leader for direction and decisions.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="example-tools-to-improve-team-traits">Example Tools To Improve Team Traits<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/07/T00:00:00.000Z-Key%20Strategies%20for%20Building%20High-Performance%20Teams%20in%20Tech#example-tools-to-improve-team-traits" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Example Tools To Improve Team Traits" title="Direct link to Example Tools To Improve Team Traits">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="getting-to-know-the-human-behind-team-personal-presentations">Getting to Know the Human Behind: Team Personal Presentations<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/07/T00:00:00.000Z-Key%20Strategies%20for%20Building%20High-Performance%20Teams%20in%20Tech#getting-to-know-the-human-behind-team-personal-presentations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Getting to Know the Human Behind: Team Personal Presentations" title="Direct link to Getting to Know the Human Behind: Team Personal Presentations">​</a></h3>
<p>Team Personal Presentations is an exercise where each team member creates a short presentation about themselves to share with the rest of the team. This can include information about their background, interests, strengths, weaknesses, and even fun facts. The goal is to allow team members to get to know each other on a deeper level, beyond just their professional roles.</p>
<p>This exercise can help to build stronger relationships within the team, foster empathy and understanding, and improve team cohesion. It gives team members an insight into who their colleagues really are, which can lead to greater trust, better communication, and a more effective working environment.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/e79385f5-d419-4a56-bda7-84f370889a82/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466RHCGMUO6%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115509Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJGMEQCIF3rynQTZV%2BJFFa2PlmHIv7usOv9%2FnEUL8U5vhBpm1xxAiAA4sewwC%2FfYIZsAHAwDYKkSO1b0HDpEyUKXKClooQTqiqIBAjU%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F8BEAAaDDYzNzQyMzE4MzgwNSIM0oJA40bCGC3mtcSRKtwDpWH4OshfNZoKe9TBdKwTx3wUbCLTE5yRJIHvSfNjzD%2FVoe%2Fmud7oc9zYQdokFeis2AIy6%2Bw1tmObD7ByBprOuPr%2Fqn6RjoR4AxPTE2f6T5oAZ8fXD8PtI%2FQbk3kLgwFgs9oWDvTLNYrQoZlyuFFN1tXaEM9hkjVOPMW3xdZjBW8jIcOru4CveAzuZUGBtoMdgNNeEj70dM4aoBD%2FHLOHg5hhuaWFcCrUQdY550wbhhXy40RXCQz5HbPJft0dF2Q1cAbhiHa9F%2FIEcUOTKBDuSmGFfK%2BD%2B8mnATjGA1F%2BazqpiIBgRORLjCJ6pXzRb5KPtXaA3qr1vK7bGvpanRnBLNu3xeu2Qywp8E4Z5oy9mZdt8kSh9wWyeo2vQweBaIqPXwck1xJygM1K9%2FQIKBf0Hy3v0KYgTDIQg%2Fb6L%2FbNJFf0y35MGtXZY2Ux2A1NQ4GJ2vQ3wX3%2BQaq82yxvjmwyH6%2BdJLyp%2BbVKBHoI0srdEdQUG91Bx3UNph%2FD9UE36ukYI4xGataoBNxUmvo16UQODavVfCGrRbafZ5rbR4Zjdk8PRhRmLQ6q%2BNNn148qwutvpyLLBGT%2FDazPokEVm1v3i7tmbKFc8YNFyLnvVbojDxfGy2QgunhDqpLrfx4wnJ2txAY6pgE0UKYvx0nKt9AYxWrDsDKAHxzAtPO7xhpGvoQlrO2PT6sqjiXcjeoGXS5ESixN4ue6X%2FWyJ755Rm52Oo5LFO2b%2FVkwpX9q89bz%2BagJv8y5zyQg0s3SGiKiECqbJ3ZJj8FQeHSC2VWSNkpsVvUZYre0RRF763fjhzSHVoECeSQ4buBhIiCW6s1%2FXb3z7or78ByldIN1fUZ41z059iG4ubv06DOrMPMu&amp;X-Amz-Signature=42dacb6d0ed803f7328528cbde35eca7402eaa28bcd05960c0639c9c611b3e6e&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="Untitled.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="getting-to-know-how-we-exchange-communication-preferences">Getting to Know How We Exchange: Communication Preferences<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/07/T00:00:00.000Z-Key%20Strategies%20for%20Building%20High-Performance%20Teams%20in%20Tech#getting-to-know-how-we-exchange-communication-preferences" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Getting to Know How We Exchange: Communication Preferences" title="Direct link to Getting to Know How We Exchange: Communication Preferences">​</a></h3>
<p>Communication Preferences is an activity that helps team members understand each other's preferred methods of communication. This can include when and how they like to receive information, how they handle conflict, and how they give and receive feedback. Understanding these preferences can greatly improve team collaboration and prevent misunderstandings.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/e53de265-96d6-44b1-b4df-c182f7d5be88/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466RHCGMUO6%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115509Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJGMEQCIF3rynQTZV%2BJFFa2PlmHIv7usOv9%2FnEUL8U5vhBpm1xxAiAA4sewwC%2FfYIZsAHAwDYKkSO1b0HDpEyUKXKClooQTqiqIBAjU%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F8BEAAaDDYzNzQyMzE4MzgwNSIM0oJA40bCGC3mtcSRKtwDpWH4OshfNZoKe9TBdKwTx3wUbCLTE5yRJIHvSfNjzD%2FVoe%2Fmud7oc9zYQdokFeis2AIy6%2Bw1tmObD7ByBprOuPr%2Fqn6RjoR4AxPTE2f6T5oAZ8fXD8PtI%2FQbk3kLgwFgs9oWDvTLNYrQoZlyuFFN1tXaEM9hkjVOPMW3xdZjBW8jIcOru4CveAzuZUGBtoMdgNNeEj70dM4aoBD%2FHLOHg5hhuaWFcCrUQdY550wbhhXy40RXCQz5HbPJft0dF2Q1cAbhiHa9F%2FIEcUOTKBDuSmGFfK%2BD%2B8mnATjGA1F%2BazqpiIBgRORLjCJ6pXzRb5KPtXaA3qr1vK7bGvpanRnBLNu3xeu2Qywp8E4Z5oy9mZdt8kSh9wWyeo2vQweBaIqPXwck1xJygM1K9%2FQIKBf0Hy3v0KYgTDIQg%2Fb6L%2FbNJFf0y35MGtXZY2Ux2A1NQ4GJ2vQ3wX3%2BQaq82yxvjmwyH6%2BdJLyp%2BbVKBHoI0srdEdQUG91Bx3UNph%2FD9UE36ukYI4xGataoBNxUmvo16UQODavVfCGrRbafZ5rbR4Zjdk8PRhRmLQ6q%2BNNn148qwutvpyLLBGT%2FDazPokEVm1v3i7tmbKFc8YNFyLnvVbojDxfGy2QgunhDqpLrfx4wnJ2txAY6pgE0UKYvx0nKt9AYxWrDsDKAHxzAtPO7xhpGvoQlrO2PT6sqjiXcjeoGXS5ESixN4ue6X%2FWyJ755Rm52Oo5LFO2b%2FVkwpX9q89bz%2BagJv8y5zyQg0s3SGiKiECqbJ3ZJj8FQeHSC2VWSNkpsVvUZYre0RRF763fjhzSHVoECeSQ4buBhIiCW6s1%2FXb3z7or78ByldIN1fUZ41z059iG4ubv06DOrMPMu&amp;X-Amz-Signature=5060c36f7aecf8198000140395ce7d47fba8e16619d2d1ea758c1e0ed1c621c1&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="https://excalidraw.com/#json=STnnDPzkDh1E7vMwED4Ln,53YwRgNjbRDrcQiMz6lfLQ" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="getting-to-know-what-we-care-about-moving-motivators">Getting to Know What We Care About: Moving motivators<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/07/T00:00:00.000Z-Key%20Strategies%20for%20Building%20High-Performance%20Teams%20in%20Tech#getting-to-know-what-we-care-about-moving-motivators" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Getting to Know What We Care About: Moving motivators" title="Direct link to Getting to Know What We Care About: Moving motivators">​</a></h3>
<p>The Moving Motivators exercise is a tool from Management 3.0 that helps in understanding the intrinsic motivations of individuals within a team. It involves a deck of ten cards, each representing a key motivator such as acceptance, curiosity, freedom, or power.</p>
<p>The participant orders these cards in order of personal importance. Then, they consider a recent change in their work or life and move the cards up or down based on whether this change has positively or negatively impacted each motivator. This provides valuable insights into what drives a person and how changes affect their motivation, which is crucial for effective team management and leadership.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/57afc750-5aeb-44fc-8ae0-0db80f16946f/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466RHCGMUO6%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115509Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJGMEQCIF3rynQTZV%2BJFFa2PlmHIv7usOv9%2FnEUL8U5vhBpm1xxAiAA4sewwC%2FfYIZsAHAwDYKkSO1b0HDpEyUKXKClooQTqiqIBAjU%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F8BEAAaDDYzNzQyMzE4MzgwNSIM0oJA40bCGC3mtcSRKtwDpWH4OshfNZoKe9TBdKwTx3wUbCLTE5yRJIHvSfNjzD%2FVoe%2Fmud7oc9zYQdokFeis2AIy6%2Bw1tmObD7ByBprOuPr%2Fqn6RjoR4AxPTE2f6T5oAZ8fXD8PtI%2FQbk3kLgwFgs9oWDvTLNYrQoZlyuFFN1tXaEM9hkjVOPMW3xdZjBW8jIcOru4CveAzuZUGBtoMdgNNeEj70dM4aoBD%2FHLOHg5hhuaWFcCrUQdY550wbhhXy40RXCQz5HbPJft0dF2Q1cAbhiHa9F%2FIEcUOTKBDuSmGFfK%2BD%2B8mnATjGA1F%2BazqpiIBgRORLjCJ6pXzRb5KPtXaA3qr1vK7bGvpanRnBLNu3xeu2Qywp8E4Z5oy9mZdt8kSh9wWyeo2vQweBaIqPXwck1xJygM1K9%2FQIKBf0Hy3v0KYgTDIQg%2Fb6L%2FbNJFf0y35MGtXZY2Ux2A1NQ4GJ2vQ3wX3%2BQaq82yxvjmwyH6%2BdJLyp%2BbVKBHoI0srdEdQUG91Bx3UNph%2FD9UE36ukYI4xGataoBNxUmvo16UQODavVfCGrRbafZ5rbR4Zjdk8PRhRmLQ6q%2BNNn148qwutvpyLLBGT%2FDazPokEVm1v3i7tmbKFc8YNFyLnvVbojDxfGy2QgunhDqpLrfx4wnJ2txAY6pgE0UKYvx0nKt9AYxWrDsDKAHxzAtPO7xhpGvoQlrO2PT6sqjiXcjeoGXS5ESixN4ue6X%2FWyJ755Rm52Oo5LFO2b%2FVkwpX9q89bz%2BagJv8y5zyQg0s3SGiKiECqbJ3ZJj8FQeHSC2VWSNkpsVvUZYre0RRF763fjhzSHVoECeSQ4buBhIiCW6s1%2FXb3z7or78ByldIN1fUZ41z059iG4ubv06DOrMPMu&amp;X-Amz-Signature=dd714cf91e084276a5b0aababc0268752d6afb4f9e563c1d90baa767c45efbb2&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="https://excalidraw.com/#json=9p-2kVpQEkhCmKF-EouDI,OCPiUgI6FaQHTX1JMIKWeg" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="getting-to-know-what-area-to-improve-next-team-health-check">Getting to Know What Area to Improve Next: Team Health Check<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/06/07/T00:00:00.000Z-Key%20Strategies%20for%20Building%20High-Performance%20Teams%20in%20Tech#getting-to-know-what-area-to-improve-next-team-health-check" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Getting to Know What Area to Improve Next: Team Health Check" title="Direct link to Getting to Know What Area to Improve Next: Team Health Check">​</a></h3>
<p>The Team Health Check is an exercise developed by Spotify to assess the health of their teams.</p>
<p>Teams collectively assess how they are doing on several aspects, such as collaboration, value delivery, mission, fun, learning, and leadership. Each team member votes on each aspect using a traffic light system (green for good, yellow for okay, red for not good).</p>
<p>The results are then discussed openly, helping to facilitate communication about challenges, improvements, and actions to be taken. The exercise is not about blaming or pointing fingers but about understanding and improving team dynamics and performance.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/5683f85a-60a7-4bb0-970e-e79c2ac3a537/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466RHCGMUO6%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115509Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJGMEQCIF3rynQTZV%2BJFFa2PlmHIv7usOv9%2FnEUL8U5vhBpm1xxAiAA4sewwC%2FfYIZsAHAwDYKkSO1b0HDpEyUKXKClooQTqiqIBAjU%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F8BEAAaDDYzNzQyMzE4MzgwNSIM0oJA40bCGC3mtcSRKtwDpWH4OshfNZoKe9TBdKwTx3wUbCLTE5yRJIHvSfNjzD%2FVoe%2Fmud7oc9zYQdokFeis2AIy6%2Bw1tmObD7ByBprOuPr%2Fqn6RjoR4AxPTE2f6T5oAZ8fXD8PtI%2FQbk3kLgwFgs9oWDvTLNYrQoZlyuFFN1tXaEM9hkjVOPMW3xdZjBW8jIcOru4CveAzuZUGBtoMdgNNeEj70dM4aoBD%2FHLOHg5hhuaWFcCrUQdY550wbhhXy40RXCQz5HbPJft0dF2Q1cAbhiHa9F%2FIEcUOTKBDuSmGFfK%2BD%2B8mnATjGA1F%2BazqpiIBgRORLjCJ6pXzRb5KPtXaA3qr1vK7bGvpanRnBLNu3xeu2Qywp8E4Z5oy9mZdt8kSh9wWyeo2vQweBaIqPXwck1xJygM1K9%2FQIKBf0Hy3v0KYgTDIQg%2Fb6L%2FbNJFf0y35MGtXZY2Ux2A1NQ4GJ2vQ3wX3%2BQaq82yxvjmwyH6%2BdJLyp%2BbVKBHoI0srdEdQUG91Bx3UNph%2FD9UE36ukYI4xGataoBNxUmvo16UQODavVfCGrRbafZ5rbR4Zjdk8PRhRmLQ6q%2BNNn148qwutvpyLLBGT%2FDazPokEVm1v3i7tmbKFc8YNFyLnvVbojDxfGy2QgunhDqpLrfx4wnJ2txAY6pgE0UKYvx0nKt9AYxWrDsDKAHxzAtPO7xhpGvoQlrO2PT6sqjiXcjeoGXS5ESixN4ue6X%2FWyJ755Rm52Oo5LFO2b%2FVkwpX9q89bz%2BagJv8y5zyQg0s3SGiKiECqbJ3ZJj8FQeHSC2VWSNkpsVvUZYre0RRF763fjhzSHVoECeSQ4buBhIiCW6s1%2FXb3z7or78ByldIN1fUZ41z059iG4ubv06DOrMPMu&amp;X-Amz-Signature=eb7503a74cf09eedfbc4478049766bd2a95eafc2a9f4baad72e128d0b4afb012&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="https://excalidraw.com/#json=RnIvsEE-MBK6_FtvveL92,xfbgr6blEekHkZyGb3E7og" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Most Engineering Hiring Processes Are Broken]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/30/T22:00:00.000Z-Most Engineering Hiring Processes Are Broken</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/30/T22:00:00.000Z-Most Engineering Hiring Processes Are Broken"/>
        <updated>2024-05-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore effective strategies for streamlining the hiring process in the tech industry. Learn how simplifying the evaluation process and reducing feedback loops can help you attract top-tier talent faster and more efficiently.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Leading a team or a company necessitates having individuals who can assist in realizing your objectives. Undoubtedly, this involves establishing a hiring process. Have you considered how hiring for software projects may consume extensive time and effort?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-average-hiring-process">The Average Hiring Process<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/30/T22:00:00.000Z-Most%20Engineering%20Hiring%20Processes%20Are%20Broken#the-average-hiring-process" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Average Hiring Process" title="Direct link to The Average Hiring Process">​</a></h2>
<p>Whenever I step into a company, my gaze is often drawn to their recruitment procedures. Typically, the process aligns with or forms a subset of this schematic.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/8f086c27-5449-4a04-b2b5-f8b50b110c83/average_process.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB4666VSUFUQK%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115512Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIHoSO8TGUzjX%2FooDEYC77hpQ08I%2BNBmeZbb7GVD2QmqbAiEA4vyMI7gRiMr5hBqvFK8e4GTfYBjEHOs8Lc6u6sSm%2FnsqiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDAmxF5wKk5IDcBf6MCrcA5sEGYXg8iIJecHEmb87WNumhvscmQ1lMNx%2Bmu9TZYxo6xnbVHgfwM2cXo%2FgP5JbN%2BOaOQfLiSfKzbmFx4bikdram3gEla4EC9f4MSkwdqoe28a9eZvdtK1aYUnSQ02aoItQaFJY4HUzio3cFn2ibjbp5CFGYXH3V7AKYDfrztyUm9lmjKO9BwzgFEenQ8MpoBnvJeejO8QePaXH9BYlWz7L3RMJ7ystJ%2BBD9%2Fu4VbU%2B8HBfIv5oDbMljL%2Ff%2BaJmVxuy77wrFKHvoJWgolHtJrIjftGxl5qMWkVRKuvRD5Pnn%2FxZSs6n%2B2WHdIlmOToTQkn%2FTpFLOYA9qry4fNLprheMqCaoy6Vtdj%2FndgrOcqmQ5YnFNwn95j4LI3noiRLAPaDeiyCRxHzBuhGZehTblGvVdrl5cz2gxLUtZh%2BdiZlHYbs%2Baa1DkXKvNnCfg6AqHxATC7iOtG3JiCnqWP%2F8bRfZPCp4%2FhCxVqh%2BM2qf8oqU0n2rKlY3NqoyQLoXpGh%2FSvOzj3trBbPG9w0n7JJJ9fRg5XFUL4L86dVdcurFL2Q3scW%2F6dneBjLnP%2FZFK3YrqKaWUyLrkZKNZnRzizyJY0WkOrUhrhUqOJP7QDkqfvKbIIlP5DT1zptwN5%2BRMMedrcQGOqUBAFOjsqY59XWkGhGfGiDGEz4mzF5M9mr04h1nJUSfO7%2FMcgE1sgg0mTpjitg8V8xZGvfp1TWyNl6DT1Rsyi04hVr5ll3rE1K6iHmWuY6jTaU2IMnF814LTKGoTB25d6j9SocTxcjJuynJCLIPtRh1SD8PHzNB1KZX7R843IbMqo7dvtp9qKuvZe3OsNxKYYOgObXCB3IXcFs%2Bbf9l%2B%2Bv3faXKmwMk&amp;X-Amz-Signature=7df5f63d1e68ac5f76b1025a907d39daad70e15a7b337ce56e99b5508efe2cf1&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="average_process.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Most companies employ these steps as filters, aiming to discover the “ideal candidate” with the least possible commitment. This turns the hiring process into a lengthy, high-effort endeavor that can span multiple months. As you can see, from application to hire, we're looking at an average of 32 days and a time investment of 15.5 hours.</p>
<p>In competitive markets—such as the one I'm familiar with—the top candidates are often hired within a maximum of two weeks after applying for a job. How can this be?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-issue-at-hand">The Issue at hand<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/30/T22:00:00.000Z-Most%20Engineering%20Hiring%20Processes%20Are%20Broken#the-issue-at-hand" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Issue at hand" title="Direct link to The Issue at hand">​</a></h2>
<p>Over-engineering can be pinpointed as the root cause of the issue.</p>
<p>Here are the three main concerns that lead to this:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Risk Avoidance Leads to Over-Complication:</strong> Trying to avoid any slip-ups during the hiring process often results in a complicated and lengthy procedure. This method is more about reducing the risk of a bad hire, even if it sacrifices speed and efficiency.</li>
<li><strong>Fear of Overlooking the Perfect Candidate:</strong> The worry of not finding that potentially perfect candidate leads to an exhaustive process. Every candidate is meticulously screened at each stage, lengthening the hiring period.</li>
<li><strong>Concern Over Wasting Employee Time:</strong> The fear of spending current employee time on unsuccessful hiring processes is a worry. This concern stems from knowing that time is valuable, especially in fast-paced work environments. If the hiring process doesn't yield a successful hire, it's considered a misuse of employee time that could have been used for immediate needs and goals.</li>
</ul>
<p>However, lengthy processes are the embodiment of these fears. The rationale is straightforward: the top candidates are often the first to be snapped up. If your hiring process is sluggish due to numerous feedback loops, chances are you're missing out on top-tier talent.</p>
<p>Remember, most companies aren't engaged in rocket science, which means you probably don't need a rocket scientist on your team. What you do need are team players who can collaborate effectively and add value to your product.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/5bda32ba-6fad-4a72-b770-456f2f682215/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB4666VSUFUQK%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115512Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIHoSO8TGUzjX%2FooDEYC77hpQ08I%2BNBmeZbb7GVD2QmqbAiEA4vyMI7gRiMr5hBqvFK8e4GTfYBjEHOs8Lc6u6sSm%2FnsqiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDAmxF5wKk5IDcBf6MCrcA5sEGYXg8iIJecHEmb87WNumhvscmQ1lMNx%2Bmu9TZYxo6xnbVHgfwM2cXo%2FgP5JbN%2BOaOQfLiSfKzbmFx4bikdram3gEla4EC9f4MSkwdqoe28a9eZvdtK1aYUnSQ02aoItQaFJY4HUzio3cFn2ibjbp5CFGYXH3V7AKYDfrztyUm9lmjKO9BwzgFEenQ8MpoBnvJeejO8QePaXH9BYlWz7L3RMJ7ystJ%2BBD9%2Fu4VbU%2B8HBfIv5oDbMljL%2Ff%2BaJmVxuy77wrFKHvoJWgolHtJrIjftGxl5qMWkVRKuvRD5Pnn%2FxZSs6n%2B2WHdIlmOToTQkn%2FTpFLOYA9qry4fNLprheMqCaoy6Vtdj%2FndgrOcqmQ5YnFNwn95j4LI3noiRLAPaDeiyCRxHzBuhGZehTblGvVdrl5cz2gxLUtZh%2BdiZlHYbs%2Baa1DkXKvNnCfg6AqHxATC7iOtG3JiCnqWP%2F8bRfZPCp4%2FhCxVqh%2BM2qf8oqU0n2rKlY3NqoyQLoXpGh%2FSvOzj3trBbPG9w0n7JJJ9fRg5XFUL4L86dVdcurFL2Q3scW%2F6dneBjLnP%2FZFK3YrqKaWUyLrkZKNZnRzizyJY0WkOrUhrhUqOJP7QDkqfvKbIIlP5DT1zptwN5%2BRMMedrcQGOqUBAFOjsqY59XWkGhGfGiDGEz4mzF5M9mr04h1nJUSfO7%2FMcgE1sgg0mTpjitg8V8xZGvfp1TWyNl6DT1Rsyi04hVr5ll3rE1K6iHmWuY6jTaU2IMnF814LTKGoTB25d6j9SocTxcjJuynJCLIPtRh1SD8PHzNB1KZX7R843IbMqo7dvtp9qKuvZe3OsNxKYYOgObXCB3IXcFs%2Bbf9l%2B%2Bv3faXKmwMk&amp;X-Amz-Signature=c81a4d4f156ae3c3c3785c683ca969b3bbe6d6573a436778a2dc6a6d7293362a&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="https://devrant.com/rants/2848905/interview-vs-job" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="solving-the-problem">Solving the problem<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/30/T22:00:00.000Z-Most%20Engineering%20Hiring%20Processes%20Are%20Broken#solving-the-problem" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Solving the problem" title="Direct link to Solving the problem">​</a></h2>
<p>To attract and secure top-tier talent in a fast and efficient manner, it is imperative to streamline and reform our hiring process.</p>
<p>The objective is to create a process that is not only efficient in its operations, but also effective in securing the best possible talent for our teams. This approach must consider the existing challenges in the hiring process and devise solutions that counter these issues, while optimizing for speed and quality of hires.</p>
<p>To facilitate such transformation in the hiring process, we need to undertake the following steps:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="simplify-evaluation-process">Simplify Evaluation Process<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/30/T22:00:00.000Z-Most%20Engineering%20Hiring%20Processes%20Are%20Broken#simplify-evaluation-process" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Simplify Evaluation Process" title="Direct link to Simplify Evaluation Process">​</a></h3>
<p>The prevailing approach in many companies operates like a wishlist, confirming that candidates meet an extensive set of expectations. However, these wishlists often become an endless array of checkboxes that candidates must tick off.</p>
<p>A more efficient solution would be to invert this evaluation method, implementing a flagging system to identify what is unacceptable in a candidate. This method streamlines the process, as it's a true or false evaluation where we all have the same expectation. Instead of having a checklist of 100 items that can have different readings by the evaluator to be covered in 2 to 4 technically focused interviews, we're able to identify any red flags in just one or two interviews.</p>
<p>Let's see examples that I have seen in real life:</p>
<table><thead><tr><th>Wishlist</th><th>Flags</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><strong>Coding Interview:</strong></td><td></td></tr></tbody></table>
<ul>
<li>Does hexagonal architecture</li>
<li>Has done unit tests</li>
<li>Has done integration test</li>
<li>Follows SOLID principles</li>
<li>Writes Clean Code</li>
<li>Refactors when needed</li>
<li>…
<strong>Whiteboard Session:</strong></li>
<li>Decouples Systems</li>
<li>Takes in count Scalability</li>
<li>Takes in count Security</li>
<li>Understands sharding</li>
<li>Understands different types of DB and their use</li>
<li>Understand evolutionary architecture</li>
<li>…
<strong>Technical Conversation:</strong></li>
<li>Can explain the business of a project</li>
<li>Can explain the technical aspect of a project</li>
<li>Understands CI/CD</li>
<li>Understands testing value</li>
<li>…
<strong>Values Session:</strong></li>
<li>Is an active listener</li>
<li>Understand fairness</li>
<li>Understand no blame culture</li>
<li>… | 🔴 Discriminates based on social or technical aspects.
🔴 Lies on an explanation when they don't know a subject.
🔴 Ignores feedback, continues without reflection.
🔴 Does not explain their train of though, after request.
🔴 Does not accommodate for people's needs regarding communication styles (ex. Drawing).
🟡 Makes things overcomplicated.
🟡 Is unable to explain certain aspects of what they do.
🟡 Does not execute or compile while working.
🟡 Does not do any kind of test while working. |</li>
</ul>
<p>Here is how the simplified process looks like:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/890e4faa-9308-4243-b289-6a539acc9cdd/simple_process_1.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB4666VSUFUQK%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115512Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIHoSO8TGUzjX%2FooDEYC77hpQ08I%2BNBmeZbb7GVD2QmqbAiEA4vyMI7gRiMr5hBqvFK8e4GTfYBjEHOs8Lc6u6sSm%2FnsqiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDAmxF5wKk5IDcBf6MCrcA5sEGYXg8iIJecHEmb87WNumhvscmQ1lMNx%2Bmu9TZYxo6xnbVHgfwM2cXo%2FgP5JbN%2BOaOQfLiSfKzbmFx4bikdram3gEla4EC9f4MSkwdqoe28a9eZvdtK1aYUnSQ02aoItQaFJY4HUzio3cFn2ibjbp5CFGYXH3V7AKYDfrztyUm9lmjKO9BwzgFEenQ8MpoBnvJeejO8QePaXH9BYlWz7L3RMJ7ystJ%2BBD9%2Fu4VbU%2B8HBfIv5oDbMljL%2Ff%2BaJmVxuy77wrFKHvoJWgolHtJrIjftGxl5qMWkVRKuvRD5Pnn%2FxZSs6n%2B2WHdIlmOToTQkn%2FTpFLOYA9qry4fNLprheMqCaoy6Vtdj%2FndgrOcqmQ5YnFNwn95j4LI3noiRLAPaDeiyCRxHzBuhGZehTblGvVdrl5cz2gxLUtZh%2BdiZlHYbs%2Baa1DkXKvNnCfg6AqHxATC7iOtG3JiCnqWP%2F8bRfZPCp4%2FhCxVqh%2BM2qf8oqU0n2rKlY3NqoyQLoXpGh%2FSvOzj3trBbPG9w0n7JJJ9fRg5XFUL4L86dVdcurFL2Q3scW%2F6dneBjLnP%2FZFK3YrqKaWUyLrkZKNZnRzizyJY0WkOrUhrhUqOJP7QDkqfvKbIIlP5DT1zptwN5%2BRMMedrcQGOqUBAFOjsqY59XWkGhGfGiDGEz4mzF5M9mr04h1nJUSfO7%2FMcgE1sgg0mTpjitg8V8xZGvfp1TWyNl6DT1Rsyi04hVr5ll3rE1K6iHmWuY6jTaU2IMnF814LTKGoTB25d6j9SocTxcjJuynJCLIPtRh1SD8PHzNB1KZX7R843IbMqo7dvtp9qKuvZe3OsNxKYYOgObXCB3IXcFs%2Bbf9l%2B%2Bv3faXKmwMk&amp;X-Amz-Signature=f9da3d3d9d8e1b1ddb5e9e62278c5313416a648f6bd5ca99b15d0cce360500d7&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="simple_process_1.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="reduce-the-feedback-loops">Reduce The Feedback Loops<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/30/T22:00:00.000Z-Most%20Engineering%20Hiring%20Processes%20Are%20Broken#reduce-the-feedback-loops" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Reduce The Feedback Loops" title="Direct link to Reduce The Feedback Loops">​</a></h3>
<p>In line with product development, minimizing feedback loops can enhance agility.</p>
<p>Inserting filters into the process simply creates delay in decision-making, as feedback must be revisited before proceeding. These waiting periods regularly lead to candidates disengaging from the process.</p>
<p>Moreover, these filters may inadvertently prevent a potential candidate from showcasing their full potential in later stages of the process, frequently leading to premature dismissal of suitable candidates for the position.</p>
<p>Eliminating filters from feedback loops can accelerate the process and lessen the burden on our existing employees. By removing reporting for future steps and not discarding candidates early, candidate success rate will increase, resulting in fewer interviews in the long run.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/61e97fe8-23a7-49a2-bea8-4d60ab7b4bd3/simple_process_2.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB4666VSUFUQK%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115512Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIHoSO8TGUzjX%2FooDEYC77hpQ08I%2BNBmeZbb7GVD2QmqbAiEA4vyMI7gRiMr5hBqvFK8e4GTfYBjEHOs8Lc6u6sSm%2FnsqiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDAmxF5wKk5IDcBf6MCrcA5sEGYXg8iIJecHEmb87WNumhvscmQ1lMNx%2Bmu9TZYxo6xnbVHgfwM2cXo%2FgP5JbN%2BOaOQfLiSfKzbmFx4bikdram3gEla4EC9f4MSkwdqoe28a9eZvdtK1aYUnSQ02aoItQaFJY4HUzio3cFn2ibjbp5CFGYXH3V7AKYDfrztyUm9lmjKO9BwzgFEenQ8MpoBnvJeejO8QePaXH9BYlWz7L3RMJ7ystJ%2BBD9%2Fu4VbU%2B8HBfIv5oDbMljL%2Ff%2BaJmVxuy77wrFKHvoJWgolHtJrIjftGxl5qMWkVRKuvRD5Pnn%2FxZSs6n%2B2WHdIlmOToTQkn%2FTpFLOYA9qry4fNLprheMqCaoy6Vtdj%2FndgrOcqmQ5YnFNwn95j4LI3noiRLAPaDeiyCRxHzBuhGZehTblGvVdrl5cz2gxLUtZh%2BdiZlHYbs%2Baa1DkXKvNnCfg6AqHxATC7iOtG3JiCnqWP%2F8bRfZPCp4%2FhCxVqh%2BM2qf8oqU0n2rKlY3NqoyQLoXpGh%2FSvOzj3trBbPG9w0n7JJJ9fRg5XFUL4L86dVdcurFL2Q3scW%2F6dneBjLnP%2FZFK3YrqKaWUyLrkZKNZnRzizyJY0WkOrUhrhUqOJP7QDkqfvKbIIlP5DT1zptwN5%2BRMMedrcQGOqUBAFOjsqY59XWkGhGfGiDGEz4mzF5M9mr04h1nJUSfO7%2FMcgE1sgg0mTpjitg8V8xZGvfp1TWyNl6DT1Rsyi04hVr5ll3rE1K6iHmWuY6jTaU2IMnF814LTKGoTB25d6j9SocTxcjJuynJCLIPtRh1SD8PHzNB1KZX7R843IbMqo7dvtp9qKuvZe3OsNxKYYOgObXCB3IXcFs%2Bbf9l%2B%2Bv3faXKmwMk&amp;X-Amz-Signature=4888b1d0f447bdf3fcedcfdb384bd3028a682c545662c0f844b2033ab0155320&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="simple_process_2.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="final-words">Final Words<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/30/T22:00:00.000Z-Most%20Engineering%20Hiring%20Processes%20Are%20Broken#final-words" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Final Words" title="Direct link to Final Words">​</a></h2>
<p>In conclusion, the key to a successful hiring process lies in simplicity and efficiency. By focusing on eliminating unnecessary steps and reducing feedback loops, companies can accelerate their hiring process and attract and retain the best talent in the market.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Break Out Of The Comfort Zone: The Need for Big Leaps Over Incremental Improvements]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/23/T00:00:00.000Z-Break Out Of The Comfort Zone: The Need for Big Leaps Over Incremental Improvements</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/23/T00:00:00.000Z-Break Out Of The Comfort Zone: The Need for Big Leaps Over Incremental Improvements"/>
        <updated>2024-05-23T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the limitations of incremental improvements and the potential of big leaps in software development and business strategy. Learn to identify signs of stagnation, enact change, and maximize your team's potential.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever felt stuck or that you're not making progress towards your goal with the current approach you or your team are employing?</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/38240359-a9c4-40de-a201-258d672ad902/cz1.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466S55LPARM%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115508Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIEcjj5Ijjqi7jbc6pLtn3oiQ%2Fl83%2Be8bFhwTlEuUhOTPAiEA45ipQt%2Ft5%2BGEJO9HILzhyjBhGrSR98G%2FSYfdLEkAo60qiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDMQBHS2Lz5AgjU%2BCwyrcA2uSKjuUtdW7kmd88nHnT0dMG1Uzn4LFLqD1MaL603yEtjWkIA3CjM%2Fe7hCd%2BLM%2BEhDK69QAwPMYffs%2FatfCNCZgoXfxVsH5vkgSk7sTX3iL71RAS%2By8N3IBlUTAYR114pLFOEXBh0KkDbZwVIKxBkOzexzCpThuJ70LtymrEc4QRCGfPJxhzOzlKQ44QBFYZiuqgKdMMYNsto%2Ff03xdo9ymyMUmEm1i2gx9uvAhdu51%2BUTj23%2FabOe93jDRDI9zqh1Bl2xYDuqfybNBngM26DtxsGcpikLCSHUUi77%2FadEeFPLgcBl1erdn54xtz4cLHfKyg1Hff%2BtZsbLDkWGUfaHrxQS0FR7AavmIYtEBj52%2B24xOkuUVGXQEbdFrDX8X6o6A0YMVlX9WmU7rHhKTtTX5g3FgcNcAhrDtGBKqtche%2BZVbMv0DyWddMSN0FTE9Z2yAB%2FXGLCC3oTr379Jqt1NjPFqOrvMrAiTd2sIYXnI8TDJGIxd2kSkjfmxBRRGRvC1i8mY9%2Fd8n95%2BwdfyhDZq0i1satPf0Tv%2Bfh5LrsXfEGY7gzVS6SmDyP17tR9JJWvJSZ3nfSJOAk7XhWn6k%2BDspOTUpj75bFgpoL7J9zyKnRlgH61TZvPW25GxpMOmdrcQGOqUBMYZV%2FqDeYbl8iuDsCmEIPEMQOX16Un3ZxgdfZZUecYRc5XJynfhnj9UdFR2m21Vbwkm4b%2FQoklnyikH48L4BN%2BNbOjIWk6Js8B4HIND%2B3K8i0kzX0%2BU93WDPXELEEf46HbhPCs23N8pZYXk4rvm3jX8slXmjzLMKtiZTDaem1iPhIMQHZTifmddZc4xW%2FfWUTZj6mlHL%2BMvNID%2BDlNdL3li4Ote0&amp;X-Amz-Signature=9dfb6199d6e5911f94c4c6724906fe323a65122ef7c14e4cc4ca268c84509cea&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="cz1.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>From a young age, we're taught the value of steady, incremental progress. The idea is that like a determined tortoise, we can reach our goals by moving deliberately in the right direction. But could there be a more efficient approach?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-comfort-zone-a-default-state">The Comfort Zone a Default State<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/23/T00:00:00.000Z-Break%20Out%20Of%20The%20Comfort%20Zone:%20The%20Need%20for%20Big%20Leaps%20Over%20Incremental%20Improvements#the-comfort-zone-a-default-state" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Comfort Zone a Default State" title="Direct link to The Comfort Zone a Default State">​</a></h2>
<p>It's widely recognized that individuals typically operate within their comfort zones. But what exactly is the comfort zone? Here's a potential definition:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The comfort zone refers to a psychological state in which one feels familiar, safe, and at ease. It is the area of experience where a person operates in an anxiety-neutral condition, using a limited set of behaviors to deliver a steady level of performance, usually without any sense of risk or need for change.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sticking to what's familiar can often deter us from making significant strides in improving our lives. More often than not, we choose minor, incremental changes that don't veer too far from our routine.</p>
<p>This fondness for comfort zones isn't just personal—it extends into software development practices and product development too. Frequently, teams would rather make minor adjustments than take the risk of adopting an entirely new approach. This could be due to fear of failure, resistance to change, or simply not being aware of the potential benefits of a different approach.</p>
<p>Sure, these incremental changes are easier to manage and implement. They cause less disruption to our current systems and processes, letting us maintain stability and make small steps forward. But, they can also restrict our potential for innovation and growth. When we only focus on baby steps, we might overlook the chance to make a big leap that could bring about significant benefits.</p>
<p>This leads us to ask: Are these small improvements enough? Do they truly meet the needs of the team and the organization, or are they simply a safe and comfortable route that leads to average results?</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="signs-of-need-for-change">Signs of Need For change<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/23/T00:00:00.000Z-Break%20Out%20Of%20The%20Comfort%20Zone:%20The%20Need%20for%20Big%20Leaps%20Over%20Incremental%20Improvements#signs-of-need-for-change" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Signs of Need For change" title="Direct link to Signs of Need For change">​</a></h2>
<p>Let's consider some signs that may indicate the presence of comfort zones:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Stalled Progress</strong>: If we see little to no significant progress over a lengthy period, it could mean our team might be tweaking things without making a real impact. In this case, the next level of improvement could be further than anticipated.</li>
<li><strong>Reluctance towards new ideas</strong>: A quick dismissal or resistance to new suggestions can indicate a deep-rooted reluctance to change. This resistance is often due to the comfort of the familiar, fear of the unknown, and potential risks associated with change.</li>
<li><strong>Unchanging strategies</strong>: If we find ourselves continually resorting to the same solutions or minor variations of past strategies, it suggests that we're stuck in a comfort zone. A hesitation to try new approaches, especially when facing repetitive challenges, signals a comfort zone.</li>
</ul>
<p>Therefore, it's crucial to continually assess your team's adaptability. If there are signs of stagnation, resistance to change, or a lack of creative problem-solving, it may be time to challenge the comfort zone and think about making more substantial changes instead of small, incremental ones.</p>
<p>If you are already measuring the behavior, you will notice comfort zones can be represented as logarithmic functions.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/26a9ed95-154a-4067-93be-3e546a6b040e/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466S55LPARM%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115508Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIEcjj5Ijjqi7jbc6pLtn3oiQ%2Fl83%2Be8bFhwTlEuUhOTPAiEA45ipQt%2Ft5%2BGEJO9HILzhyjBhGrSR98G%2FSYfdLEkAo60qiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDMQBHS2Lz5AgjU%2BCwyrcA2uSKjuUtdW7kmd88nHnT0dMG1Uzn4LFLqD1MaL603yEtjWkIA3CjM%2Fe7hCd%2BLM%2BEhDK69QAwPMYffs%2FatfCNCZgoXfxVsH5vkgSk7sTX3iL71RAS%2By8N3IBlUTAYR114pLFOEXBh0KkDbZwVIKxBkOzexzCpThuJ70LtymrEc4QRCGfPJxhzOzlKQ44QBFYZiuqgKdMMYNsto%2Ff03xdo9ymyMUmEm1i2gx9uvAhdu51%2BUTj23%2FabOe93jDRDI9zqh1Bl2xYDuqfybNBngM26DtxsGcpikLCSHUUi77%2FadEeFPLgcBl1erdn54xtz4cLHfKyg1Hff%2BtZsbLDkWGUfaHrxQS0FR7AavmIYtEBj52%2B24xOkuUVGXQEbdFrDX8X6o6A0YMVlX9WmU7rHhKTtTX5g3FgcNcAhrDtGBKqtche%2BZVbMv0DyWddMSN0FTE9Z2yAB%2FXGLCC3oTr379Jqt1NjPFqOrvMrAiTd2sIYXnI8TDJGIxd2kSkjfmxBRRGRvC1i8mY9%2Fd8n95%2BwdfyhDZq0i1satPf0Tv%2Bfh5LrsXfEGY7gzVS6SmDyP17tR9JJWvJSZ3nfSJOAk7XhWn6k%2BDspOTUpj75bFgpoL7J9zyKnRlgH61TZvPW25GxpMOmdrcQGOqUBMYZV%2FqDeYbl8iuDsCmEIPEMQOX16Un3ZxgdfZZUecYRc5XJynfhnj9UdFR2m21Vbwkm4b%2FQoklnyikH48L4BN%2BNbOjIWk6Js8B4HIND%2B3K8i0kzX0%2BU93WDPXELEEf46HbhPCs23N8pZYXk4rvm3jX8slXmjzLMKtiZTDaem1iPhIMQHZTifmddZc4xW%2FfWUTZj6mlHL%2BMvNID%2BDlNdL3li4Ote0&amp;X-Amz-Signature=7ffc1b11fdab2107837efedef68e422fd9eec425099dbf3443459e29894f92e7&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="Untitled.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="implementing-change">Implementing Change<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/23/T00:00:00.000Z-Break%20Out%20Of%20The%20Comfort%20Zone:%20The%20Need%20for%20Big%20Leaps%20Over%20Incremental%20Improvements#implementing-change" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Implementing Change" title="Direct link to Implementing Change">​</a></h2>
<p>Recognizing the need for change is just the beginning. Here's how we can pave the way forward:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Spot key metrics</strong>: Initiate by spotting key metrics that accurately represent the area you're aiming to enhance. These metrics should be specific, measurable, and directly tied to the performance or behavior you're looking to improve.</li>
<li><strong>Gauge the current situation</strong>: Use these as a benchmark to contrast your future performance and evaluate the progress of your initiative.</li>
<li><strong>Set a North Star</strong>: Set a clear, ambitious yet attainable goal that will steer your efforts. This goal should push your team to step out of their comfort zone, but still be within reach. Ensure this goal is in line with your wider business objectives and resonates with your team members, providing them a strong incentive to aim for the initiative.</li>
<li><strong>Estimate the gap</strong>: Evaluate the difference between your current performance and your North Star. This is the distance your team needs to traverse to achieve the desired improvement. Understanding this gap will give you a clear sense of the scope of the change required and will help shape your strategy for the initiative.</li>
<li><strong>Plan the change</strong>: Having defined your key metrics and North Star, begin plotting the course required for the initiative. You will be faced with 2 options:<!-- -->
<ol>
<li><strong>Bold Move</strong>: Occasionally, a significant departure from the current state to your ultimate goal is necessary. Always consider this as your primary option.</li>
<li><strong>Gradual Progress</strong>: If the change appears overwhelming or too abrupt, reduce it by taking smaller steps towards your ultimate goal.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><strong>Review and Refine</strong>: Continually track your progress and compare it to your initial benchmark. Use this information to fine-tune your approach, adjust your strategy, and implement necessary modifications.</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/23/T00:00:00.000Z-Break%20Out%20Of%20The%20Comfort%20Zone:%20The%20Need%20for%20Big%20Leaps%20Over%20Incremental%20Improvements#final-thoughts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Final Thoughts" title="Direct link to Final Thoughts">​</a></h2>
<p>It's crucial to remember that change is not always easy, but it's often necessary for growth. Incremental improvements have their place, but occasionally, we need to take confident leaps to truly innovate and realize our full potential. By willing to step outside our comfort zones, we open ourselves up to new possibilities and opportunities for improvement. Next time you're with your team, ponder over these topics. It's vital to identify your guiding star to reach it.
For example, consider this in the context of your team's productivity. What practices could make you the most efficient team? For me, the answer was Extreme Programming (XP). You might contemplate a significant shift from individual development with pull requests to mob programming, and smaller steps towards adopting Trunk-Based Development due to the need for additional tools.</p>
<p>Also, don't hesitate to think creatively about product development. For instance, we often have to shift Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) to meet Objectives and Key Results (OKRs), like increasing the lead conversion percentage. If the leap percentage is high, you might need to implement revolutionary new strategies, rather than sticking with the status quo.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[T-Shaped players, what the Market Needs Now!]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/14/T03:00:00.000Z-T-Shaped players, what the Market Needs Now</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/14/T03:00:00.000Z-T-Shaped players, what the Market Needs Now"/>
        <updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the T-shaped model for professionals in tech and business, highlighting the blend of deep expertise and broad understanding that fosters success in complex, user-centric markets. Learn how this model encourages continuous learning, enhancement of job satisfaction, and increases marketability.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before starting this article, I would like to extend my thanks for reading, and also my apologies to for not being able to write last week. It was a busy but enriching week at some training where I actually learned quite a few things, I will share them here soon so stay tuned.</p>
<p>I will today release this short article, and expect a longer one towards the end of this week.</p>
<hr>
<p>Have you ever encountered professionals who seem to place importance only on a certain type of knowledge? It's a situation humorously depicted in this comic strip from CommitStrip.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/fd39b0b1-9017-499d-ae0e-71cd764be906/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466W7FIWCRH%2F20250227%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250227T120441Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEDsaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJIMEYCIQDBzesE11y7P%2BM8ixJ%2BEKXzf9WC%2FmQAS10cjNxA4OhbQAIhAMmihbRwfKCZ7RivObXWdiozOswxV0a1w1ClpUu6xn3WKv8DCHQQABoMNjM3NDIzMTgzODA1Igzx0GdVrB3paF%2Fq8k4q3APGWp8Y1dXekHWnEYCguRWlxcKKfYgsCDiGAPfLTtiOjktrKJBrqC%2BMVvcAFZ46O%2FHUw7D7NHzAS1VYsStCMad2zf7S0y0BK2vohw9H50Sdbxf6QGyzvYWK4mgr2ZjXbpmzRB3slKZ9clT%2BpsOKSF4CEGIXRdXC%2BEiFk81vDEyM8P9Qdp%2B5uahF1mizqEyNSurQx0uWBvc92hgB3Y3CSDnKkJLxEu0Ql0jPsWmMgV3Y%2BLa2ddn9nkGOZX59jZnwjoO5%2FOHK76B28jx3ZfGSyZdsmYZLCHAOEo0dU%2B5VahtcX6m0t4do0RgF7BZpNqpX8h96reI30x78sblU81RlKnSkQHyZzh8%2BAw%2BTcXHn691h6GS7p3LIvmsdD2%2BwdkFniwxZinMBUtBA9bP6eLD47K%2F7sDYobPqUoA2yBG9pONeamcCtJjyGgA6usyTQgQsghAJDGBZEaKE%2FoAvl0noGEtyGgJtRl1bEn4PcHQkBz2AWDwNr5B2MBfd4FLEbdkT3WosZKtPWxDp%2FgPpq54IWriwlPYGyM0N5JmHpui4%2FNTgyD3bMzfLTy6WlgrNezFxflZFVwkXoZ7HjtJRRTASvoF4HrH%2B%2BB23fjr%2BkiDPlzbVDlgXrS1y57HiVyGwzPDCLkYG%2BBjqkAaYcqAKZ1bobpbafr8RrnETJwmzk9zOyh1dKv5GITvygnttS%2B1S%2FHB4xDX50bX7pzNqLXX5Xrtcs2qC0eFvfioQmvQaCsPvqy5Q4tGLN02tUlw5PvT1dFxvUpPFrfv6tj6PB99OMRIhFvCbXcJcNFgr8kIN5fBLzS%2BLhiKQs3TzUS2su74hvOzQoLSzujxrUWNVSic6FMTeb4FXATF1RkAdqgWX3&amp;X-Amz-Signature=77ecf3baadb2ff04f54992bc3ae72e6809dc55ae3b495fc6474fc92382bbb738&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="https://www.commitstrip.com/en/2016/09/09/the-mistakes-of-youth/?setLocale=1" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>While expertise is certainly beneficial, it's not always a necessity in the market.  In the end, we need to ask ourselves the question if we are either “problem solvers” or “executing monkeys”.</p>
<p>The role of engineering professionals is evolving, moving from a sole focus on knowledge to an all-encompassing approach, represented by the “T-shaped” model. The objective is not just to build right, but to build what's necessary. This calls for a blend of product, technical, and interpersonal skills.
For leaders, this translates into promoting continuous learning, cross-functional teamwork, and advocating for stepping beyond comfort zones, thereby cultivating a culture that appreciates all facets of everyday work.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="t-shape-a-blend-of-breadth-and-depth">T-Shape: A Blend of Breadth and Depth<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/14/T03:00:00.000Z-T-Shaped%20players,%20what%20the%20Market%20Needs%20Now#t-shape-a-blend-of-breadth-and-depth" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to T-Shape: A Blend of Breadth and Depth" title="Direct link to T-Shape: A Blend of Breadth and Depth">​</a></h2>
<p>The T-shaped model is the idea that everyone should possess a depth of vertical expertise in their preferred area (the vertical bar of the “T”) while also having a broad horizontal understanding of ancillary areas (the horizontal bar of the “T”).
This dual focus ensures not only the capability to execute specific tasks but also the ability to see beyond and understand the larger context, ensuring that what is built is truly what is needed and also not selling snake oil.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="vertical-expertise-the-depth">Vertical Expertise: The Depth<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/14/T03:00:00.000Z-T-Shaped%20players,%20what%20the%20Market%20Needs%20Now#vertical-expertise-the-depth" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Vertical Expertise: The Depth" title="Direct link to Vertical Expertise: The Depth">​</a></h3>
<p>The vertical bar of the “T” serves as a symbol for an individual's core skill set, demonstrating their domain of deep expertise. It is their specialty, the area where they could be considered an expert or a specialist.
This deep expertise is what most people have traditionally concentrated on in their day-to-day professional lives. It's the strength that they bring to the table in their field and what they are known for.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="horizontal-skills-the-breadth">Horizontal Skills: The Breadth<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/14/T03:00:00.000Z-T-Shaped%20players,%20what%20the%20Market%20Needs%20Now#horizontal-skills-the-breadth" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Horizontal Skills: The Breadth" title="Direct link to Horizontal Skills: The Breadth">​</a></h3>
<p>The horizontal bar symbolizes the broad range of complementary skills outside of one's core expertise. This notably includes:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Product Sense</strong>: An understanding of the product's goals, target users, and market position. This involves empathy towards the user's needs, an appreciation of user experience (UX) principles, and the ability to prioritize features based on user and business value.</li>
<li><strong>Collaboration and Communication</strong>: The ability to work effectively with cross-functional teams, including product managers, designers, and other stakeholders. Clear communication of technical difficulties, solutions, and trade-offs in a way that is accessible to non-technical team members is vital.</li>
<li><strong>Business Acumen</strong>: A grasp of the business context in which the product operates. This includes understanding the competitive landscape, business models, and how one's work contributes to the overall success and strategy of the company.</li>
<li><strong>Adaptability and Learning</strong>: The capacity to quickly learn new skills, adapt to new tools, technologies, and methodologies as required by the ever-changing tech landscape.</li>
<li><strong>Any &amp; All Technical Knowledge</strong>: refers to a wide range of technical skills and understanding that one might need to do their job effectively. It emphasizes the need for individuals to be comfortable with various technologies and able to learn and adapt to new technical tools and methodologies as required.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="benefits-of-becoming-t-shaped">Benefits of becoming T-Shaped<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/14/T03:00:00.000Z-T-Shaped%20players,%20what%20the%20Market%20Needs%20Now#benefits-of-becoming-t-shaped" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Benefits of becoming T-Shaped" title="Direct link to Benefits of becoming T-Shaped">​</a></h2>
<p>Here are the benefits of becoming T-shaped:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Personal Growth</strong>: The T-shaped model encourages continuous learning and adaptation, leading to personal and professional development.</li>
<li><strong>Enhanced Job Satisfaction</strong>: Having a broader understanding of the product and the business can make the work more meaningful and satisfying.</li>
<li><strong>Increased Marketability</strong>: With a diverse set of skills, T-shaped people are more attractive to employers in a competitive job market.</li>
<li><strong>Job Security</strong>: The ability to adapt to new technologies and methodologies also provides more job security in a rapidly changing industry.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="rounding-up">Rounding Up<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/14/T03:00:00.000Z-T-Shaped%20players,%20what%20the%20Market%20Needs%20Now#rounding-up" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Rounding Up" title="Direct link to Rounding Up">​</a></h2>
<p>As you may have noticed, I am not naming development anywhere. T-shaped has already crossed that line, it's not only applicable to technical roles but also to business roles. Where, for example, to take decisions is not only valid anymore to not understand certain parts of the product.</p>
<p>In conclusion, T-shaped embodies the holistic skill set essential in today's dynamic product development environments. By fostering these all-rounded professionals, engineering leaders can ensure their teams are not just executing to spec but actively contributing to the creation of meaningful, impactful products. As we progress into increasingly complex and user-centric markets, the T-shaped approach will undoubtedly become not just beneficial, but essential for success.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="related-articles">Related Articles<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/14/T03:00:00.000Z-T-Shaped%20players,%20what%20the%20Market%20Needs%20Now#related-articles" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Related Articles" title="Direct link to Related Articles">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://leadshorizons.com/p/the-future-of-teams-crossfunctional-and-t-shaped" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">bookmark</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Make Remote Work, Great Again]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make Remote Work, Great Again</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make Remote Work, Great Again"/>
        <updated>2024-05-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the nuances of remote work in our in-depth analysis. Discover how the right strategies and tools can transform remote work into an effective, productive, and rewarding experience.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What is your stand on the location where you work from? Work location seems to have become a complex subject for companies and employees in the last year. With an imbalance in the demand for local and remote work, the issue merits discussion.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/d0c68370-26e8-43d4-b883-eeef626c5dbd/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466VDEZN2VN%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115508Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIQCjVYjb9rSrpWkUr7iEb8bbxZjW16KWHGk%2Fm88R5vJXvgIgcYyJNmfnim4I5g26Y4VkLIbEHDFdGVf%2FXDspRzHzCD4qiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDH1%2Bb19iT5qs%2B9DzSCrcAwdA%2BJZyJCGX6xqRvQWM1aTVyuQJz5LSVdiKVimCN8hikLOJwonDw64dbQabhsMylDeiAoFvMzZNV9DiL72d3E2wEfkyf5%2BNBhtqgUHmHo%2Ba6qU4CHBBfMX%2Broa58UV87GizFO%2Bc3FaGqvnAJ3ACBtmroJH4rRZTj7MrSrqo3SiYREafsfkT%2BGvjkc81K92ftjRLCXL9logjM%2F0y0b1uoZpVE1VuJvWWDd7%2BjD%2BSgCEcHet3OsdX6Io04QpqIIbRTe1WxA0Qf6%2B99ZPKO1ApGWug4ufK%2BCOdyCfXfBAdE5XIOZ%2FIu824s4QyeaDiMSI5cS7a%2F1%2FZ8pqoyUOlW3n5rb%2FbuvGJBS3RHuO1yyAMIpLVKKt%2FiMO1Wq%2FiEtlrucxyArh9cvqZMf7RqQQDleeHmhmKmWZuU9z8tllivS16hFFoQ%2F6eO65VDqMXwPh6Cb8bogAFf%2BVAr%2FDeiq5fCU6mpbee8MDg93WqsvDR%2Fu83IfksHHUJFeeFGwRKWfwSHmp0wdrqliah4Zzt65ywE%2B%2BJR8K3nKEu9N2RQ1NQTTlvm3G2Irdgnnhi6QRQVKpTVrh9IbdD3WpF7ksFW0lPW6lz9Ft87gbVFF4uVjL3cO3rMA2U%2FhmPT%2B%2Fa34jGqDLkMO2crcQGOqUBZL%2BGi7IDopGrNBqi27qsZbI1nIC0o%2BnxMNrGs5Zs39BvborYjD1lJTZDHMRPU0MLZYGUBeNZpwhcv%2BBxP2DzgciqMSeRvsrPPpIImjicC5Ic9%2FTlOKBsUOJUiZQ2XyKyVvD5bh2zSC1I9WknAuko2dSREbiuPSHWEVTrz9KSuuh1rgIfmuLzBXc1%2F1LQwvRSyhS27OcrbBxYtP48obRyXzshGj2y&amp;X-Amz-Signature=4a7a781cfa6fdde9db1e9984e91aa3f532259e9f05fd1994d8402f993887a824&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="Employers Offer Fewer Fully Remote Jobs and More Fully Onsite Jobs Than Employees Want — WFH Research [1]" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Reflecting on my professional journey, I have had the opportunity to explore various work modalities. From my early days in on-site environments, savoring technical discussions around me, to remote work across different regions, embracing the nomadic lifestyle and thriving in multicultural settings.</p>
<p>Let's delve into this topic further in the article.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="work-location-in-the-past-5-years">Work Location in the past 5 Years<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make%20Remote%20Work,%20Great%20Again#work-location-in-the-past-5-years" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Work Location in the past 5 Years" title="Direct link to Work Location in the past 5 Years">​</a></h2>
<p>Let's address an important aspect first. Remote work isn't a novel concept that emerged during the COVID-19 pandemic. In fact, I've been working remotely from various locations including France, Spain, and the USA since 2016. The tools and infrastructure for remote work, however, have definitely evolved over time.</p>
<p>Before the pandemic, the majority of companies preferred on-site operations and invested heavily in office spaces to meet their employees' needs.</p>
<p>However, the pandemic essentially forced a large-scale social experiment in remote work. The majority of us had to adapt to working from home. Surprisingly, it turned out to be quite effective!</p>
<p>However, as the pandemic winds down, there's an increasing push from companies to revert to the pre-pandemic model. Interestingly, many employees are reluctant to give up the benefits of work-life balance they've experienced during this period (less commute, more family time, more personal time, etc).</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-different-modalities-of-work">The different modalities of Work<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make%20Remote%20Work,%20Great%20Again#the-different-modalities-of-work" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The different modalities of Work" title="Direct link to The different modalities of Work">​</a></h2>
<p>Before we delve further into the topic, let's look at the different work models.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>On-Site</strong>: This is the conventional work model where employees need to be physically present at a particular location, often an office, to do their work.
This means the employee needs to be in the same city as the company at all times.</li>
<li><strong>Hybrid</strong>: This flexible model blends on-site and remote work. Employees might work from home some days and be in the office on others.
This usually means the employee needs to be in the same city as the company.
Some subtypes include:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><strong>Weekly days at the office</strong>: set days are designated as either on-site or remote.</li>
<li><strong>Flexible hybrid</strong>: the individual can choose the best place to work at any given moment, but there is a quota for on-site time.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Remote</strong>: Here, employees work from outside the traditional office environment such as from home, a co-working space, or any other location with internet access.
This doesn't require the employee to be in the same city as the company.
Some subtypes include:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><strong>Quarterly days</strong>: A certain quota needs to be met within a specific timeframe that enables the person to work remotely.</li>
<li><strong>On-demand travel</strong>: There are instances where travel is needed for significant interactions that require groups of people to collaborate.</li>
<li><strong>Full remote</strong>: unless it's necessary, the employee doesn't need to travel at any particular time.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As we can see, there are subtle differences that separate a Hybrid from a Remote work model. The deciding factor that differentiates one from the other is the employee's ability to be located in the same city or nearby.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="excuses-to-go-back-to-the-office">Excuses to go back to the office<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make%20Remote%20Work,%20Great%20Again#excuses-to-go-back-to-the-office" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Excuses to go back to the office" title="Direct link to Excuses to go back to the office">​</a></h2>
<p>Some of the reasons that can be affecting the current situation:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Distrust of Employees</strong>: Some companies might harbor concerns about the potential lack of productivity when employees work remotely. These concerns stem from the belief that without direct supervision, employees might be more prone to distractions or unproductive behaviors. Working from home introduces a complexity to the monitoring of employees that some companies dislike.</li>
<li><strong>Cultural Concerns</strong>: A strong, cohesive company culture is often considered a key factor in a business's success. Some companies believe that this culture can only be fostered through face-to-face interactions and shared experiences that come with working in the same physical space. They worry that remote work might dilute this culture, making it harder to maintain shared values, facilitate team bonding, and encourage a sense of belonging among employees.</li>
<li><strong>Performance Changes</strong>: The shift to remote work can bring about changes in employees' performance. This is a complex matter as employee performance does not have a single definition, and as we will see later in this article, it can be driven not only by the person but by their environment.</li>
<li><strong>Office Investments</strong>: Companies that have invested substantial amounts of money in their office spaces may feel compelled to make use of these investments. These investments could include not just the physical office space itself, but also equipment, furniture, and other amenities designed to make the office a comfortable, productive environment. The continued payment for office rents, maintenance, and utilities while the space remains largely unused can also be a motivating factor to return to the office.</li>
<li><strong>Investor Contributions</strong>: In an investment landscape, investors often diversify their investments as a risk management strategy. A significant portion of these investments may be allocated to real estate, directly or indirectly, through various investment funds. If the workforce shifts towards remote work, the demand for these office spaces could decrease, leading to potential implications on the return on investment for these real estate investments. Therefore, the trend towards remote work can have a broader impact on the investment community.</li>
<li><strong>Community Impact</strong>: The presence of office districts in cities and towns has resulted in the creation of numerous jobs in various sectors. The local economy in these districts frequently thrives on the regular influx of office-goers. This includes a wide range of businesses such as restaurants, cafés, fitness centers, and retail stores, all of which rely substantially on the footfall generated by employees working in nearby offices. These businesses can be significantly influenced if more people transition to remote work. As the footfall decreases, these businesses may struggle to sustain themselves, leading to potential job losses and broader socio-economic implications.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="debunking-concerns">Debunking Concerns<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make%20Remote%20Work,%20Great%20Again#debunking-concerns" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Debunking Concerns" title="Direct link to Debunking Concerns">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="distrust-of-employees--performance-changes"><strong>Distrust of Employees &amp; Performance Changes</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make%20Remote%20Work,%20Great%20Again#distrust-of-employees--performance-changes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to distrust-of-employees--performance-changes" title="Direct link to distrust-of-employees--performance-changes">​</a></h3>
<p>While personal skepticism can influence views, performance assessments should be driven by solid data. With that in mind, let's delve into some of the available data:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One ground-breaking Stanford study on the subject, which included 16,000 participants, found a marked increase in remote employee output—even for employees who only worked from home a few days a week. During the study, the telecommuting group displayed a 13% average improvement in performance over the office-based control.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://qz.com/1627980/remote-work-can-boost-productivity-if-you-have-the-right-tools" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Source</a></p>
<p>While we possess this data, it's important to note that our employees' performance can fluctuate between different work modalities.</p>
<p>In both Remote and On-site work environments, everyone operates under the same modality, thus establishing a unified workflow. Conversely, the Hybrid mode can introduce complications. This is due to certain sub-categories that we've discussed, where some individuals are local and others are remote. Such a dynamic can inadvertently impact the performance of remote workers, not through any fault of their own, but due to potential exclusion or differential treatment.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="cultural-concerns"><strong>Cultural Concerns</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make%20Remote%20Work,%20Great%20Again#cultural-concerns" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to cultural-concerns" title="Direct link to cultural-concerns">​</a></h3>
<p>The cultural concern is normally embodied by the phrase:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>There are things that happen in the office, that don't happen in remote</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The concept here is that specific discussions occur naturally in a local setting. Hybrid work capitalizes on this by emphasizing the value of office days when such interactions can take place. However, a common concern among hybrid employees is that they spend a substantial portion of their office time on remote calls.</p>
<p>Conversely, effective communication and the right tools are crucial for remote work to ensure these interactions can be replicated. This is an area many companies are still struggling to address effectively.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="office-investments"><strong>Office Investments</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make%20Remote%20Work,%20Great%20Again#office-investments" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to office-investments" title="Direct link to office-investments">​</a></h3>
<p>Investments, particularly in real estate, are often expected to grow over time; hence they can be complex. It's essential to distinguish companies between two groups based on their ownership of the space:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Owners</strong>: As outright owners of the physical space, this asset is a key component of their balance sheet. Naturally, they'll want to maximize its value, as it directly impacts their valuation.</li>
<li><strong>Renters</strong>: With temporary ownership, the space represents an ongoing cost that they need to manage. Minimizing this cost can significantly enhance their profit margins.</li>
</ul>
<p>As you might expect, each group has a distinct focus. On-Site will likely appeal to Owners, while Remote will be more beneficial for Renters.</p>
<p>As you can see and</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="addressing-remote-concerns-make-remote-work">Addressing Remote Concerns: Make Remote Work<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make%20Remote%20Work,%20Great%20Again#addressing-remote-concerns-make-remote-work" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Addressing Remote Concerns: Make Remote Work" title="Direct link to Addressing Remote Concerns: Make Remote Work">​</a></h2>
<p>From our observations, the primary concern stems from the absence of a unified approach and a shared workspace.</p>
<p>As a company, to surmount these challenges, we can adhere to a few key principles:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="remote-first">Remote First<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make%20Remote%20Work,%20Great%20Again#remote-first" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Remote First" title="Direct link to Remote First">​</a></h3>
<p>The guiding principle of this work model is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If one person is remote, everyone is remote</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This approach aims to treat all employees equally, irrespective of their location. Every process, ranging from meetings to casual conversations, should be designed keeping remote employees in mind. This method ensures that remote workers are not sidelined or disadvantaged compared to their on-site peers.</p>
<p>To this end, investing in the right collaborative tools is crucial so that everyone has the same access and capabilities. Here are some tools you might need:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Virtual White Boards</strong>: Most meetings involve some form of interaction that typically takes place on whiteboards in an office setting. If we use a physical whiteboard in conjunction with a conferencing tool, we risk limiting the involvement of remote participants. Therefore, having a virtual alternative is necessary. A good example of this is <a href="http://miro.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Miro</a>, where you can invite people to collaborate live on various types of boards</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Pairing Software</strong>: To work efficiently in pair or mob programming, we should simplify collaboration as if everyone were working on the same machine. Code with me from IntelliJ is an example of this.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lq0fCMCK-Yw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lq0fCMCK-Yw</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Collaborative Knowledge Base: It's important to have a centralized location for team and company information. However, many tools are rigid and lack concurrent editing capabilities. We need to ensure we choose the right tool for our needs. Personally, I've found <a href="http://notion.so/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Notion</a> quite useful.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Collaborative Documents: Just like our knowledge base, we need the ability to concurrently edit documents like presentations and spreadsheets when preparing for presentations or budget cycles. Google and Microsoft offer robust products with the necessary features.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Async Communication Tools: All workers need their focus time, so having the right tools for asynchronous communication, including a chat application and traditional email, is essential.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The last three tools are not exclusively for remote work but are important for any work mode.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="virtual-office">Virtual office<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make%20Remote%20Work,%20Great%20Again#virtual-office" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Virtual office" title="Direct link to Virtual office">​</a></h3>
<p>Much like a physical office promotes interaction and collaboration, a virtual office offers an online shared space for employees to engage, collaborate, and foster relationships.</p>
<p>This isn't merely about conferencing tools, but about the creation of social environments with virtual desks and communal areas. These tools enable employees to engage in organic conversations when close to another's virtual desk, relax in virtual coffee spaces, indulge in games, and more. Gather.town is a prime example of such a tool.</p>
<p>It's also worth noting the cost-effectiveness of virtual offices compared to traditional physical spaces.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zbllvQZRyh0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">video</a></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="parting-words">Parting words<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/05/01/T22:00:00.000Z-Make%20Remote%20Work,%20Great%20Again#parting-words" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Parting words" title="Direct link to Parting words">​</a></h2>
<p>Remote work has the potential to be as effective as in-office work, offering employees better work-life balance without compromising the company culture that we hold dear. Like many challenges in our industry, successful remote work hinges on using the right tools. The traditional tools used for in-person work may not be suitable for this new dynamic.</p>
<p>To be candid, hybrid work models often fall short in numerous ways, often representing a compromise rather than an ideal solution. In my view, hybrid models are the most challenging to manage and their impacts are not always evident.</p>
<p>Given this, it's essential that we reassess the paths our companies are taking. We may be inadvertently hindering our own potential due to a few manageable concerns.</p>
<p>[1] <a href="https://wfhresearch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/WFHResearch_updates_April2024.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://wfhresearch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/WFHResearch_updates_April2024.pdf</a></p>
<p>[2] <a href="https://qz.com/1627980/remote-work-can-boost-productivity-if-you-have-the-right-tools" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://qz.com/1627980/remote-work-can-boost-productivity-if-you-have-the-right-tools</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unpacking the Truth of Peer Reviews in the Software Industry]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking the Truth of Peer Reviews in the Software Industry</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking the Truth of Peer Reviews in the Software Industry"/>
        <updated>2024-04-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Dive into the world of peer review in software development. Discover how it's more than just pull requests and explore the efficiency of pair programming backed by research data. Learn how peer reviews can improve quality, foster collaboration, and enhance team dynamics in various roles, from design to leadership.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I currently feel like the odd one, out. It appears that many people are associating peer review in software with code reviews via pull requests. Do you also share this perspective?</p>
<p>Even before I transitioned into leadership roles, where coding took on a secondary function, I did not engage in pull requests. In fact, I haven't submitted a pull request in a professional context since 2017.</p>
<p>Let's delve into the nuances of the peer review process in this article.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="understanding-peer-review">Understanding Peer Review<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking%20the%20Truth%20of%20Peer%20Reviews%20in%20the%20Software%20Industry#understanding-peer-review" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Understanding Peer Review" title="Direct link to Understanding Peer Review">​</a></h2>
<p>Peer reviews, also commonly referred to as peer assessments, involve a rigorous and structured process whereby a professional's work or research is evaluated and critiqued by one or more individuals who possess similar competencies, educational background, and expertise. This concept and methodology of peer review originated and took root in the academic sphere, where it is routinely employed as a critical tool to appraise and judge the value of scholarly outputs and research findings.</p>
<p>The primary function of this system is to serve as a form of quality control, significantly bolstering the credibility, reliability, and overall accuracy of the work that is being reviewed. This is achieved by providing an additional level of scrutiny, thereby eliminating any potential errors or oversight that might have been missed by the original author.</p>
<p>Fundamentally, peer review is a cooperative and collaborative process. It is meticulously designed to enhance the quality of work produced, encourage continuous learning and improvement among professionals, and support the establishment and maintenance of objectivity. It ensures that the work produced adheres to the highest standards of excellence, providing an essential layer of accountability in professional settings.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="software-development-peer-reviews">Software Development Peer Reviews<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking%20the%20Truth%20of%20Peer%20Reviews%20in%20the%20Software%20Industry#software-development-peer-reviews" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Software Development Peer Reviews" title="Direct link to Software Development Peer Reviews">​</a></h2>
<p>Within software development, peer reviews often manifest as code reviews. This involves a developer scrutinizing a software project's source code to identify bugs, errors, or potential enhancements. It's about more than just pinpointing issues—it's also about understanding varied methodologies and learning from colleagues.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="types-of-code-review">Types of Code Review<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking%20the%20Truth%20of%20Peer%20Reviews%20in%20the%20Software%20Industry#types-of-code-review" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Types of Code Review" title="Direct link to Types of Code Review">​</a></h3>
<p>I want to emphasize this point, as it appears that the contemporary software development scene may not fully grasp it.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Code reviews aren't always synonymous with Pull Requests 🤯</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let's delve into the alternatives:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/503307b1-972e-4006-8987-2f81eaa0849f/peer_review.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466TXTDZXAE%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115508Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIQDp7cQ3wh7CTeoCCgaoakm0%2BhutFa3xok02MwxiVB2ADAIgEVBFUQpBstVJFCUS2HEv7o%2BPtvUw1bDG%2BAkG0n2wStgqiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDIEr9zsbzIwAimHHXircAz42ZPYHWz86V97UIspB8uhhR1pOpVWSkrDVCwxVbkSOXMPUsepo5rLr%2FsR5Aou1Dsa8N7fmwDWkh0eloIIQzLlIMRnhdV%2FZTML6WIemaEmf42BL92%2BGWqLtYYz301TfaA664JyLO%2BS0y2wVfTKkwCaoiHhwnxgrUMchQ1FCSuWHBAeXkt13rHzHfjG9%2B2fvtGss2UrroK9cZIGdepts%2F6qSUgPXWUowqMnIdtg0DGFX8a4LxVyUipgqQJlqo0UcjhdhbpGdEIIVKh8nQPQSNmk3VAY2Zd4XXUTbUgSYJhfNSRMNj%2Bjv18Q7tGRK1qMeHq%2FOKd%2Fh3Dl2Xh86E4OX7FjWFF8hcBvAQzPDHXJp4Vq3HIO7KMMJcKD%2Fpv8ckDH0BaYwFFj%2FBKEZITSlog4YQ6IkwGlFk0Rh1E5Rd4cqgeMMpuo%2FzcU1UeJKaBnpFJVon9vAVGAazGNXcer%2FFoVSjcna7DVK2AA14u0VfFMAHWfxdF78hDkBcNb10PfKi4ZYasrILM4xwo4UFUxDCBR12kGXsDUoYpJxXRZ40ltOyBPbaSSiG0Ke27UfRlbnhlGLvH%2B0E0zZDQvQBzCxMvgwRwfi7JfwuExoG1l2pRC37Hrqh0VOKvcB%2BRXQvBi7MJ2drcQGOqUBmvzUHUWlrG44EOLodvRDaHYdeVCeJdeQDqT2vfR%2BPUWV0s8YwRQgO1vBJAcQhXR2j16YnqC5w9j0lMj3Xe5k5QpsqUSyzRQmtHlJ8uzdpDzK0uPHmOO3cs2bMzZtsOjkoHuA464y%2Fa0ZA8zKuOUd8cBA4TRZ3dWMcC0jADb1KfIkQDChRDmZ1BEw2lWt6NMtyl3tcOUIiBrQH7GUjOo16DcEWt7Z&amp;X-Amz-Signature=8f3964a377a76fdc00fe1774b123f152fd2f37c57e2884be98f0355543a2c313&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="peer_review.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Kent Beck has offered a two-dimensional perspective on the types of peer reviews in his <a href="https://tidyfirst.substack.com/p/thinking-about-code-review" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">article</a>. The two dimensions are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Synchronicity: Refers to the timing of the review process. It can occur in real-time as the code is being written (synchronous) or after the author has completed the code (asynchronous).</li>
<li>Continuity: Considers the workflow in relation to the review process. It can either allow the author to continue working (non-Blocking), or require the author to pause until the review is completed (Blocking).</li>
</ul>
<p>Let's explore what does each of this peer review means:</p>
<ul>
<li>Formal Review: A formal review is a thorough and systematic evaluation of a project, product, or performance. It is often conducted by a group of qualified individuals and follows a specific procedure or set of criteria.</li>
<li>Pull Request: A Pull Request is a feature in version control systems, like Git, where a developer proposes changes to a codebase. The request is a way to communicate the changes to the team and ask for review and integration into the main code branch.</li>
<li>Over The Shoulder Review: This is an informal method of code review where one developer looks over the author's shoulder as the latter walks through the code.</li>
<li>Code Comments:  In this approach, developers annotate the source code with comments. These comments offer insights, point out potential issues, and suggest improvements.</li>
<li>Pair Programming: This is a method where two programmers work simultaneously at one workstation. The “driver” writes the code, while the “observer” reviews each line of code as it's being written.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-relation-between-feedback-cycle--waste">The Relation Between Feedback Cycle &amp; Waste<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking%20the%20Truth%20of%20Peer%20Reviews%20in%20the%20Software%20Industry#the-relation-between-feedback-cycle--waste" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Relation Between Feedback Cycle &amp; Waste" title="Direct link to The Relation Between Feedback Cycle &amp; Waste">​</a></h3>
<p>Inherent to the process of peer reviewing is its role as a “quality” gate. As such, many these processes tend to fall into the blocking quadrant of operational procedures. This characteristic of peer reviews can create situations where individuals become idle, waiting for the process to be unblocked. This idle time is not only detrimental to productivity, but can also affect morale and engagement among team members if they span over time. Therefore, it is important to streamline the feedback cycle to minimize these idle periods and maintain efficient workflow dynamics.</p>
<p>In addition, the involvement of a second individual to review the work is also necessary for any type of peer review process. Implying that the longer the feedback cycle between the generation of code and its review, leads to an increase in waste and rework. This is due to the fact that the longer the delay in feedback, the greater the potential for the initial work to diverge from the optimal path, necessitating more significant changes and revisions later on.</p>
<p>Therefore, it is crucial to establish a swift and efficient feedback cycle in peer review processes. By doing so, we not only reduce the likelihood of waste and rework, but also enhance the overall productivity and effectiveness of our teams.</p>
<p>If we take this into account, we want to be as much as possible in the sync &amp; non-blocking quadrant, as the synchronicity causes a small feedback cycle and the non-blocking minimizes the IDLEs.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/1293ddd5-7e74-4e39-a041-3bc532d3d432/peer_review2.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466TXTDZXAE%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115508Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIQDp7cQ3wh7CTeoCCgaoakm0%2BhutFa3xok02MwxiVB2ADAIgEVBFUQpBstVJFCUS2HEv7o%2BPtvUw1bDG%2BAkG0n2wStgqiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDIEr9zsbzIwAimHHXircAz42ZPYHWz86V97UIspB8uhhR1pOpVWSkrDVCwxVbkSOXMPUsepo5rLr%2FsR5Aou1Dsa8N7fmwDWkh0eloIIQzLlIMRnhdV%2FZTML6WIemaEmf42BL92%2BGWqLtYYz301TfaA664JyLO%2BS0y2wVfTKkwCaoiHhwnxgrUMchQ1FCSuWHBAeXkt13rHzHfjG9%2B2fvtGss2UrroK9cZIGdepts%2F6qSUgPXWUowqMnIdtg0DGFX8a4LxVyUipgqQJlqo0UcjhdhbpGdEIIVKh8nQPQSNmk3VAY2Zd4XXUTbUgSYJhfNSRMNj%2Bjv18Q7tGRK1qMeHq%2FOKd%2Fh3Dl2Xh86E4OX7FjWFF8hcBvAQzPDHXJp4Vq3HIO7KMMJcKD%2Fpv8ckDH0BaYwFFj%2FBKEZITSlog4YQ6IkwGlFk0Rh1E5Rd4cqgeMMpuo%2FzcU1UeJKaBnpFJVon9vAVGAazGNXcer%2FFoVSjcna7DVK2AA14u0VfFMAHWfxdF78hDkBcNb10PfKi4ZYasrILM4xwo4UFUxDCBR12kGXsDUoYpJxXRZ40ltOyBPbaSSiG0Ke27UfRlbnhlGLvH%2B0E0zZDQvQBzCxMvgwRwfi7JfwuExoG1l2pRC37Hrqh0VOKvcB%2BRXQvBi7MJ2drcQGOqUBmvzUHUWlrG44EOLodvRDaHYdeVCeJdeQDqT2vfR%2BPUWV0s8YwRQgO1vBJAcQhXR2j16YnqC5w9j0lMj3Xe5k5QpsqUSyzRQmtHlJ8uzdpDzK0uPHmOO3cs2bMzZtsOjkoHuA464y%2Fa0ZA8zKuOUd8cBA4TRZ3dWMcC0jADb1KfIkQDChRDmZ1BEw2lWt6NMtyl3tcOUIiBrQH7GUjOo16DcEWt7Z&amp;X-Amz-Signature=bb983e8fca5de0b8adb136b32a09a754c6dba6a3039c8f108f8f3b494552c08d&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="peer_review2.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="debunking-pair-programming-myths">Debunking Pair Programming Myths<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking%20the%20Truth%20of%20Peer%20Reviews%20in%20the%20Software%20Industry#debunking-pair-programming-myths" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Debunking Pair Programming Myths" title="Direct link to Debunking Pair Programming Myths">​</a></h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Why're then we not all doing pair programming?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Pair programming is often misunderstood and associated with numerous fallacies, specially in the realm of efficiency of project resources and velocity. With this in mind, let's review the studies:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://collaboration.csc.ncsu.edu/laurie/Papers/XPSardinia.PDF" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Costs and Benefits of Pair Programming</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The significant benefits of pair programming are that:<br>
<!-- -->• many mistakes get caught as they are being typed in rather than in QA test or in the field (continuous code reviews);<br>
<!-- -->• the end defect content is statistically lower (continuous code reviews);<br>
<!-- -->• the designs are better and code length shorter (ongoing brainstorming and pair relaying);<br>
<!-- -->• the team solves problems faster (pair relaying);<br>
<!-- -->• the people learn significantly more, about the system and about software development (line- of-sight learning);<br>
<!-- -->• the project ends up with multiple people understanding each piece of the system;<br>
<!-- -->• the people learn to work together and talk more often together, giving better information flow and team dynamics;<br>
<!-- -->• people enjoy their work more.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The development cost for these benefits is not the 100% that might be expected, but is
approximately 15%. This is repaid in shorter and less expensive testing, quality assurance, and field support.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/77168f39-fda7-4799-bfd2-36fb3ff5cd01/peer_review3.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466URY2E3ZF%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115509Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJIMEYCIQC7To7cB%2F8Vdpx3%2BaM3tD6foEHxsNfd%2BocVe%2FKyrV8ZtAIhAP3Mev4bCydau8Q366jXxxOogroNIcTb7%2BzLUqJjURJYKogECNT%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEQABoMNjM3NDIzMTgzODA1Igyu1nIWmHnPd%2Feyiukq3AOHJ8%2Fy%2BXgQcPqk1HbCj3izAFk6JhvZpON8LIDB2%2FZ7pcNXEU2gqa7NJp6SBdxv19AMUg1saGkQdk3asYI2rtFEHIzJWhuAM0lYUa44GrC6EfvT6fkYMzDOeDE%2ByrCZzBYp2YKxI53VizZ4oMDHIZXoycIgX%2Bm6vzfJlNrmgvsCnYnoYhuPHHZNJmW60RSVRSuhnTa56SZo%2BnWCCLRZZUVopY1pBBEnGqPxAEvpaTepT16pq5nYxKmO%2FPYDEjPavUWqoHxqD%2BxYxjrcZsP3VNldQyGoKU9W%2F%2BoUHCvE5dn9Pe%2FmsPBX9gnu5iQvgtzGin4R5FNHviU7XtP36rcIHu%2BtOydHSAqwvbCPz89x3eYx%2BS3X4BF7kxLP048mFChkvS9bWT5ztJsqXPbgiNl2%2FzAa97AySMV3zsBLhs08JAouQWHP5zVJY53iTxTN%2FwrJQ%2BfwmbnGyGXpHUo9pe4SealwbQPYVHQUOFZtpOKAp%2B22axrP9tfU4KDMhU5EdbDOpE7tI%2BQ45fpHB855nsCv3d7Wm1JMWzt6iVVPP48dbebodu%2F1ba8zf%2BxBd%2BOdAOeXkvRb34WAzisrpdPF1U%2BQl%2BlBeSj6irtK90SAwdGKRsteQj%2B6B4ccAXD3cF6KHjDHnK3EBjqkASt%2FTtv1153WPNWCaOgn7JJYADQDjkZGboTAuPQJz4lqXcDic18M6RKVyOvgKxBU9XZqs6cGbRFe2l1Gx6Pq8aayA%2BRL57Q8W3Q3U0oGgdvOUyzED4n42Dqrh7zGkHvhZw4Zc3LZPalfDcNewK%2BxVWO6D4bbPGBwqmQmZep9zngpXP4JgiWxc%2B2aMwtOgcjjqPU9is58yJgufrZIPc6vLN2MF3Ku&amp;X-Amz-Signature=71bd3237e7cf49af14f563868175493d4ce7210ddeb00d5d9496130737e13dac&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="peer_review3.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27295641_The_Case_for_Collaborative_Programming" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Case for Collaborative Programming</a>: Teams completed their task 40% <em>faster</em> than the individuals (and this result was statistically significant).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A field experiment was conducted using experienced programmers who worked on<br>
<!-- -->a challenging problem important to their organization, in their own<br>
<!-- -->environments, and with their own equipment. Findings revealed that all the<br>
<!-- -->teams outperformed the individual programmers, enjoyed the problem-solving<br>
<!-- -->process more, and had greater confidence in their solutions.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/4ac2c4d0-1a01-49e8-bade-23657d2d1e64/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB4667YX3YWSA%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115510Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIQDiLKR%2B6B%2BxQzH4jXnNkMcd1nFxIN0EhyXN7XqN0hYrmQIgc9Ih4ctUIkYeOgKnZQBXuQbiCkdBCRi4tvCRUeT%2FaL8qiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDIpZpBkAyPFy0hT7cyrcA8MrzFOy1X3kvVz2kBRK0FQmCdx%2FQpt8VK2HO2viHK%2BqYz5SOU72QExvsU49nzzXOv9%2FcmlOwcEGtoexmJuj%2FIG3Ee3s66ODNHrt7TjGgJQoG0kjlDggGzQDVAeUFQT3B4Mpny4UtY0vC9L19tMMZZ5TGWkP5%2F%2F5qrgsP2ken0q6orHRwc0OM4R7GutZqF1RU01jIgUv%2Biiv3%2FKWA3zH4vfPbH5yNxWCGMXnkkOMuY3SPI78lxt9lIUyOsM7OyrEWQlGoqhzr2fpZCruKYjiQ17hpdcliEABTD6Akv6OJ9fV%2BQTqvsWw7XtUkmQJ3k4Xr2xEIjUN4SKgRJGaZWSgcVJzUPPOhpDh6vcFTlreWACZPBttVdozZVDGCUINBcFSCSha3XzjOMiSdGEPA03Riqzf%2FKKYG3PaoKuf95UfPpIlR6JYWV8zmaMLhgURuzVfbnRQr9oR6vc58ltBS8i4pxQUc5m9OhalNhF1F2Ayd8nkONIWvl%2FzXtkFP82ux%2F%2FEK66034p%2BoX2oIn%2Fg4U0PnU6UdlD6d88izV%2BLccBUzdfE5PHsQKQVtrGtDxzvhT86%2FVRyFF9uWQ%2F2GxW9OTc5SAHeMVo76GpubGgy6bzB4HwMCEGzzINArY7cz6zfMKSdrcQGOqUBWcqy79GNeghPxKyOrBLWe3IVk5bdJ4cDye%2FIkF8wh58YN%2FMUoWAry6YFnm3YQNrPQmCfk9SPYkWF%2BCEJq0AGcgMbP%2Fb5lvvNEgLEAJqnaDxImBqkDwNQ1QLTjBypWvyO%2Fv5F9mbum%2BQt9E9Onzbgci9B4e2CBhRQSYEeAmYPpwkwfACFKhs7eNby%2FYg7%2FK%2Fp55f3tuMewMRxu9DQm4K%2FJcnVgyHz&amp;X-Amz-Signature=a4b1309a3759705f1b4b5d2f51bfd8b2360efe7ceaf05825087e9d70d94bf272&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="Untitled.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Management Impact on Software Cost and Schedule: Regarding the performance of pairs vs individuals:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Final project results were outstanding.  Total productivity was 175 lines<br>
<!-- -->per person-month (lppm) compared to a documented average individual<br>
<!-- -->productivity of only 77 llpm.<br>
<!-- -->[…]<br>
<!-- -->The error rate […] was three orders of magnitude lower than the<br>
<!-- -->organization’s norm.</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="http://www.cs.utah.edu/~lwilliam/Papers/ICSE.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Collaborative Software Process</a>: One key finding was that pairs took 15% more developer hours to produce their solutions, but those solutions had 15% fewer bugs.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>An experiment was run in 1999 with approximately 40 senior Computer Science<br>
<!-- -->students at the University of Utah. Two-thirds of the students worked in<br>
<!-- -->two-person collaborative teams […]. The other students worked<br>
<!-- -->independently […] to develop the same assignments.  The productivity,<br>
<!-- -->cycle time, and quality of the two groups have been compared. Empirical<br>
<!-- -->results point in favor of the collaborative teams […].</p>
</blockquote>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Having reviewed the data, it's important to recognize that our industry leans against this technique not due to the data, but for other subconscious underlying reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>The data might seem counterintuitive.</li>
<li>The available tools are more attuned to a different technique (pull requests).</li>
<li>Given our inherent social tendencies, there's a psychological aspect to consider that we believe spending too much time with a person is not enjoyable.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="pairing-in-other-engineering-roles">Pairing in Other Engineering Roles<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking%20the%20Truth%20of%20Peer%20Reviews%20in%20the%20Software%20Industry#pairing-in-other-engineering-roles" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Pairing in Other Engineering Roles" title="Direct link to Pairing in Other Engineering Roles">​</a></h2>
<p>Pairing can be applied effectively in these roles in the following ways:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="design">Design<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking%20the%20Truth%20of%20Peer%20Reviews%20in%20the%20Software%20Industry#design" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Design" title="Direct link to Design">​</a></h3>
<p>In design, pairing can be used for brainstorming, critiquing, and refining design concepts. This includes sketching, prototyping, user testing, and iterating on designs. Pairing helps to bring multiple perspectives to a design problem, leading to more innovative and inclusive solutions.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="product">Product<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking%20the%20Truth%20of%20Peer%20Reviews%20in%20the%20Software%20Industry#product" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Product" title="Direct link to Product">​</a></h3>
<p>In product roles, pairing can be beneficial during product planning, strategy discussions, and execution. Two product managers can collaborate to define the product roadmap, prioritize features, and make decisions based on customer feedback and data analysis. Pairing can lead to more robust product strategies and better decision-making.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="leadership">Leadership<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking%20the%20Truth%20of%20Peer%20Reviews%20in%20the%20Software%20Industry#leadership" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Leadership" title="Direct link to Leadership">​</a></h3>
<p>In leadership roles, pairing can be used for decision-making, strategic planning, and problem-solving. Two leaders can work together to guide their team or company, make critical business decisions, and navigate complex challenges. Pairing in leadership can foster a culture of collaboration, improve communication, and lead to better outcomes for the team and organization.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/25/T00:00:00.000Z-Unpacking%20the%20Truth%20of%20Peer%20Reviews%20in%20the%20Software%20Industry#closing-thoughts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Closing thoughts" title="Direct link to Closing thoughts">​</a></h2>
<p>Peer review, in software development, is a critical quality control process. It involves evaluation of a professional's work by others with similar expertise, enhancing the work's credibility and accuracy.</p>
<p>However, peer review isn't synonymous with pull requests and can take various forms such as formal reviews, over the shoulder reviews, code comments, and pair programming.</p>
<p>Pair programming, often misunderstood, is an efficient method that reduces errors, improves design, and enhances team dynamics. It can be applied to other roles like design, product, and leadership for brainstorming, refining concepts, strategic planning, and decision-making.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mastering Second Level Relationships: A Key Strategy for Workplace Success]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Mastering Second Level Relationships: A Key Strategy for Workplace Success</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Mastering Second Level Relationships: A Key Strategy for Workplace Success"/>
        <updated>2024-04-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Boost your workplace productivity and job satisfaction by understanding and effectively managing second level relationships. Learn about their impact, methods to assess them, and strategies to enhance these relationships.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Workplaces operate as complex social ecosystems, with dynamics that reach beyond our immediate coworkers and supervisors to include a broader network of relationships. These secondary connections, which are frequently underestimated, are vital to personal success and the overall effectiveness of an organization.</p>
<p>Have you ever thought about how to manage these second level relationships? This post aims to delve into the concept of second level relations at work and their significance.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="understanding-second-level-relationships">Understanding Second Level Relationships<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Mastering%20Second%20Level%20Relationships:%20A%20Key%20Strategy%20for%20Workplace%20Success#understanding-second-level-relationships" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Understanding Second Level Relationships" title="Direct link to Understanding Second Level Relationships">​</a></h2>
<p>Second level relations in a work context refers to connections with individuals or groups outside your immediate team, who nonetheless can dramatically impact your work. This includes stakeholders, teams from other departments, service providers, and clients. Much like distant relatives in a family, you may not interact with them daily, but their influence on the work environment can be significant.</p>
<p>These second level relations have a substantial impact on productivity. For example, a good rapport with a key stakeholder could mean faster approvals and quicker project completion. Similarly, positive relations with other teams can foster cross-departmental collaboration, creating a more cohesive and efficient work environment. Conversely, negative relationships could cause problems. That's why it's essential to proactively manage these relationships.</p>
<p>Now, let's categorize and delve into these relationships.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="stakeholders"><strong>Stakeholders</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Mastering%20Second%20Level%20Relationships:%20A%20Key%20Strategy%20for%20Workplace%20Success#stakeholders" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to stakeholders" title="Direct link to stakeholders">​</a></h3>
<p>A stakeholder can be an individual, group, or organization that has an interest in, or can be affected by, the outcomes of a project or business activity. This can include other employees, customers, suppliers, shareholders who have a stake in the project or organization's success.
Stakeholders can significantly influence the direction and success of our projects, as they are the promoters of the needs that we are trying to solve. Maintaining open communication, understanding their needs and expectations, and addressing their concerns proactively can foster a positive and productive relationship.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="other-teams"><strong>Other Teams</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Mastering%20Second%20Level%20Relationships:%20A%20Key%20Strategy%20for%20Workplace%20Success#other-teams" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to other-teams" title="Direct link to other-teams">​</a></h3>
<p>These are groups within the same organization but working on different projects or tasks. They may have different goals and objectives, but their actions and decisions can significantly influence the progress of our projects.</p>
<p>Healthy relationships with other teams can facilitate better resource sharing, problem-solving, and collaboration. Miscommunication or disputes with other teams can hinder progress, cause delays and create a challenging work environment. Thus, it's essential to maintain clear communication and mutual respect with other teams.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="providers"><strong>Providers</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Mastering%20Second%20Level%20Relationships:%20A%20Key%20Strategy%20for%20Workplace%20Success#providers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to providers" title="Direct link to providers">​</a></h3>
<p>These are the external organizations or individuals who supply goods, services, or expertise that are essential to our projects. This can include everything from software vendors, consulting firms, to freelance experts. Providers can have a significant impact on our project timelines, budgets, and overall success.</p>
<p>If a provider fails to deliver as expected, it can cause delays, increase costs, or even jeopardize the entire project. On the flip side, a reliable provider who understands our needs and reliably meets their commitments can be a key factor in a project's success. Therefore, maintaining good relationships with providers is crucial. This involves clear communication, timely payments, and treating them as partners in our success.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="clientscustomers"><strong>Clients/Customers</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Mastering%20Second%20Level%20Relationships:%20A%20Key%20Strategy%20for%20Workplace%20Success#clientscustomers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to clientscustomers" title="Direct link to clientscustomers">​</a></h3>
<p>These are the end-users of the product or service we are developing. They can greatly influence our projects, as their feedback and satisfaction often determine the project's direction and success.</p>
<p>Understanding their needs, addressing their concerns quickly, and valuing their feedback are essential for a positive relationship. A satisfied client can lead to repeat business, positive word-of-mouth, and improved reputation, while an unsatisfied client can hinder the project's success.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="determining-importance-of-relationships">Determining Importance of relationships<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Mastering%20Second%20Level%20Relationships:%20A%20Key%20Strategy%20for%20Workplace%20Success#determining-importance-of-relationships" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Determining Importance of relationships" title="Direct link to Determining Importance of relationships">​</a></h2>
<p>In assessing the value of relationships, it's key to look at aspects like how often you interact, how interconnected your work is, and their sway in decision-making. By ranking relationships with these factors in mind, you can direct your energies where they'll have the most impact - after all, we can't cultivate every relationship equally.</p>
<p>I typically use Stakeholder Mapping to gauge influence and examine the state of a relationship. You'll find a template in the following image and this <a href="https://excalidraw.com/#json=7qSzy52drnbwd6Sy8C2dz,bEm6jClB_RWoI3a6YV5QRg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">link</a>.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/59d3a19f-5fef-4b4f-8971-39c02c627e98/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB4665ICWK4T7%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115508Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJIMEYCIQDGCPTAXo%2BRi6N6OK7QhuRA%2B2dnyaykON4z5Hiafq9GrgIhALuFdULhczhtZhKlHH8pNNDYJRcBHSrTNyDhX%2BX7bR6nKogECNT%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEQABoMNjM3NDIzMTgzODA1IgyI5LoKTBb%2BoVGeTjIq3ANn4vSK5KICeL8eT%2FvfMv362SKcwFXoFHfQ8t9q%2FiWFdHZsHWgRyu9kR94KHQuuhUeSfGF5aLXE92ggjJzhqkRyR1kl4lgyJkzybXgBPG4AYm2x2W%2B796REThNmfct%2B0SRkqs7sidT6aDouidIW0HwtO0T4Av9sQwNajzfVj4TPaHvBQw6SdSNhdvzK3hRBWBL7CnM4LwS7h2c%2BLkJtoCBAeeksFi62qy6edsbI8pzo0%2BnJUN9Fe1YAj2LVOkRzf03eAQ9EsKOtRTI14jSrUQ2gvsWUrI2O1j64JyYHH2%2BoN8O0MXBwgbTVF1NSa558uDm%2FxQLVAyYAVZsWHoQRWmavgxsYJYqJ6fMKHf3u2s6iQI3KU7VLcDRSOf9SW9RseZyAImgBLinNoXT7e5YDD2hcFRc95mqPLI%2Fx61Y4h2dqxbOGSa5%2BK%2BElJ7BPRFJaNUNm8JYf0VjYcxcCVA6ord01wz6B22ndEmnGIpn1qAU7OxsDrCh6QmVZxaGpur8JtaysYQvyjzhklRDYke22VY6V7cgewocORCDEOe%2FQBLbIsFlYN0Qe3QjBeXLD%2B2fzBJiOoTER1ti2%2B5gGdIFMRUhKYXBhvbHPrJqH1JoK1DaFyI2TChQ0aTnuIZnbwDDinK3EBjqkAdOYnqaJ4QSs8BSJpx1hI%2FiaH9lgvWJDVa1%2FLoA53ijxqepVk5Q5NV%2FzDF6oH%2FDIWLAMT1gBsSH3pdV%2BUXPpI%2FdIP6HZQJ%2Ftj5yfeWneZ5dZAhm3W9sZgdUSbUjkqdA0fd1vW60lOI6SgYgNy8xAuCGx2O4FJTYnnt86%2FMfw6o5E7CON97j0cOnXaTcMsOVqI%2FEN9owDFUYa0MCcuC5g0M56Kc%2FS&amp;X-Amz-Signature=889a887a99f7813ddd70390b492015efa55eb6cd31c916bb6379ffd30de43b42&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="Untitled.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>To map out the relationships that impact your project, follow these steps:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Identify Relationships</strong>: Make a list of all the 2nd level relationships that have an impact on your project.
For example, while the CEO may be a key figure in the company, if they are not directly involved in your project, including them on your map may only complicate things.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/40ed4941-4d92-406e-9526-d3628416a2d8/Untitled.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466S5665CYS%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115510Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJGMEQCIFh6pDhFT1sE1jCMfCEAgCT4uGINgPcOHQy7Ehet5uqXAiBRMa%2BH2%2BSHngXNbn3D1dGOdxUNRWVCD1zfMWrYzQx3lCqIBAjU%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F8BEAAaDDYzNzQyMzE4MzgwNSIM79qK8lXkVaK1tYaSKtwDo%2FQBmaeInOPF1QGOnyfKD3vr8ht%2B9F%2Fw%2BIrNlHDh4RjKJKtZtABxWZrXulVnKdGQiHx7CB%2BVInBz7rqDiBMo2pNOcM3n4Z7Sfd%2FXAzQsgaJiwkyVjrqh%2BAiBXUItB0FeUuO2Vr1TMB1iwdVvdb9yen%2BddcJ2BkJFTmClAs1ILmE9r2xWRuL84K48mTrys3%2B%2FViwk0DhHQEAeci0EZm17js%2FhZURqmmLg1YFUiVysvrB8gGlhjqksIOz6XRa3RC4GZSRoiF8ptjdvUR%2BrkX3rPWaE3cZXBWROdT1Auf%2F779wbgmvPXZTbywZjuypZ9EWoaTzLbtuwM6SMvcF0l7uqWKUHfsfQ9sImpw3YbUJlChpErl3KAOov2n3Gru5m5L3nERdi2hRbbFcmUdmk%2F7rGhQ1%2BwyduWa3Wy1HEnm7eorZpA8ad8g9qd4KfC9odjudkgf%2FldFI2gWHSg1oMyxAtkOHd3llXa2UvF%2FZCb5Uv8Tea7x23Zq3Nok%2BKvgTg%2BUk4hPUtLllACu2oLO36vf6hkTtkpDQC0Up2fld%2B3gOVEqGD4DPUDBsjHJYEFd%2BnLnpIR%2Bli%2BxBanWe8fHzrKhUgPwPT7T7LICrm2801rr1QkSLop%2BbzjebYolQif%2BIwyZ2txAY6pgFpbin%2BmPbaJMAn0%2BPcs7qB2darNG4gnTaxxXwPie79ruHW2vT%2FTuaHKKhmnMo89kLpeArFmV%2BRQ%2BREaoG5FODMEr9F8WryGxKM2zrSUZgHCEps2gnmA42t1ex%2BClI%2BRv%2BlwcdWCiouONp50YUBZom3JdN9zVaFc8mHKec31sguPqa1s9ul00v0nr4Oqw7AEqnXMSZ85UVyxMrtg7PfPJ%2BpiTWOh5US&amp;X-Amz-Signature=942343019cd7fd9e09466a7dfcda0abc89462e89db3a3baa0832fb94bc2e1384&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="Untitled.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Assess Influence</strong>: Position these relationships on the influence axis according to how much they affect your project, relative to each other.
For example, while the CEO might hold a lot of sway in the company, if they don't affect your project, their influence on you is limited.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/4e3674d8-dc03-4ecf-ba84-bb9f01e74c36/Captura_de_pantalla_2024-04-16_a_las_10.52.20.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB4667W7HJ32H%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115510Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJGMEQCIBvrsn868kA0TuJUNHOrBYH%2BXrx4mtiAyuxUkA78dvieAiB8g%2Fwx3dCfG8fXROtaWdvtPRhvQgt0%2FIaJswMcBiUN2iqIBAjU%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F8BEAAaDDYzNzQyMzE4MzgwNSIMRMOV01ZW8cnUMgc6KtwDf1QnODZuPfwlr%2FLSwN%2BNotvPOs85HsrLZLG%2FIVT5ElzhAasIriCHabJer3nwWwikIU2fzuzjWq6lsrU1zRx6Qg%2FqRBRGH%2Fxml%2FzZDL4imfBLBpfLukjOk60%2FYlXMvbBlehJhJPPpJZhfVfTlSSMIq6l4zv0ah%2BPC3bsqcRwxs8ZsIHVXgped5UB4r%2FLTb1jhalE2c%2B3SMOXPuhVWruKqwqpVQA4VfNYZ2gxDZRkayHspZD7r3sc0ag5mQsFnZn4qZdhBNpVMKZMkjFk7dhrSNLUTStBcZzO5Ird5N2VoiYdQhS8rHQiFpqYh7Ts4oFjoeKL1DuKicx0biioTPvz5WmPWZ24nsXhgtBKjpyv70akOxUSOJDXnAqmyng9IFGLsiYW5ElD5mEhCJQR3UEGAM%2BVVKxXtILXVaKSaW8JjTM%2BVE0dRdA7YDzOh9jE0fEUH5b6Nk9hEJOIBtEnAMuUp%2Ba6yukCrJxGGZ612j%2FBWWplCYYQx7of%2BbR58kCSVlkRu00URsl30EieoRU9cOoCl3BSKEiPqy6UOtaGV8gQnsKBD5uKlaoLdXu%2Bojv2iQa7026uwdd3ayv0YQtQc73EjM%2BbxOb6HGVjGmzGCAvooF7cjiECX8ZEqwfmq97Yw5J2txAY6pgHX699YmSkT6vxCNXuPo4ocVctobqpRFA%2FtEWHnNKIz33f7W5oAUZPItokKgkZpxasVV9tRLOpkjss%2BOz%2Bbg6e0ncbLwpH1qspHANyUsz%2FSuAYxbZoScsUy2UztNRzSFS%2BKelF8ZK2POY1oAezwlGZ8XsdnPURFjJSP1b7O0NWLRG%2Bexi7CzHWxui2flEatjWLntDRvLZAkL%2FwKpSKlWCC2srT9iZGy&amp;X-Amz-Signature=79eb3b05c85dcc33188871c0b61f0ff7a0951006cfeb71bc0724a3ed35c21140&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="Captura_de_pantalla_2024-04-16_a_las_10.52.20.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Define Relationship Status</strong>: Determine whether they are supporting your efforts (Supporters) or hindering your progress (Detractors), relative to each other.
For instance, if your main stakeholder is continuously expressing dissatisfaction and losing faith in the project and team, they would be considered a Detractor.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/038f6062-bea9-4362-b307-dcb9f77a4aaa/Captura_de_pantalla_2024-04-16_a_las_10.53.14.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB4665TL7BT3J%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115512Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJHMEUCIFZIz24iy%2Bi93ruKwmFzMANZ2ldRAPljZSeGi0s%2BVbj6AiEAqEPTcFZf0XrBoYYZF2K5jJ3fm5ykqelLBMkmsqMHCxMqiAQI1P%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FARAAGgw2Mzc0MjMxODM4MDUiDJ%2BROERF4MIBAF4ZvircAxHS0o1setQlY6o55WPJLBu6WUSvbKvXrNXGJRjvanV2dB5NqQpbFrRaQcnpLMJPzP5KKQvkd2cqIQI9zYZJw0uH8%2FF7Z8Q2kPWE6O%2FFl%2Ff5sYcyMQEqWwBRQpU7jYkjJp9Pxi3CHYIciukx1n4R3NnghHao6lVP8IibuArny%2FBdQUp0LRBAqm4Kp5PueLDs07ku1bvwBVzckcbmVn1%2Ba%2BWPpOtu4Bj1jmA6j0rt1mdfNJNeb9qArxBHW5nqWJJULTjWRTWZShJcQIqfHZ%2ByqXR2wmtLGu1VIVJTtvM4afDtfT5q70O13EeTzHlUHFQ5jjV58krh8kkvP7xDZrOX0kvVKQp8SRJ772dxISdEJjpTXOqgHco3eOnisQSXWuG7JlTBD2uIU0nJaC2cNSD7rk7gO3xF1Nwhw3TSUOf%2FPgVVGUQz4oB1RS6rqPwKDVVBzDkcA7SVqxFY7IcdpsIStSBnsrFj4fKfbrGYOstZGBuzYPuV5bo1pucHtNXPf%2Fni2Sy%2BeQ8BaNmPuEz6%2F9dJ24ZttVsgEgrk3oyOb8AKRZ5LZ0Lwsv%2F5M28SGSPOpfk2M8G1e%2BqstXVlxWvDhUYyyhN%2FvW1AS8Lh2lNtdrffwGsi8wqRaS1H4Y8a%2BpUnMKidrcQGOqUB5ncX%2FDGNiRFQRn8%2BkvzCifHqffMttdtjWdTFFfdr8X6ABpn0W74E0dT%2F1bVFo85Y%2FNyqgoxFUpM85atGlHnE%2Bpy9ze1hxFkhHrylSBVODhh2ih%2BOtNZcmuBIO4j9SymQvjXmgwITvJZkbMiPsU%2BlK4IGIb8rhESv6WOcZiODygZD%2FmWd05KNe1tzwXBFGGN1KRwy8nKFYaai0kCVHejM%2FHybqfLH&amp;X-Amz-Signature=e052f4a2af832295052c040742343c24309368807c7782e51e76e9e47b93ae92&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="Captura_de_pantalla_2024-04-16_a_las_10.53.14.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Decide on Areas for Improvement</strong>: Choose a few relationships that need attention. These are usually high-influence Detractors that you would want to convert into Supporters.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/bfbddee9-3882-4e42-912b-d4fbb8ecf838/Captura_de_pantalla_2024-04-16_a_las_10.56.59.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB466RLJ4LWEI%2F20250731%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250731T115512Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEKv%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2FwEaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJGMEQCIBhDoypdaO0OXcozbHEa%2BE4P8fc9MfDL2fRucdglmVsfAiA%2BEuVjCBlzO0aucf22wAybMs5o4sTFmis%2FjN9%2BmC56qSqIBAjU%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F%2F8BEAAaDDYzNzQyMzE4MzgwNSIM3Boju7etQUECeKAcKtwDNvgFGD2sTkJEzLh%2BljUQtHj0HwgALlGl75Bn0D2eFtGdyzrTWIjGIl4CqJ7eJOLQN3VkPMmkOrdX7s1xZyzMedKlO09BsQPPHHW9NfZWxX%2BeBA5fpFPBx4ipafjOwg1TQDFWnWSaB6BtgyV%2FcoEA%2FgcK6rh5L5w4wDm75rAQnTLhXyyLU%2Fy%2BXMMZoxya3yCblk9AZftHwsv%2BU8V9UK6mpZAi8%2Bx6T2Ydki2CXOAk8FULIAGXg018n%2Bd1unga3ChLCj2NNB9Eg7hfOsQv9B4lgaaqdWz0ekVFqgAmdVp0tNXtqdlTIeI46UwHfxnU0W7SWTLpzL1wv3IcNMFs3ueVf7laK1GOKDhUD2TPcDWDf90ahnB1Q0JVV15A7nmBFpSrMoMLv24bNS%2F3%2F9bhUeq5FoauOXHLCO4%2F3WfC1Hx9bifqPjHfVPlMR2ely3tRpNxWLpEx2b%2BqSuNvLu1o8qEzO0fM6tDuItBPrZ8cKDy9gAyW3EiSbALsGMq2VDl%2F7WWHH3985a3IQ8HItL%2BUcsvMrxrrzbdc3I7eLP1vJwvd2HHFu0nxRVuD8a22s3CvWHe%2Bbt4UNn8xbTbvkX4gJYLFw7hwrTcw%2BwqZnN241AbIPNCVshUqp9Foq10ivk8w6Z2txAY6pgGgf9pJ7B%2FZxdmRhqtHcjO8X36Nprio7g%2B5b4%2BURsTWZb30Xp4eS05nEcK0fXC0cKxfBilVZrTIgOnBWrWIRiQxKkr8TnY3cb7tI9m6MbnFDVEKtYR%2BryPW2BwDXDs%2FAxnoLeijMRpOGJ0U1q3p4xEnwQiPs%2BJf1I1YNWFKULlcTgE%2BMBDUDRyVXQVh7LE0B68yblysX6ZXrYEKVn4jWRaaq%2FCy8bhy&amp;X-Amz-Signature=619567e09509cff9c3668c47a9a438f952adf617df0ed1f8cae385017579db85&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-amz-checksum-mode=ENABLED&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="Captura_de_pantalla_2024-04-16_a_las_10.56.59.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Revisit and Reevaluate Regularly</strong>: Relationships can change over time. It's important to frequently reassess the status and influence of your second-level relationships and modify your strategies as needed.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="improving-relationships">Improving Relationships<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Mastering%20Second%20Level%20Relationships:%20A%20Key%20Strategy%20for%20Workplace%20Success#improving-relationships" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Improving Relationships" title="Direct link to Improving Relationships">​</a></h2>
<p>When relationships that require enhancement have been pinpointed, a variety of specific strategies can be implemented to foster growth and improvement in these areas:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Empathize</strong>: It is crucial to not only understand but also empathize with the concerns, anxieties, and reservations that the other party may have. This involves putting yourself in their shoes and viewing situations from their perspective, which can go a long way in building mutual understanding and respect.</li>
<li><strong>Be proactive</strong>: Rather than waiting for the other party to take action or initiate improvements, it's beneficial to take the first step. This proactive approach shows your commitment to the relationship and can inspire the other party to reciprocate your efforts.</li>
<li><strong>Improve Communication</strong>: Quite often, the root cause of relationship issues is miscommunication or a complete lack of communication. It's essential to understand the communication needs of the other party and act upon them. This could involve being more open, transparent, or timely with your communication, or perhaps adjusting your communication style to better match theirs.</li>
<li><strong>Build the connections</strong>: Beyond the professional capacity, take the time to get to know the person behind the role. Keep in mind that not all factors that motivate a person are work-related. By sharing personal experiences and being open to finding common ground and understanding, you may discover shared interests or values that can strengthen your working relationship. Better interpersonal relationships can contribute to a more cohesive and productive working environment.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Mastering%20Second%20Level%20Relationships:%20A%20Key%20Strategy%20for%20Workplace%20Success#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>In conclusion, second level relations at work, though not immediately visible, have a substantial impact on an individual's work experience and the overall productivity of an organization. Effective management of these relationships can lead to improved collaboration, smoother workflow, and enhanced job satisfaction. As the work environments continue to evolve, recognizing and nurturing these secondary relationships will become an increasingly important aspect of workplace strategy.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[AI In The Workplace: Are LLMs Hype or Reality?]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/04/T00:00:00.000Z-AI In The Workplace: Are LLMs Hype or Reality</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/04/T00:00:00.000Z-AI In The Workplace: Are LLMs Hype or Reality"/>
        <updated>2024-04-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the potential and pitfalls of Large Language Models (LLMs) in the workplace. This comprehensive guide discusses the hype surrounding AI and LLMs, their psychological appeal, and practical applications in user-facing products, company tools, and work augmentation. Learn about the quality and licensing issues in coding with LLMs, and understand their impact on productivity and code quality. The article also highlights the importance of ethical decision-making in technology advancement.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This past year, the buzz word in technology has undeniably been "AI". But what exactly do we mean when we say AI?</p>
<p>Often, our comprehension of terms and definitions can be clouded due to the ambiguity in the language used. A prime example is the term "Artificial Intelligence" (AI). This term used to encompass a broad spectrum of technologies, but recently, it has become largely associated with Large Language Models (LLMs).</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-are-we-talking-about">What are we talking about?<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/04/T00:00:00.000Z-AI%20In%20The%20Workplace:%20Are%20LLMs%20Hype%20or%20Reality#what-are-we-talking-about" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What are we talking about?" title="Direct link to What are we talking about?">​</a></h2>
<p>AI, in its purest form, is the ability of a machine or computer program to think and learn. It is the theory and development of computer systems able to perform tasks that typically require human intelligence.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, LLMs are defined in this <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large_language_model" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikipedia article</a> as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A language model notable for its ability to achieve general-purpose language generation and other natural language processing tasks such as classification. LLMs acquire these abilities by learning statistical relationships from text documents during a computationally intensive self-supervised and semi-supervised training process.[1] LLMs can be used for text generation, a form of generative AI, by taking an input text and repeatedly predicting the next token or word</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It goes without saying that we have yet to reach the real definition of AI, with neither LLMs nor other technologies.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-psychology-of-llms-hype">The Psychology of LLMs Hype<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/04/T00:00:00.000Z-AI%20In%20The%20Workplace:%20Are%20LLMs%20Hype%20or%20Reality#the-psychology-of-llms-hype" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Psychology of LLMs Hype" title="Direct link to The Psychology of LLMs Hype">​</a></h2>
<p>What has made these large language models so intriguing over the past year, prompting such widespread interest?</p>
<p>Their ability to “bullshiting with confidence”. Just try this out yourself, ask any question to an LLM and just tell them they are mistaken and request another option. You'll typically receive an apology followed by an assertive, alternative response.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://prod-files-secure.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/df75203e-cd58-41eb-8339-d5bf4288eb0e/702b745b-8e9a-437c-a8ee-92063ef1b0c2/llm1.png?X-Amz-Algorithm=AWS4-HMAC-SHA256&amp;X-Amz-Content-Sha256=UNSIGNED-PAYLOAD&amp;X-Amz-Credential=ASIAZI2LB4662ZSZUZAG%2F20250227%2Fus-west-2%2Fs3%2Faws4_request&amp;X-Amz-Date=20250227T120441Z&amp;X-Amz-Expires=3600&amp;X-Amz-Security-Token=IQoJb3JpZ2luX2VjEDsaCXVzLXdlc3QtMiJGMEQCIGU6LXH8i2FLPa9OFjiGjh93AKScJq9NkZds%2B9G2RvD5AiBq1iLukn2fcNuIDfJBHBgLfgWv4iTp9X2A5VpBlglZ1ir%2FAwh0EAAaDDYzNzQyMzE4MzgwNSIMF78PHZWG3zuMoNKpKtwDQItA96I6PJbmNv8SglAUABpdP8%2FZgSM%2F3rjRj%2FqEdTQXodJyV57sxuFX4Zd7eQTipVtF8xStGHHcUO7yygDO4sW3ejlfVnFUdVyuVMOTkKoknBimwTnyqicvlkOZW5JwEpfpN%2F0vBOrQyK%2BcoiapetQEhj%2B5KzH2JiuCkd3bSvIFOGfpninJXFCIO5qLnEGU54u4RB%2FNKNSXhHaF4cywdI8zrUKiw1ePUC0DU2uJoOWD3mHlwN175rZd7lZjtIYwVd8gIn8ctjy7%2BdtgJ2dojH3CGZIZdmBIB55BY4N5tTHOytSH00cFakN3o70UhrCCncQPwKufhdsfm2F7xmxjs9IPdjyTw9wRvGTaVqcvjf44HEXSCtEwenrWgQEgFLYgssGK2d92WKNccfP1mC96xO8fRlaqKHOy5XOIw2LBuU%2FWx4JlZHiKexaX8LxwaF4%2FDKOtaPWSavRGk79vylaftHGn60uxqQoGYbtgnzu2u9W9IEH151Zva%2FDgrDFDy39XlRgVVS2QNLzmD%2BoqmPhyd1xqGLELCBRtEid0PNStUQwGRYW4rgFjffUUqTknyZ2u7MFocFIutKiSti8lwlcqxKTWW1lq4ss98F9rXzhuLnydhh1STmu6Vy%2FKCrUw75CBvgY6pgFyIo5wwML0tu%2BZ0SH9%2FqfeTwivSkFMzPhU8aXACgiEsXGeVK%2FgTUoOna%2F5t%2Fj8VHSo%2BLjZ%2Fi0QK86iPPK%2F0%2FX0LSptPinmBSFOT2Xy1JKvjo6Ae3azdHl7GrJxLaf7gg7xdI3eUtidBEBWFTWHV1UhF6vzqKhqPA3fXEv%2Bqhv45d799Ekh%2FeAIeo38mQQ9dKXpBqVJ1i9FrzYw24PtmTJYEDQSvmzV&amp;X-Amz-Signature=a65a4a322f8ebcc81a58b8d8719feb7ff0a1d43c4794f8ff63a8a43e3c1bfcde&amp;X-Amz-SignedHeaders=host&amp;x-id=GetObject" alt="llm1.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>To clarify, these software models aren't intentionally deceptive. They simply aim to provide responses that align with your queries. Meanwhile, we as recipients are prone to accept information as accurate, especially when it's delivered with apparent confidence. This applies to both machine-generated responses and human communication. Even this paragraph, written by a non-psychologist, likely seems plausible because it's framed convincingly.</p>
<p>So how does an LLM “bullshiting with confidence”. LLMs are trained to recognize patterns in data and make predictions based on these patterns. Essentially, they are statistical functions that predict, given the words in a question, the words that will form a compelling response. This phenomenon of non-accurate but compelling responses goes by the name of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hallucination_(artificial_intelligence)" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">hallucinations</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="llms-at-the-workplace">LLMs at the Workplace<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/04/T00:00:00.000Z-AI%20In%20The%20Workplace:%20Are%20LLMs%20Hype%20or%20Reality#llms-at-the-workplace" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to LLMs at the Workplace" title="Direct link to LLMs at the Workplace">​</a></h2>
<p>Are LLMs useless? Not at all. Despite the caution required due to the nature of statistically generated responses, these systems can indeed provide substantial value.</p>
<p>Let's explore potential applications:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="user-facing-products">User-Facing Products<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/04/T00:00:00.000Z-AI%20In%20The%20Workplace:%20Are%20LLMs%20Hype%20or%20Reality#user-facing-products" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to User-Facing Products" title="Direct link to User-Facing Products">​</a></h3>
<p>Interestingly, this technology might just be the first to convince humans they're interacting with another human or an intelligent entity. This opens up new product opportunities where the perceived "human interface" might have more value than the precise accuracy of the content.</p>
<p>Potential applications could include:</p>
<ul>
<li>First-tier customer support: By integrating LLMs with user manuals, we could develop a chatbot interface for customers.</li>
<li>Sales representatives: LLMs could be utilized to create more human-like, machine-driven robot calls or chatbots.</li>
</ul>
<p>Does this mean human roles will be totally replaced? No, because LLMs lack a true understanding of the problem or the conversation. Therefore, a second level of human intervention remains essential. However, this technology could help businesses scale their operations in a novel way.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>⚠️ Personally, I would not use the current technology for products that require accuracy. (example: tax calculations, finances, etc.).</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="company-tools">Company Tools<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/04/T00:00:00.000Z-AI%20In%20The%20Workplace:%20Are%20LLMs%20Hype%20or%20Reality#company-tools" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Company Tools" title="Direct link to Company Tools">​</a></h3>
<p>Typically, businesses possess an extensive amount of data that encapsulates their knowledge base. Filtering this data can be challenging, especially when it's scattered across various systems, making it tough to query. Leveraging LLMs can significantly streamline this process and reduce the mental strain of pinpointing the required information.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>⚠️ Keep in mind, LLMs do normally not provide precise responses. Thus, it's crucial to critically assess the answers and cross-reference with the original data for accuracy.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="work-augmentation">Work Augmentation<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/04/T00:00:00.000Z-AI%20In%20The%20Workplace:%20Are%20LLMs%20Hype%20or%20Reality#work-augmentation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Work Augmentation" title="Direct link to Work Augmentation">​</a></h3>
<p>This tool has a wide range of applications that can be incorporated into daily workflows. Let's explore some common utilization.</p>
<p><strong>Writing Assistance</strong></p>
<p>LLMs can provide valuable support in crafting documents, emails, and other written communications. They offer grammatically correct and contextually fitting sentence suggestions, enhancing the overall writing process.</p>
<p>As a general rule, this is a highly productive use of the technology. Just ensure to review the generated suggestions for maximum benefit.</p>
<p><strong>Reference Tool</strong></p>
<p>LLMs can serve as a dynamic reference resource, drawing on the vast expanse of knowledge they've been trained on. They function like a sophisticated search engine, delivering consolidated information.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>⚠️ However, as LLMs may not always provide accurate responses, it's crucial to approach the information critically and cross-check with original data sources when necessary.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Coding</strong></p>
<p>Within the realm of coding, LLMs can help in code generation and even in writing documentation. This is possibly the field that can affect most of the readers of this newsletter, so let's do a deep dive on this point.</p>
<p>From my professional experience, we've opted not to utilize this technology so far. The main factors influencing this decision include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Quality Inheritance: The quality of code that LLMs generate is directly linked to the quality of the training data. If the model is trained on data that includes poor or flawed code, the generated code will inherit those flaws.</li>
<li>Cognitive Load: While LLMs can simplify routine coding processes, they can also increase the cognitive burden on developers who need to review and comprehend the generated code, ensuring it meets expectations. Developers may face a choice of accepting the code as-is with potential issues or spend additional time deciphering the proposed code.</li>
<li>Licensing: Employing LLMs may lead to potential breaches of software licenses. If the model is trained on code under copyleft licenses (e.g., GPL), the generated code could be seen as derivative, thus resulting in licensing complications.</li>
</ul>
<p>Additionally, upon reviewing the data accumulated over the duration this technology has been in existence, we can observe the following results:</p>
<ul>
<li>Supporting Data:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Microsoft Experiment: The results were that developers using copilot were able to complete the task 55.8% faster.</li>
<li>Pinterest  Experiment (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=70Rc4wJRluA&amp;t=1032s" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a>):  They found that their engineers who commit code less often increased their commit rate by 50-100%, and engineers who commit code the most often became about ~40% more productive.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Detracting Data:<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Git Clear Research (<a href="https://www.gitclear.com/coding_on_copilot_data_shows_ais_downward_pressure_on_code_quality" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a>): analyzed approximately 153 million changed lines of code, they found code churn (the percentage of lines that are reverted or updated less than two weeks after being authored) is projected to double in 2024 compared to its 2021, pre-AI baseline.</li>
<li>Security Researchers (<a href="https://www.theregister.com/2021/08/25/github_copilot_study/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Link</a>): Explored Copilot's performance on three distinct code generation axes (examining how it performs given diversity of weaknesses, diversity of prompts, and diversity of domains). In total, we produce 89 different scenarios for Copilot to complete, producing 1,689 programs. Of these, we found approximately 40% to be vulnerable.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>⚠️ While the technology shows promise, it's not fully developed yet.<br>
<!-- -->Our studies indicate that while short-term productivity may increase, this comes at the expense of code quality. This aligns with the concerns we initially discussed.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Our studies indicate that while short-term productivity may increase, this comes at the expense of code quality. This aligns with the concerns we initially discussed.</p>
<p>As we conclude this article, it's important to highlight the potential vulnerabilities associated with Large Language Models (LLMs) in the workplace. I strongly recommend familiarizing yourself with potential threats and reading more about this topic via the <a href="https://owasp.org/www-project-top-10-for-large-language-model-applications/assets/PDF/OWASP-Top-10-for-LLMs-2023-slides-v1_0.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OWASP TOP 10 for LLMs</a> resource.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/04/T00:00:00.000Z-AI%20In%20The%20Workplace:%20Are%20LLMs%20Hype%20or%20Reality#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>The term "Artificial Intelligence" (AI) has recently become synonymous with Large Language Models (LLMs). However, true AI, the ability of a machine to think and learn, has not been achieved with LLMs or other technologies.</p>
<p>LLMs have gained popularity due to their ability to generate convincing responses, but these responses are merely statistical predictions based on input data. Despite this, LLMs can be valuable in the workplace, serving as user-facing products, company tools, and work augmentation. However, caution is advised due to their lack of accuracy.</p>
<p>Lastly, it's imperative that we bear in mind our social responsibility as creators and innovators in the realm of technology. With the current global population standing at 8.1 billion, each decision we make, each technological advancement we introduce, has the potential to impact a vast number of lives. We should, therefore, strive to prioritize the wellbeing of each individual in this global community, ensuring that our contributions to technology are both ethical and beneficial to all.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Strategic Vs. Tactical Mindset]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/03/T22:00:00.000Z-The Strategic Vs. Tactical Mindset</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/03/T22:00:00.000Z-The Strategic Vs. Tactical Mindset"/>
        <updated>2024-04-03T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the balance between strategic and tactical mindsets in the field of engineering. This article discusses the importance of both perspectives in problem-solving, goal setting, and planning for the future. It also highlights how the focus shifts from tactical to strategic as engineers advance in their careers. Ideal for engineering leaders and team members seeking to improve their productivity and strategic thinking.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How much time do you or your team spend on the day to day vs. planing the future? .</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff644c4da-a1f5-47af-8dda-0341bd3af204_1080x1080.png" alt="https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff644c4da-a1f5-47af-8dda-0341bd3af204_1080x1080.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>I would tend to think that for most this is not a binary situation, as we need to be able to have a plan and deliver on it. For this, we require practicing and intentionally using different types of mindsets. Let’s delve into this deeper in this article.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="balancing-today--tomorrow">Balancing Today &amp; Tomorrow<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/03/T22:00:00.000Z-The%20Strategic%20Vs.%20Tactical%20Mindset#balancing-today--tomorrow" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Balancing Today &amp; Tomorrow" title="Direct link to Balancing Today &amp; Tomorrow">​</a></h2>
<p>Working in engineering demands a careful balance between two distinct mindsets: the strategic and the tactical. Understanding these two mindsets and knowing when to apply each is crucial for successful leadership and team performance. Let's delve into what each of these mindsets entails.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="strategic-mindset">Strategic Mindset<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/03/T22:00:00.000Z-The%20Strategic%20Vs.%20Tactical%20Mindset#strategic-mindset" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Strategic Mindset" title="Direct link to Strategic Mindset">​</a></h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Where do we need to go?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A strategic mindset is forward-looking. It's about setting goals, identifying opportunities, and developing plans to achieve those goals. It involves thinking about the bigger picture and the future direction of the team or the organization, providing a common path for everyone.</p>
<p>An example of a strategic mindset could be considering organizing the company in vertical slices, to define common tools and practices, etc.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="tactical-mindset">Tactical Mindset<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/03/T22:00:00.000Z-The%20Strategic%20Vs.%20Tactical%20Mindset#tactical-mindset" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Tactical Mindset" title="Direct link to Tactical Mindset">​</a></h3>
<blockquote>
<p>What do we need to do?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>On the other hand, a tactical mindset is about the here and now. This involves focusing on the tasks at hand, solving problems as they arise, and executing the immediate steps of any strategy. This mindset is required to survive.</p>
<p>An example of a tactical mindset could be keeping legacy money-making systems running healthy, fixing a bug that affects clients, etc.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="problems-of-being-stuck-in-one-mindset">Problems of Being Stuck in One Mindset<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/03/T22:00:00.000Z-The%20Strategic%20Vs.%20Tactical%20Mindset#problems-of-being-stuck-in-one-mindset" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Problems of Being Stuck in One Mindset" title="Direct link to Problems of Being Stuck in One Mindset">​</a></h2>
<p>Balancing the strategic and tactical mindsets is not an easy task. It requires conscious effort, adaptability, and situational awareness. To lead effectively, engineering leaders must be able to switch seamlessly between these two mindsets, adapting to the fluctuating needs of their team and the project at hand.</p>
<p>If any of the mindsets is dominant, it can lead to issues on a company and team level. Let's discuss the problems of being stuck in each of these mindsets:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="tactical">Tactical<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/03/T22:00:00.000Z-The%20Strategic%20Vs.%20Tactical%20Mindset#tactical" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Tactical" title="Direct link to Tactical">​</a></h3>
<p>Being overly tactical can lead to:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Lack of bigger picture</strong>: Without a strategic approach, leaders might become so focused on immediate issues that they lose sight of broader goals and objectives</li>
<li><strong>Lost opportunities</strong>: A purely tactical approach might miss out on potential opportunities for improvement or innovation, as the focus is solely on dealing with the immediate issues at hand.</li>
<li><strong>Increased Baseline</strong>: Quick fixes might be preferred over sustainable solutions, leading to extra effort of maintenance and the need for extra hands to maintain systems up and running.</li>
<li><strong>Crisis management loop</strong>: A purely tactical mindset can lead to a reactive approach where leaders are constantly dealing with immediate issues rather than planning for the future, keeping the team in a perpetual state of crisis management.</li>
<li><strong>Burnout</strong>: The continuous pressure to handle immediate issues and the lack of preventive measures can lead to increased stress and eventual burnout.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="strategic">Strategic<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/03/T22:00:00.000Z-The%20Strategic%20Vs.%20Tactical%20Mindset#strategic" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Strategic" title="Direct link to Strategic">​</a></h3>
<p>Being overly strategic can lead to:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Analysis Paralysis</strong>: Spending too much time planning and strategizing can lead to indecisiveness, delaying important decisions and actions.</li>
<li><strong>Missed details</strong>: Overemphasis on the big picture might lead to overlooking important details, which can result in faulty execution of strategies.</li>
<li><strong>Disconnect from the team</strong>: Leaders who are overly strategic might lose touch with the day-to-day challenges their team faces, leading to unrealistic plans and expectations.</li>
<li><strong>Frustration among team members</strong>: If leaders are always focused on future plans, team members might feel their immediate concerns are being ignored, leading to dissatisfaction and frustration.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-role-progression-from-tactical-to-strategic">The Role Progression: From Tactical to Strategic<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/03/T22:00:00.000Z-The%20Strategic%20Vs.%20Tactical%20Mindset#the-role-progression-from-tactical-to-strategic" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Role Progression: From Tactical to Strategic" title="Direct link to The Role Progression: From Tactical to Strategic">​</a></h2>
<p>As engineers progress in their careers and take on more senior roles, there’s often a necessary shift from a primarily tactical mindset to a more strategic one.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Early Career (99% Tactical, 1% Strategic):</strong> Focuses primarily on tactical tasks such as coding, debugging, and learning new technologies. Their work is closely guided by the guidelines set by the bigger picture.</li>
<li><strong>Mid-Career Engineer (90% Tactical, 10% Strategic):</strong> Start to introduce tactical work with strategic thinking to prepare themselves for future work. They are knowledgeable about larger parts of the codebase and product, allowing them to provide input for strategical decisions.</li>
<li><strong>Late Career Engineer (60% Tactical, 40% Strategic):</strong> Continues to execute hands on work, but spends an increasing amount of time on strategic tasks. They make architectural decisions, mentor other engineers, align with other teams engineers.</li>
<li><strong>Leaders (30% Tactical, 70% Strategic):</strong> Spends a significant amount of their time on strategic tasks. They are responsible for planning and coordinating the team's work and ensuring that it aligns with the company's strategic goals.</li>
<li><strong>Directors (5% Tactical, 95% Strategic):</strong> Primarily focused on strategic tasks. They make decisions about the overall direction of the engineering team, manage resources, and coordinate with other parts of the business.</li>
<li><strong>C-Level (1% Tactical, 99% Strategic):</strong> Almost entirely focused on strategic tasks. They set the technological direction of the company, make decisions about the use of resources, and represent the engineering team at the executive level.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="summary">Summary<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/04/03/T22:00:00.000Z-The%20Strategic%20Vs.%20Tactical%20Mindset#summary" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Summary" title="Direct link to Summary">​</a></h3>
<p>A strategic mindset focuses on setting goals and planning for the future, while a tactical mindset concentrates on immediate tasks and problem-solving. However, overemphasis on either mindset can lead to issues such as lack of broader vision or missed details. As engineers progress in their careers, there is often a shift from a primarily tactical mindset to a more strategic one, with leaders and executives focusing more on strategic tasks.</p>
<p>I hope this post has helped solve the long-standing question of what is this person doing in their role. And helps also to understand how successful engineering requires a balance between strategic and tactical mindsets.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Product teams: Aligning to Value]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/28/T03:00:00.000Z-Product teams: Aligning to Value</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/28/T03:00:00.000Z-Product teams: Aligning to Value"/>
        <updated>2024-03-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Dive into the transformative world of product teams and vertical slicing in our latest Engineering Strategy 101 series. Gain insights on building cross-functional teams, fostering innovation, and aligning with customer values for more efficient and agile product development. Unlock the blueprint to revolutionize your software development approach and drive success. ]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When you contemplate the structure and effectiveness of your software departments, the concept of product teams and the strategy of vertical slicing emerge as pivotal part of the journey.</p>
<p>These methodologies can revolutionize the way products are developed and maintained, directly impacting their success and the adaptiveness of the organization. This post aims to explore the essence of product teams, their significance, and the practical steps to implement vertical slicing within those teams.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="understanding-product-teams"><strong>Understanding Product Teams</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/28/T03:00:00.000Z-Product%20teams:%20Aligning%20to%20Value#understanding-product-teams" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to understanding-product-teams" title="Direct link to understanding-product-teams">​</a></h2>
<p>A product team is a cross-functional team that includes all the roles necessary to develop, test, and deliver value to the customer. It's centered around a single user need, this will either mean a single product or a closely related set of products.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="value-of-product-teams"><strong>Value of Product Teams</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/28/T03:00:00.000Z-Product%20teams:%20Aligning%20to%20Value#value-of-product-teams" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to value-of-product-teams" title="Direct link to value-of-product-teams">​</a></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Enhanced Focus and Agility</strong>: Product teams focus on a single product or a set of products, enabling them to rapidly respond to changing customer needs and market conditions. This focus accelerates decision-making processes and product iterations.</li>
<li><strong>Improved Accountability</strong>: With clear ownership, product teams have a better understanding of their objectives, leading to increased accountability and a stronger sense of purpose among team members.</li>
<li><strong>Boosted Innovation</strong>: Cross-functional interaction within the team promotes diverse viewpoints, fostering an environment ripe for innovation and creative problem-solving.</li>
<li><strong>Customer-Centric Development</strong>: Product teams operate with a strong understanding of and alignment with customer needs, ensuring that the products developed truly resonate with and bring value to the end users.</li>
<li><strong>Efficiency</strong>: Such teams minimize the traditional overhead associated with coordination across different departments, leading to more efficient use of time.</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="roles-in-product-teams">Roles In product teams<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/28/T03:00:00.000Z-Product%20teams:%20Aligning%20to%20Value#roles-in-product-teams" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Roles In product teams" title="Direct link to Roles In product teams">​</a></h3>
<p>Lets delineate the core skills essential to a product team's success and explain the unique value each contributes to the team's objectives:</p>
<ul>
<li>Product Manager: acts as the visionary and strategist of the team. They are responsible for identifying customer needs, setting the product vision, and prioritizing the development roadmap. By ensuring that the team understands the 'why' behind their work, product managers play a critical role in aligning product development with market demands and organizational goals.</li>
<li>Developers: bring the product vision to life through code. They are the architects and builders of the product, responsible for implementing features, fixing bugs, and ensuring the product's technical viability. Their expertise spans across front-end, back-end, and full-stack development, allowing for versatile problem-solving and innovation.</li>
<li>Designers:  focus on the user interface (UI) and user experience (UX) of the product. They ensure that the product is not only functional but also intuitive, engaging, and accessible to users. By advocating for the end-user's perspective, designers play a key role in making products that are genuinely user-centric.</li>
<li>Quality Assurance: are the guardians of product quality. They are responsible for identifying and mitigating defects before the product reaches the end-users. Through various testing methodologies, QA engineers ensure the product meets all functional requirements, performance standards, and user expectations.</li>
<li>Operations Professionals: often including DevOps, focus on the deployment, monitoring, and maintenance of the product in production environments. They ensure that the product's infrastructure is robust, scalable, and secure. By facilitating continuous integration and delivery, they enable the team to release updates quickly and reliably.</li>
<li><strong>Business Analyst</strong>: Serves as the bridge between business objectives and technology solutions. They analyze market trends, assess business processes, and gather requirements to guide the team towards solutions that align with strategic goals. Their insights help prioritize features based on business value and customer impact.</li>
<li><strong>Data Analyst</strong>: Plays a crucial role in informing decision-making through data. They collect, process, and analyze data related to product performance, customer behavior, and market trends. By turning data into actionable insights, data analysts help the team understand user needs, measure product success, and identify areas for improvement.</li>
</ul>
<p>Incorporating these roles into a product team ensures a comprehensive approach to product development, where strategic vision, technical execution, user experience, quality assurance, operational stability, business alignment, and data-driven decision-making converge to create products that truly meet customer needs and drive business value.</p>
<p>These roles not always need to be different people, nevertheless they are skill that team members need to have or nurture. We could talk here about the T-shapped engineering concept but i am sure you can find deeper knowledge in  newsletter and other resources I have published on the past.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="understanding-vertical-slicing"><strong>Understanding Vertical Slicing</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/28/T03:00:00.000Z-Product%20teams:%20Aligning%20to%20Value#understanding-vertical-slicing" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to understanding-vertical-slicing" title="Direct link to understanding-vertical-slicing">​</a></h2>
<p>Vertical slicing refers to the process of breaking down functionalities and features into smaller, manageable pieces that can be developed, tested, and deployed independently. This method contrasts with the traditional horizontal slicing, where projects are divided among different departments or layers (e.g., backend, frontend, database). Implementing vertical slicing necessitates a cultural shift and strategic planning:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Redefine Team Composition</strong>: Transition from discipline-centric teams (e.g., a backend development team) to cross-functional teams that include members capable of handling all aspects of feature development, from UI design to database management.</li>
<li><strong>Adopt Customer-Centric Approaches</strong>: Align team objectives and features development with customer journeys and value delivery. Each slice should represent a step towards solving a customer problem or fulfilling a need.</li>
<li><strong>Foster a Collaborative Mindset</strong>: Encourage open communication and collaboration within and among product teams. This can be facilitated by regular stand-ups, shared goals, and common platforms for project management and documentation.</li>
<li><strong>Leverage Agile and DevOps Practices</strong>: Implement agile methodologies and DevOps practices to support the rapid development, testing, and deployment of vertical slices. Continuous integration and continuous deployment (CI/CD) pipelines are essential for automating these processes.</li>
<li><strong>Train and Mentor</strong>: Equip your teams with the necessary skills and knowledge to function effectively in this new environment. This might involve cross-training to ensure that team members can handle multiple aspects of development and operations or specific training in agile methodologies.</li>
<li><strong>Measure and Adapt</strong>: Establish metrics to measure the effectiveness of product teams and the impact of vertical slicing on product development. Use these insights to continuously improve processes and adapt strategies as needed.</li>
</ol>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="slicing-your-organization-into-product-teams">Slicing your organization into product teams<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/28/T03:00:00.000Z-Product%20teams:%20Aligning%20to%20Value#slicing-your-organization-into-product-teams" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Slicing your organization into product teams" title="Direct link to Slicing your organization into product teams">​</a></h2>
<p>Most companies will not be organized in this ways so its important to understand how to get there if its our objective. Initiating the transition towards product teams and vertical slicing involves several key steps:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Define the user journey:</strong> Understand the path your user takes when interacting with your product or service. This includes the initial contact, engagement, and long-term interaction. Understanding the user journey helps to identify gaps and opportunities in your product or service.</li>
<li><strong>Event storming of the value journey:</strong> This is a collaborative workflow of brainstorming and problem-solving using sticky notes to visualize the sequence of events in a user journey. This method helps to identify actions and interactions the user experiences.</li>
<li><strong>Map to existing products:</strong> Align the event storming with your existing products. This can provide insights into how well your products fit into the user journey and where improvements or new products might be needed.</li>
<li><strong>Reorganize ownerships:</strong> This involves adjusting team responsibilities to align with the user journey and product mapping. Teams should own certain steps of the user journey to ensure they are focused on delivering value at each stage.</li>
<li><strong>Re-architecture if necessary:</strong> If your current system architecture does not support the user journey and product mapping, consider a redesign. This could involve breaking down a monolithic system into microservices or adjusting your tech stack to better serve user needs.</li>
<li><strong>Support teams on mentality change:</strong> Transitioning to a user journey-focused approach with vertical slicing and product teams requires a shift in mindset. Support your teams through this change by providing training, fostering open communication, and promoting a culture of collaboration.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion"><strong>Conclusion</strong><a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/28/T03:00:00.000Z-Product%20teams:%20Aligning%20to%20Value#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to conclusion" title="Direct link to conclusion">​</a></h3>
<p>By embracing the concept of product teams and implementing vertical slicing within software departments, leaders can create environments that are more agile, innovative, and aligned with customer needs. This approach not only enhances the efficiency and quality of product development but also fosters a culture of collaboration and continuous improvement. As an engineering leader, steering your organization towards this paradigm will necessitate thoughtful planning, commitment, and adaptability, but the resulting advantages can profoundly transform your product development lifecycle.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beyond Clean Code & Architecture: Adapting Practices for Project Success]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/21/T03:00:00.000Z-Beyond Clean Code &amp; Architecture: Adapting Practices for Project Success</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/21/T03:00:00.000Z-Beyond Clean Code &amp; Architecture: Adapting Practices for Project Success"/>
        <updated>2024-03-21T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the critical examination of traditional coding practices like Clean Code and Clean Architecture. Understand the importance of aligning coding efforts with project and company goals, balancing innovation with discipline, and fostering a culture of critical thinking and adaptability to drive software project success.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Raise your hand 🖐️ if you recognize this meme:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe3101a1f-5287-4886-8246-89b64805fe64_1400x805.png" alt="https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe3101a1f-5287-4886-8246-89b64805fe64_1400x805.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Do you agree with it? I generally do. In today's fast-changing tech world, it's easy to get lost in the 'rules' of coding.</p>
<p>It's important that we occasionally stop and rethink our methods—not to reduce the importance of solid coding principles, but to make sure our efforts align with the broader goals of our projects and companies.</p>
<p>Leads Horizons is a reader-supported publication. To receive new posts and support my work, consider becoming a free or paid subscriber.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="avoiding-the-pitfalls-of-dogma--hype">Avoiding the Pitfalls of Dogma &amp; Hype<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/21/T03:00:00.000Z-Beyond%20Clean%20Code%20&amp;%20Architecture:%20Adapting%20Practices%20for%20Project%20Success#avoiding-the-pitfalls-of-dogma--hype" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Avoiding the Pitfalls of Dogma &amp; Hype" title="Direct link to Avoiding the Pitfalls of Dogma &amp; Hype">​</a></h2>
<p>Traditional coding practices are the foundation of software development projects. They ensure code readability, maintainability, and scalability. But blindly applying these practices, without considering the project's specific context, can lead to inefficiencies and waste.</p>
<p>For example, being too rigid with certain practices might slow down development in the early stages of a startup, where the ability to pivot quickly is key.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="a-real-world-example">A Real-World Example<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/21/T03:00:00.000Z-Beyond%20Clean%20Code%20&amp;%20Architecture:%20Adapting%20Practices%20for%20Project%20Success#a-real-world-example" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A Real-World Example" title="Direct link to A Real-World Example">​</a></h3>
<blockquote>
<p>Please take this as an example and not literal agains this specific pattern. I share as its what is fresh in my mind as I've experienced this in at least two workplaces over the last year.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We're currently seeing a lot of hype around Clean Architecture, which involves using the Ports &amp; Adapter Pattern. Well-known figures like Uncle Bob or Vaughn Vernon advocate for it, making it the center of attention.</p>
<p>In many organizations, every single project starts as a Ports &amp; Adapters project, focusing on business logic and separating it from external contact points. While the pattern can be valuable at a code level, we need to consider its drawbacks:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Starting up:</strong> Setting up a Ports &amp; Adapters project takes more initial time, potentially delaying the first release. It may not be the best fit for projects with tight deadlines or a priority on launching a minimum viable product quickly.</li>
<li><strong>Cognitive load:</strong> Ports &amp; Adapters can increase the cognitive load for developers, especially those unfamiliar with the pattern. It might require more training and time for developers to understand and use effectively, slowing down development.</li>
<li><strong>Over-engineering:</strong> The Ports &amp; Adapters pattern can lead to over-engineering, especially in simple projects where such a complex structure isn't needed. This could make the code more complicated and difficult to manage.</li>
<li><strong>Maintenance:</strong> The Ports &amp; Adapters pattern could add more maintenance work. If a project's scope isn't too complex, a simpler architecture might be easier to maintain and evolve over time.</li>
</ul>
<p>If you have unlimited time or budget, this might not be a concern. But that's not the reality for most new products. Especially in a fast-paced product development environment where you're trying to find product-market fit or experiment with user reactions, this could hinder your profitability.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F946c07cd-6ea9-4a42-b00a-9a99954c8fdc_1080x1080.png" alt="https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F946c07cd-6ea9-4a42-b00a-9a99954c8fdc_1080x1080.png" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="aligning-practices-with-goals">Aligning Practices with Goals<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/21/T03:00:00.000Z-Beyond%20Clean%20Code%20&amp;%20Architecture:%20Adapting%20Practices%20for%20Project%20Success#aligning-practices-with-goals" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Aligning Practices with Goals" title="Direct link to Aligning Practices with Goals">​</a></h2>
<p>Here are some things to consider to align coding practices with your project and company goals:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Assess the Project Lifecycle Phase:</strong> The needs of a nascent project are vastly different from those of a mature one. Early on, the focus might be on prototyping and rapid iteration. As the project matures, stability and scalability become more important.<!-- -->
<ol>
<li><strong>Proof of Concept</strong>: At this stage, you might prioritize speed over structure. The main goal is to validate your idea's feasibility, so it will be acceptable to take shortcuts in code quality and/or testing.</li>
<li><strong>Minimum Valuable Product</strong>: At this stage, the goal is to create a functional product with just enough features to satisfy early customers and provide feedback for future product development. Therefore, while it's important to strive for reusable code, speed and functionality might take precedence.</li>
<li><strong>Minimum Lovable Product</strong>: This stage focuses on improving the user experience, making the product more appealing and enjoyable. While maintaining the focus on functionality, you might prioritize refining the user interface, improving performance, or adding features that enhance user satisfaction.</li>
<li><strong>Production Quality Product</strong>: At this stage, the focus is on refining the product into a fully-fledged offering that can sustain long-term growth. You might prioritize code quality, extensive testing, and scalable architecture, as the product's stability and performance become increasingly critical.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><strong>Understand the Business Impact:</strong> Consider how the project directly impacts the business. Projects that are critical to revenue or customer experience might require more stringent practices, whereas internal tools might allow for more flexibility.<!-- -->
<ol>
<li><strong>Team Tools</strong>: For tools used by the engineering team, the balance might lean towards speed and functionality. These tools are often used to automate tasks or improve workflows, so they need to work efficiently. Code quality and maintainability can be slightly relaxed, as long as the tool's functionality and performance are not compromised.</li>
<li><strong>Internal Tools:</strong> These might include tools for other non-engineering departments. In these cases, the investment normally is not high so there is a need to balance functionality and code quality, maintainability, and scalability.</li>
<li><strong>Client Product:</strong> For products that directly touch the client, such as a mobile app or a web platform, the focus might lean heavily towards both functionality and user experience. It is crucial to ensure code quality, maintainability, and scalability to provide a smooth and reliable user experience.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li><strong>Assess Team Abilities:</strong> Your team's experience and skills are essential. Consider the potential learning curve when introducing new practices, patterns, or frameworks, as they may not yield the expected results.</li>
<li><strong>Balance Risk and Reward:</strong> Understand the risk profile of different decisions. For example, skipping peer review process might speed up deployment but increase the risk of bugs in production.</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="moving-forward">Moving Forward<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/21/T03:00:00.000Z-Beyond%20Clean%20Code%20&amp;%20Architecture:%20Adapting%20Practices%20for%20Project%20Success#moving-forward" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Moving Forward" title="Direct link to Moving Forward">​</a></h3>
<p>As leaders, we need to ensure that our teams aren't following practices just for compliance, but are actively contributing to our company’s objectives. We should foster an environment where questioning the status quo is welcomed, as long as it's with the intent of finding better, more aligned ways to work.</p>
<p>This doesn't mean lowering our standards, but rather adapting them intelligently to better serve our ultimate goals. It's about efficient and effective application, not complete abandonment or blind adherence. Balancing the discipline of coding standards with the flexibility needed to meet business objectives is an art that can greatly influence the success of software projects.</p>
<p>Let’s create a culture that values critical thinking and adaptability as much as coding excellence. By doing so, we not only align our coding practices with our project and company goals but also empower our teams to contribute their best work towards collective success.</p>
<p>Thank you for reading Leads Horizons. This post is public so feel free to share it.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.notion.so/alvarolorentedev/%25%share_url%25%25" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Share</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conway's Law: The Organizational Frame your Architecture will not escape from]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways Law: The Organizational Frame your Architecture will not escape from</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways Law: The Organizational Frame your Architecture will not escape from"/>
        <updated>2024-03-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover how to align your organizational structure with software architecture to meet user needs effectively, leveraging Conway's Law for enhanced product development.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever read Conway's law before:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Organizations which design systems are constrained to produce designs which are copies of the communication structures of these organizations.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>— Melvin E. Conway, How Do Committees Invent?</p>
<p>And considered how it relates to your experience upon entering a new organization and seeing its entire architecture? We will explore the different levels where Conway's law impacts and how to mitigate its effects if desired.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conways-law--alternatives">Conway's Law &amp; Alternatives<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#conways-law--alternatives" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conway's Law &amp; Alternatives" title="Direct link to Conway's Law &amp; Alternatives">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-status-quo-conways-law">The Status Quo (Conway's Law)<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#the-status-quo-conways-law" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Status Quo (Conway's Law)" title="Direct link to The Status Quo (Conway's Law)">​</a></h3>
<p>Conway's Law, proposed by Melvin Conway in <strong>1967</strong>, has withstood the test of time. It asserts that a system's design will mirror the structure of the organization that designed it. In other words, if a company has independent teams, the final product will likely consist of distinct components that function independently. Understanding this law can help organizations predict their system architecture based on their internal structure.</p>
<p>If we let Conway's law take the lead, regardless of our system design knowledge, the outcome may not meet our expectations, as we'll see in various layers where Conway's law can influence.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-other-side-inverse-conway-maneuver">The Other Side (Inverse Conway Maneuver)<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#the-other-side-inverse-conway-maneuver" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Other Side (Inverse Conway Maneuver)" title="Direct link to The Other Side (Inverse Conway Maneuver)">​</a></h3>
<p>The Inverse Conway Maneuver is a method of restructuring an organization to align better with the desired system architecture, which involves intentionally restructuring the organization to match the desired system architecture. This process can be challenging and disruptive, but it can lead to a more efficient and effective organization.</p>
<p>Key steps to successfully implementing the Inverse Conway Maneuver include:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Define the desired system architecture.</strong>&nbsp;This should align with the organization's goals and objectives.</li>
<li><strong>Analyze the current organizational structure.</strong>&nbsp;Identify where the current structure does not align with the desired system architecture.</li>
<li><strong>Develop a restructuring plan.</strong>&nbsp;This plan should include a timeline and a communication strategy.</li>
<li><strong>Implement the plan.</strong>&nbsp;This should be done in phases to minimize disruption.</li>
<li><strong>Monitor the results.</strong>&nbsp;Track the restructuring progress and make adjustments as needed.</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="middle-ground-user-centric-conway-maneuver">Middle Ground (User-Centric Conway Maneuver)<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#middle-ground-user-centric-conway-maneuver" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Middle Ground (User-Centric Conway Maneuver)" title="Direct link to Middle Ground (User-Centric Conway Maneuver)">​</a></h3>
<p>Conventionally, profitable software is based on user needs. Many organizations claim to be user-centric but fail to organize around them. User-centric Conway Maneuver involves focusing on our client's process and needs, which will impact the organizational structure and systems architecture.</p>
<p>Key steps to successfully implementing the User-Centric Conway Maneuver include:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Understand your Target User.</strong>&nbsp;This should align with the organization's goals and objectives.</li>
<li><strong>Analyze the current organizational structure.</strong>&nbsp;Identify where the current structure does not align with the desired system architecture.</li>
<li><strong>Analyze the current architecture.</strong>&nbsp;Identify where the current structure does not align with the desired system architecture.</li>
<li><strong>Develop a restructuring plan.</strong>&nbsp;This plan should include a timeline and a communication strategy.</li>
<li><strong>Implement the plan.</strong>&nbsp;This should be done in phases to minimize disruption.</li>
<li><strong>Monitor the results.</strong>&nbsp;Track the restructuring progress and make adjustments as needed.</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>⚠️ Note that any transformation is complex and challenging and should only be undertaken with careful planning and execution.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="layers-of-influence">Layers of Influence<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#layers-of-influence" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Layers of Influence" title="Direct link to Layers of Influence">​</a></h2>
<p>Conway's Law is not just about high-level architecture; it influences various facets of system design and team collaboration. Here, we detail the layers where Conway's law manifests:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="global-architecture">Global Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#global-architecture" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Global Architecture" title="Direct link to Global Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>At the Global Architecture level, Conway's Law suggests that the technical and non-technical organization definitions can affect your high-level architecture. Let's look at some examples:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Non-technical departments:</strong> In a company with separate marketing and operations departments, the marketing department is likely the primary stakeholder for systems related to the customer funnel, while the operations department is likely the primary stakeholder for systems related to customer care. If there is no communication between departments, your company might make promises it can't keep, or provide a poor customer experience.</li>
<li><strong>Technical departments:</strong> In a company with technical organizational departments where horizontals exist, your teams will reflect that structure. If not careful, you might implement very similar functionalities or overwhelm other teams with too many requirements.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="product-architecture">Product Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#product-architecture" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Product Architecture" title="Direct link to Product Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>In the context of a User-Centric Conway Maneuver, the product architecture level requires you to focus on how the various teams collaborate to deliver a product that fulfills user needs. You need to assess how the teams are structured and how their communication patterns align with the user journey you have defined.</p>
<p>For instance, if you have separate teams for front-end and back-end development, you may need to foster better communication and collaboration between these teams to ensure that your product provides a seamless user experience. This could involve regular cross-team meetings, joint planning sessions, or even restructuring teams to be cross-functional.</p>
<p>Your architecture may have to evolve to support this more integrated approach. For example, you may decide to use a full-stack development approach where each team is responsible for both front-end and back-end development for a certain part of the user journey. This can lead to a product architecture that is more aligned with the user's needs and can adapt more quickly to changes in those needs.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="code-architecture">Code Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#code-architecture" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Code Architecture" title="Direct link to Code Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>At the code level, the User-Centric Conway Maneuver involves considering how the communication and collaboration styles of individual team members can influence the design of system components. This is where the understanding of your target user and their journey can guide the design of individual features or components.</p>
<p>If a developer tends to work in isolation on a feature, this could result in a component that does not integrate well with the rest of the system or does not meet user needs effectively. To address this, you may need to encourage more collaboration and communication within your team.</p>
<p>For instance, you could use pair programming or code reviews to ensure that all team members have input into feature development. This can lead to code architecture that is more cohesive and adaptable, and that better reflects the needs of the user.</p>
<p>Remember, these are just examples, and your actual actions will depend on the specific needs and structure of your organization.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="user-centric-conway-maneuver-action-plan">User-Centric Conway Maneuver Action Plan<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#user-centric-conway-maneuver-action-plan" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to User-Centric Conway Maneuver Action Plan" title="Direct link to User-Centric Conway Maneuver Action Plan">​</a></h2>
<p>You should now be aware that Conway's law can impact your organization unconsciously. Based on our multi-layered view, let's focus on the user-centric Conway maneuver:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="global-architecture-1">Global Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#global-architecture-1" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Global Architecture" title="Direct link to Global Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>In this layer, you need to know what your business value is for your users to align to it, as it will likely change the least after you achieve a product-market fit. This knowledge can fuel your organizational and architectural changes. The knowledge required is not technical, but you should at least have defined your target user and their journey.</p>
<p>After defining these models, we will understand the business better, and we can map some new knowledge to reorganize and re-architect. Some possible actions from the examples we saw in the previous section:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reorganize Non-technical departments:</strong> If there is no communication between marketing and operations, they need to work closer. This could involve having weekly syncs or a common leadership/organization, so their objectives are aligned.</li>
<li><strong>Technical departments:</strong> In the case of horizontal slicing, moving to a more user-centric environment could reorganize teams to be multifunctional and value stream aligned.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="product-architecture-1">Product Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#product-architecture-1" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Product Architecture" title="Direct link to Product Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>In the context of a User-Centric Conway Maneuver, the product architecture level requires a focus on how the various teams collaborate to deliver a product that fulfills user needs. This could involve regular cross-team meetings, joint planning sessions, or even restructuring teams to be more cross-functional.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="code-architecture-1">Code Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#code-architecture-1" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Code Architecture" title="Direct link to Code Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>At the code level, the User-Centric Conway Maneuver involves considering how the communication and collaboration styles of individual team members can influence the design of system components. This is where understanding of your target user and their journey can guide the design of individual features or components.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T00:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>In conclusion, Conway's Law provides valuable insight into how an organization's structure can impact the design of its systems. While the experience and skill of your hires certainly contribute to the quality of work, the architecture of the systems you develop will be significantly influenced by your organizational communication patterns. Hence, you will have to apply the maneuver or none depending on if you accept, mitigate, or want to pivot on the tradeoffs.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conway's Law: The Organizational Frame your Architecture will not escape from]]></title>
        <id>https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways Law: The Organizational Frame your Architecture will not escape from</id>
        <link href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways Law: The Organizational Frame your Architecture will not escape from"/>
        <updated>2024-03-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover how to align your organizational structure with software architecture to meet user needs effectively, leveraging Conway's Law for enhanced product development.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever read Conway's law before:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Organizations which design systems are constrained to produce designs which are copies of the communication structures of these organizations.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>— Melvin E. Conway, How Do Committees Invent?</p>
<p>And considered how it relates to your experience upon entering a new organization and seeing its entire architecture? We will explore the different levels where Conway's law impacts and how to mitigate its effects if desired.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conways-law--alternatives">Conway's Law &amp; Alternatives<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#conways-law--alternatives" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conway's Law &amp; Alternatives" title="Direct link to Conway's Law &amp; Alternatives">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-status-quo-conways-law">The Status Quo (Conway's Law)<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#the-status-quo-conways-law" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Status Quo (Conway's Law)" title="Direct link to The Status Quo (Conway's Law)">​</a></h3>
<p>Conway's Law, proposed by Melvin Conway in <strong>1967</strong>, has withstood the test of time. It asserts that a system's design will mirror the structure of the organization that designed it. In other words, if a company has independent teams, the final product will likely consist of distinct components that function independently. Understanding this law can help organizations predict their system architecture based on their internal structure.</p>
<p>If we let Conway's law take the lead, regardless of our system design knowledge, the outcome may not meet our expectations, as we'll see in various layers where Conway's law can influence.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-other-side-inverse-conway-maneuver">The Other Side (Inverse Conway Maneuver)<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#the-other-side-inverse-conway-maneuver" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Other Side (Inverse Conway Maneuver)" title="Direct link to The Other Side (Inverse Conway Maneuver)">​</a></h3>
<p>The Inverse Conway Maneuver is a method of restructuring an organization to align better with the desired system architecture, which involves intentionally restructuring the organization to match the desired system architecture. This process can be challenging and disruptive, but it can lead to a more efficient and effective organization.</p>
<p>Key steps to successfully implementing the Inverse Conway Maneuver include:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Define the desired system architecture.</strong>&nbsp;This should align with the organization's goals and objectives.</li>
<li><strong>Analyze the current organizational structure.</strong>&nbsp;Identify where the current structure does not align with the desired system architecture.</li>
<li><strong>Develop a restructuring plan.</strong>&nbsp;This plan should include a timeline and a communication strategy.</li>
<li><strong>Implement the plan.</strong>&nbsp;This should be done in phases to minimize disruption.</li>
<li><strong>Monitor the results.</strong>&nbsp;Track the restructuring progress and make adjustments as needed.</li>
</ol>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="middle-ground-user-centric-conway-maneuver">Middle Ground (User-Centric Conway Maneuver)<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#middle-ground-user-centric-conway-maneuver" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Middle Ground (User-Centric Conway Maneuver)" title="Direct link to Middle Ground (User-Centric Conway Maneuver)">​</a></h3>
<p>Conventionally, profitable software is based on user needs. Many organizations claim to be user-centric but fail to organize around them. User-centric Conway Maneuver involves focusing on our client's process and needs, which will impact the organizational structure and systems architecture.</p>
<p>Key steps to successfully implementing the User-Centric Conway Maneuver include:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Understand your Target User.</strong>&nbsp;This should align with the organization's goals and objectives.</li>
<li><strong>Analyze the current organizational structure.</strong>&nbsp;Identify where the current structure does not align with the desired system architecture.</li>
<li><strong>Analyze the current architecture.</strong>&nbsp;Identify where the current structure does not align with the desired system architecture.</li>
<li><strong>Develop a restructuring plan.</strong>&nbsp;This plan should include a timeline and a communication strategy.</li>
<li><strong>Implement the plan.</strong>&nbsp;This should be done in phases to minimize disruption.</li>
<li><strong>Monitor the results.</strong>&nbsp;Track the restructuring progress and make adjustments as needed.</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>⚠️ Note that any transformation is complex and challenging and should only be undertaken with careful planning and execution.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="layers-of-influence">Layers of Influence<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#layers-of-influence" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Layers of Influence" title="Direct link to Layers of Influence">​</a></h2>
<p>Conway's Law is not just about high-level architecture; it influences various facets of system design and team collaboration. Here, we detail the layers where Conway's law manifests:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="global-architecture">Global Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#global-architecture" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Global Architecture" title="Direct link to Global Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>At the Global Architecture level, Conway's Law suggests that the technical and non-technical organization definitions can affect your high-level architecture. Let's look at some examples:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Non-technical departments:</strong> In a company with separate marketing and operations departments, the marketing department is likely the primary stakeholder for systems related to the customer funnel, while the operations department is likely the primary stakeholder for systems related to customer care. If there is no communication between departments, your company might make promises it can't keep, or provide a poor customer experience.</li>
<li><strong>Technical departments:</strong> In a company with technical organizational departments where horizontals exist, your teams will reflect that structure. If not careful, you might implement very similar functionalities or overwhelm other teams with too many requirements.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="product-architecture">Product Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#product-architecture" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Product Architecture" title="Direct link to Product Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>In the context of a User-Centric Conway Maneuver, the product architecture level requires you to focus on how the various teams collaborate to deliver a product that fulfills user needs. You need to assess how the teams are structured and how their communication patterns align with the user journey you have defined.</p>
<p>For instance, if you have separate teams for front-end and back-end development, you may need to foster better communication and collaboration between these teams to ensure that your product provides a seamless user experience. This could involve regular cross-team meetings, joint planning sessions, or even restructuring teams to be cross-functional.</p>
<p>Your architecture may have to evolve to support this more integrated approach. For example, you may decide to use a full-stack development approach where each team is responsible for both front-end and back-end development for a certain part of the user journey. This can lead to a product architecture that is more aligned with the user's needs and can adapt more quickly to changes in those needs.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="code-architecture">Code Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#code-architecture" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Code Architecture" title="Direct link to Code Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>At the code level, the User-Centric Conway Maneuver involves considering how the communication and collaboration styles of individual team members can influence the design of system components. This is where the understanding of your target user and their journey can guide the design of individual features or components.</p>
<p>If a developer tends to work in isolation on a feature, this could result in a component that does not integrate well with the rest of the system or does not meet user needs effectively. To address this, you may need to encourage more collaboration and communication within your team.</p>
<p>For instance, you could use pair programming or code reviews to ensure that all team members have input into feature development. This can lead to code architecture that is more cohesive and adaptable, and that better reflects the needs of the user.</p>
<p>Remember, these are just examples, and your actual actions will depend on the specific needs and structure of your organization.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="user-centric-conway-maneuver-action-plan">User-Centric Conway Maneuver Action Plan<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#user-centric-conway-maneuver-action-plan" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to User-Centric Conway Maneuver Action Plan" title="Direct link to User-Centric Conway Maneuver Action Plan">​</a></h2>
<p>You should now be aware that Conway's law can impact your organization unconsciously. Based on our multi-layered view, let's focus on the user-centric Conway maneuver:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="global-architecture-1">Global Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#global-architecture-1" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Global Architecture" title="Direct link to Global Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>In this layer, you need to know what your business value is for your users to align to it, as it will likely change the least after you achieve a product-market fit. This knowledge can fuel your organizational and architectural changes. The knowledge required is not technical, but you should at least have defined your target user and their journey.</p>
<p>After defining these models, we will understand the business better, and we can map some new knowledge to reorganize and re-architect. Some possible actions from the examples we saw in the previous section:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Reorganize Non-technical departments:</strong> If there is no communication between marketing and operations, they need to work closer. This could involve having weekly syncs or a common leadership/organization, so their objectives are aligned.</li>
<li><strong>Technical departments:</strong> In the case of horizontal slicing, moving to a more user-centric environment could reorganize teams to be multifunctional and value stream aligned.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="product-architecture-1">Product Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#product-architecture-1" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Product Architecture" title="Direct link to Product Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>In the context of a User-Centric Conway Maneuver, the product architecture level requires a focus on how the various teams collaborate to deliver a product that fulfills user needs. This could involve regular cross-team meetings, joint planning sessions, or even restructuring teams to be more cross-functional.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="code-architecture-1">Code Architecture<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#code-architecture-1" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Code Architecture" title="Direct link to Code Architecture">​</a></h3>
<p>At the code level, the User-Centric Conway Maneuver involves considering how the communication and collaboration styles of individual team members can influence the design of system components. This is where understanding of your target user and their journey can guide the design of individual features or components.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="https://alvarolorente.dev/blog/2024/03/14/T03:00:00.000Z-Conways%20Law:%20The%20Organizational%20Frame%20your%20Architecture%20will%20not%20escape%20from#conclusion" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Conclusion" title="Direct link to Conclusion">​</a></h2>
<p>In conclusion, Conway's Law provides valuable insight into how an organization's structure can impact the design of its systems. While the experience and skill of your hires certainly contribute to the quality of work, the architecture of the systems you develop will be significantly influenced by your organizational communication patterns. Hence, you will have to apply the maneuver or none depending on if you accept, mitigate, or want to pivot on the tradeoffs.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Alvaro Jose</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/alvarolorentedev</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>